Preface to the Second Edition

After the lapse of upwards of thirty years I have to write a preface to a second edition of a work which has long been out of print. This is in some respects a trying task. Those who were my fellow labourers and assistants in collecting the materials for the original work, so long ago as the year 1845, are now nearly all dead. Some of them, to whom I was much attached, and on whose fidelity I placed the greatest reliance, led astray by designing men, joined in a native war against the Europeans, and perished, many of them on the field of battle; others from that want and those diseases which invariably accompany war. Others, again, surviving such disasters, died from old age or sickness, in a state of obstinate and resolute isolation from the Europeans, under a native king, in the mountainous fastnesses of the interior of the North Island.

Others, and not a small number of my native friends, remained true to their religious faith, and to their promises. Nearly all of these have gradually died off from natural causes—many of them much respected and admired. European hands and European regard have raised monuments to some of them—monuments which testify not only to native worth, but also to British admiration for nobility of character and purpose, wherever these qualities may be found.

Such, indeed, has been, upon the whole, the feeling between the two races during and since the cessation of the war to which I am alluding, that the Europeans thoroughly appreciated all instances of truly noble courage in the natives who were opposed to them, and loudly expressed their admiration for the men who thus distinguished themselves.

Even upon a recent occasion, when it was proposed to interfere, in an undesirable way, with a piece of land, which, in the eyes of all, was almost sanctified by an act of invincible and heroic courage on the part of a small body of hostile natives, the House of Representatives, composed of ninety-one European and four native members, insisted that the piece of land and its vicinity should be forever reserved as public ground, dedicated to the remembrance of the heroic deed of which it had been the theatre.

A generous conquering race thus preserved a record not of its own triumphs, but of an act of unconquerable courage upon the part of its adversaries, who fell before superior numbers and weapons—an act which the future inhabitants of New Zealand will strive to imitate, but can never surpass.[1]

However, wars and years have swept off nearly all those grand old chiefs who were my associates in many great trials, and for whom I felt and still cherish a deep regard. I desired to preserve, and they aided me in preserving, a memento of a noble race, in its original state when first discovered. No complete record of such a nation in its savage state-exists, and yet such a record, complete and perfect, is required to clear up many important points in the history of mankind.

There are also peculiar circumstances connected with the New Zealanders which render such a record peculiarly desirable in their case. They were probably the most remote of the Polynesian race, from the point from which that people came in their emigration to the islands of the Pacific. They therefore were most likely sprung from those who first separated from the parent stock, whose descendants in successive generations would probably have always kept continually in front in the line of successively advancing emigrations.

Again, in so far as our knowledge goes, it appears probable that no other people with whom we are acquainted, had been for so long a time shut off from all communication with exterior nations as the New Zealanders had been when first visited by Europeans. If these suppositions are granted, we ought to expect to find the Polynesian language, religion, legends, and customs all preserved in New Zealand in their most unadulterated form.

When the first edition of this work was published in 1855, I had no true idea of the number of New Zealand printed books and manuscripts which I had collected in pursuit of the task I had undertaken. In 1858 they were, however, all carefully arranged and catalogued, when it appeared that the collection contained 301 printed volumes, nearly all in the Māori language, and 223 manuscripts, and that the latter documents contained 10,090 pages. The tabulated form which follows, taken from the cata logue of Māori books which was published at Cape Town in 1858, shows the size of the various books and manuscripts, which are deposited in the library at that place.

Description of Books, Māori Language. I. Publications. | Books. | Leaves.
Folio | 132 | 264
Quarto | 17 | 308
Octavo | 79 | 4,737
Duodecimo | 57 | 1,956
Sedecimo and smaller | 16 | 906
Total of Publications | 301 | 8,171
II. Manuscripts. | — | —
Folio | 174 | 3,564
Quarto | 44 | 990
Octavo | 5 | 491
Total of Manuscripts | 223 | 5,045
Total of Māori Books | 524 | 13,216

It is very desirable that the portion of the Cape of Good Hope catalogue which relates to New Zealand should be republished in this country. It consists of only 76 pages, and contains a description of the contents of each printed work and of each manuscript.

Many of the manuscripts were written by natives from the dictation of the most celebrated old chiefs, such as Rangihaeata, Te Rauparaha, Pōtatau, Te Heuheu, Patuone, Te Taniwha, etc. Those that I took down from the dictation of the great chiefs, were all carefully gone over and corrected by natives who could read and write. The chiefs who supplied the various religious services, poems, legends, and histories, including the wars and events which had taken place during their own lives, were as anxious as I was, that a complete picture of the Māori race in its original state should be preserved and handed down to posterity, and they cheerfully and eagerly aided me in the work. In many cases I told them exactly what I wanted, supplied them with the requisite writing materials, and some months afterwards received a valuable manuscript which had been dictated to an educated native. Probably no such collection of materials for illustrating the history of a barbarous race has ever before been made. The labour undergone in its collection was great.

Another reason why this Cape catalogue should be republished in New Zealand (it has been long out of print) is, that it contains a minute account of the information supplied to me by each individual, which was embodied in the first edition of the Māori legends. When two or more individuals, European or native, supplied the same portion of a legend the manuscript furnished by each was catalogued, so that the aid rendered by each individual was recorded, although it was not made use of, except as a confirmation of that which had been previously supplied.

I find from the Cape of Good Hope catalogue of manuscripts, that the following European gentlemen gave me the undermentioned papers connected with Māori poetry and legends.

J. White, Esq.—A manuscript of 215 pages of various songs, proverbs, and customs, all relating to the tribes of Hokianga, which were collected by Mr. White and by him prevented to Sir G. Grey.

A manuscript of two pages, being a translation by Mr. White of the Tale of the Two Dwarfs.

Neither of these manuscripts has been published. They are bound up in Vol. 146 of Māori works in the Cape Library. They are of value, not only from their intrinsic worth, but as illustrating the Ngāpuhi dialect. Copies of them should be obtained for New Zealand.

The Present Bishop Of Wellington.—Manuscript, being an original paper on the System of Government amongst the New Zealand Tribes in their Savage state, written in 1846 by the Rev. Octavius Hadfield, 23 pages. A very valuable manuscript for Native history. A copy ought to be procured from the Cape of Good Hope for the purpose of publication in New Zealand.

Manuscript, being an original paper by the Rev. Octavius Hadfield, written in 1846, on the relations then existing between the British and the Native Tribes of New Zealand, 68 pages. Both of these MSS. are bound up in the 147th Vol. of Māori works.

Sir Wm. Martin.—Manuscript, The Legend of Pāoa, written by Wm. Hoeti.

Manuscript, Explanations of various expressions in Native Poems as given by Natives, in the handwriting of Sir Wm. Martin, so eminent for his knowledge of the Natives, their language, and customs. This valuable manuscript is bound up in the 151st Vol. of Māori works. A copy ought to be procured from the Cape, and published for the use of students. It consists of twelve pages.

Archdeacon Maunsell.—Manuscript, a treatise by the Rev. R. Maunsell on the Poetry of the New Zealanders, illustrated by examples of various songs. Bound up in Vol. 152 of New Zealand works. A copy of this ought to be procured from the Cape for the use of students. The name of the author shows its value.

The Rev. J. F. H. Wholers, a German missionary who resided in Foveaux Straits, and at Ruapuke (Island).—Manuscript of nine pages, containing Six Legends of the Tribes inhabiting Foveaux Straits, with translations. Very valuable as containing the dialect spoken in the extreme south of New Zealand. Bound up in Vol. 151 of New Zealand works. Mr. Wholers has recently died. He was not only an amiable and excellent missionary, but a man of superior attainments. He published some Māori legends with English translations in the 7th Vol. Transactions New Zealand Institute, 1875. Pp. 3–53.

The foregoing list of contributions to my task, afforded by European friends, will show how very large my obligations were to the Māori chiefs for the assistance which they afforded me. This is perhaps as it should be. The legends, poems, and histories are Māori—as they recognised them, and supplied them. One instance that occurs to my recollection is this. Attracted by the beauty of the spot, I determined to pass a morning on the island of Mokoia.[2] I proceeded there in a canoe with some friends and two or three natives. Wandering about, I grew weary, and was tempted at last to sit down at the edge of a beautiful warm spring, close to the margin of Lake Rotorua, in which lake the island of Mokoia stands. After a time a native chief came up to me, and knowing my fondness for legends, he told me the beautiful legend of his ancestress Hinemoa, who had landed on the spot where we sat. I was charmed with the tale, made him repeat it, and at once wrote it down in my notebook. I crossed over again to Te Ngae, the mission station on the mainland, in the afternoon, and repeated the legend to my old friend, Mr. Chapman, the missionary. He said, “It is strange, I have lived here for a good many years, and they never told me this.” I could not help smiling, and told him they could never have imagined that a missionary would have cared about such a thing. But he went out at once to ask some of his native converts about the matter, and returned quite pleased to think that he lived near so interesting a spot.

The discovery of this legend, on December 26, 1849, created a strong sensation of pleasure in many minds in New Zealand. It was not then known, and at first could hardly be believed, that tales, containing so much of romance and poetic beauty, existed in New Zealand. I shall never forget the pleasure with which my valued friend Domett first heard it, and long will live the magnificent poem, “Ranolf and Amohia,” into which his genius has expanded the legend, so fortuitously acquired.

The foregoing list of Māori manuscripts taken from the Cape of Good Hope catalogue will show how largely the Cape Library is endowed with New Zealand native literature of extraordinary value. Since the establishment of that Library I have made another collection of New Zealand manuscript literature for the Auckland Public Library. This latter is as yet unarranged, and no catalogue of it has been made. It is, however, extensive and valuable. But in the Auckland Library will also be found a considerable collection of manuscript South African literature, which would be of great value to the Cape Library. I must thus seem to have made an injudicious arrangement regarding the place of deposit of great historical treasures.

A man employed in the service of a great and extensive Empire can, however, never perfectly adjust or arrange his entire life. He can neither at any given moment estimate the time he may live, nor can he know in what part of the world he may in a few months find himself. Thus ignorant of his own fate, he is equally I ignorant of that of each of his associates. An arrangement he may deem wise and prudent may turn out, if he lives to a considerable age, not to have been the wisest he could have made, if it was in his power to have foretold the future. When I made arrangements for giving a Library to the Cape of Good Hope, I believed, if I lived so long, that I was likely to have resided at the Cape for a few years. My friend Dr. Bleek, one of the greatest of living philologists, was then resident at Cape Town. He was a good Māori scholar. We were in the habit of working together, and I hoped that we should have worked out and published a great part of the New Zealand literature which was deposited at the Cape. I soon had to leave the Cape, have never returned there, and my friend Dr. Bleek, many years younger than myself, is dead. Perhaps still advantages may be derived from the arrangement which was made. The learned of the Cape of Good Hope and of New Zealand must, in time, be driven into frequent and intimate correspondence regarding the sources of information which the two countries mutually possess of their early history, and of the native populations which inhabited each of two such important portions of the world. From such correspondence and literary intimacy great mutual advantages may arise to each of these two places. Ultimately, I have no doubt also, that frequent exchanges of literary treasures will take place between them, and that they will thus, each of them by relinquishing something, gradually acquire those manuscripts which, in their respective estimations, they think it most desirable that each country should possess. If in any respect either of them may feel disappointed, they will, I know, readily pardon a man whose sole desire was to benefit each of them, according to the best of his ability and knowledge at the moment he formed his decision.

I am indebted to my friend, Dr. Edward Shortland, an eminent Māori scholar, for having corrected for the press the native part of this volume, with the exception of about the first fifty or sixty pages. The students of the Māori language, in studying that portion of this work, will find their labour greatly lightened from the ability and care with which this has been done.

G. Grey.

Kawau, Oct. 6th, 1885.

The Children of Heaven and Earth

Ko Ngā Tama A Rangi

Tradition Relating To The Origin Of The Human Race

Men had but one pair of primitive ancestors; they sprang from the vast heaven that exists above us, and from earth which lies beneath us. According to the traditions of our race, Rangi and Papa, or Heaven and Earth, were the source from which, in the beginning, all things originated. Darkness then rested upon the heaven and upon the earth, and they still both clave together, for they had not yet been rent apart; and the children they had begotten were ever thinking amongst themselves what might be the difference between darkness and light; they knew that beings had multiplied and increased, and yet light had never broken upon them, but it ever continued dark. Hence these sayings are found in our ancient religious services: “There was darkness from the first division of time, unto the tenth, to the hundredth, to the thousandth,” that is, for a vast space of time; and these divisions of times were considered as beings, and were each termed a Po; and on their account there was yet no world with its bright light, but darkness only for the beings which existed.

At last the beings who had been begotten by Heaven and Earth, worn out by the continued darkness, consulted amongst themselves, saying, “Let us now determine what we should do with Rangi and Papa, whether it would be better to slay them or to rend them apart.” Then spoke Tūmatauenga, the fiercest of the children of Heaven and Earth, “It is well, let us slay them.”

Then spake Tānemahuta, the father of forests and of all things that inhabit them, or that are constructed of trees, “Nay, not so. It is better to rend them apart, and to let the heaven stand far above us, and the earth lie beneath our feet. Let the sky become as a stranger to us, but the earth remain close to us as a nursing mother.”

The brothers all consented to this proposal, with the exception of Tāwhirimātea, the father of winds and storms, and he, fearing that his kingdom was about to be overthrown, grieved greatly at the thought of his parents being torn apart. Five of the brothers willingly consented to the separation of their parents, but one of them would not consent to it.

Hence, also, these sayings of old are found in our prayers, “Darkness, darkness, light, light, the seeking, the searching, in chaos, in chaos;” these signified the way in which the offspring of heaven and earth sought for some mode of dealing with their parents, so that human beings might increase and live.

So, also, these sayings of old time, “The multitude, the length,” signified the multitude of the thoughts of the children of Heaven and Earth, and the length of time they considered whether they should slay their parents, that human beings might be called into existence; for it was in this manner that they talked and consulted amongst themselves.

But at length their plans having been agreed on, lo, Rongomātāne, the god and father of the cultivated food of man, rises up, that he may rend apart the heavens and the earth; he struggles, but he rends them not apart. Lo, next, Tangaroa, the god and father of fish and reptiles, rises up, that he may rend apart the heavens and the earth; he also struggles, but he rends them not apart. Lo, next, Haumia-tikitiki, the god and father of the food of man which springs without cultivation, rises up and struggles, but ineffectually. Lo, then, Tūmatauenga, the god and father of fierce human beings, rises up and struggles, but he, too, fails in his efforts. Then, at last, slowly uprises Tānemahuta, the god and father of forests, of birds, and of insects, and he struggles with his parents; in vain he strives to rend them apart with his hands and arms. Lo, he pauses; his head is now firmly planted on his mother the earth, his feet he raises up and rests against his father the skies, he strains his back and limbs with mighty effort. Now are rent apart Rangi and Papa, and with cries and groans of woe they shriek aloud, “Wherefore slay you thus your parents? Why commit you so dreadful a crime as to slay us, as to rend your parents apart?” But Tānemahuta pauses not, he regards not their shrieks and cries; far, far beneath him he presses down the earth; far, far above him he thrust up the sky.

Hence these sayings of olden time, “It was the fierce thrusting of Tāne which tore the heaven from the earth, so that they were rent apart, and darkness was made manifest, and so was the light.”

No sooner was heaven rent from earth than the multitude of human beings were discovered whom they had begotten, and who had hitherto lain concealed between the bodies of Rangi and Papa.

Then, also, there arose in the breast of Tāwhirimātea, the god and father of winds and storms, a fierce desire to wage war with his brothers, because they had rent apart their common parents. He from the first had refused to consent to his mother being torn from her lord and children; it was his brothers alone that wished for this separation, and desired that Papatūānuku, or the Earth alone, should be left as a parent to them.

The god of hurricanes and storms dreads also that the world should become too fair and beautiful, so he rises, follows his father to the realms above, and hurries to the sheltered hollows in the boundless skies; there he hides and clings, and nestling in this place of rest he consults long with his parent, and as the vast Heaven listens to the suggestions of Tāwhirimātea, thoughts and plans are formed in his breast, and Tāwhirimātea also understands what he should do. Then by himself and the vast Heaven were begotten his numerous brood, and they rapidly increased and grew. Tāwhirimātea despatches one of them to the westward, and one to the southward, and one to the eastward, and one to the northward; and he gives corresponding names to himself and to his progeny the mighty winds.

He next sends forth fierce squalls, whirlwinds, dense clouds, massy clouds, dark clouds, gloomy thick clouds, fiery clouds, clouds which precede hurricanes, clouds of fiery black, clouds reflecting glowing red light, clouds wildly drifting from all quarters and wildly bursting, clouds of thunder storms, and clouds hurriedly flying. In the midst of these Tāwhirimātea himself sweeps wildly on. Alas! alas! then rages the fierce hurricane; and whilst Tānemahuta and his gigantic forests still stand, unconscious and unsuspecting, the blast of the breath of the mouth of Tāwhirimātea smites them, the gigantic trees are snapt off right in the middle; alas! alas! they are rent to atoms, dashed to the earth, with boughs and branches torn and scattered, and lying on the earth, trees and branches all alike left for the insect, for the grub, and for loathsome rottenness.

From the forests and their inhabitants Tāwhirimātea next swoops down upon the seas, and lashes in his wrath the ocean. Ah! ah! waves steep as cliffs arise, whose summits are so lofty that to look from them would make the beholder giddy; these soon eddy in whirlpools, and Tangaroa, the god of the ocean, and father of all that dwell therein, flies affrighted through his seas; but before he fled, his children consulted together how they might secure their safety, for Tangaroa had begotten Punga, and he had begotten two children, Ikatere, the father of fish, and Tū-te-wehiwehi, or Tū-te-wanawana, the father of reptiles.

When Tangaroa fled for safety to the ocean, then Tū-te-wehiwehi and Ikatere, and their children, disputed together as to what they should do to escape from the storms, and Tū-te-wehiwehi and his party cried aloud, “Let us fly inland;” but Ikatere and his party cried aloud, “Let us fly to the sea.” Some would not obey one order, some would not obey the other, and they escaped in two parties: the party of Tū-te-wehiwehi, or the reptiles, hid themselves ashore; the party of Puuga rushed to the sea. This is what, in our ancient religious services, is called the separation of Ta-whiri-ma-tea. Hence these traditions have been handed down:—“Ikatere, the father of things which inhabit the water, cried aloud to Tū-te-wehiwehi, ‘Ho, ho, let us all escape to the sea.’

“But Tū-te-wehiwehi shouted in answer, ‘Nay, nay, let us rather fly inland.’

“Then Ikatere warned him, saying, ‘Fly inland, then; and the fate of you and your race will be, that when they catch you, before you are cooked, they will singe off your scales over a lighted wisp of dry fern.’

“But Tū-te-wehiwehi answered him, saying, ‘Seek safety, then, in the sea; and the future fate of your race will be, that when they serve out little baskets of cooked vegetable food to each person, you will be laid upon the top of the food to give a relish to it.’

“Then without delay these two races of beings separated. The fish fled in confusion to the sea, the reptiles sought safety in the forests and scrubs.”

Tangaroa, enraged at some of his children deserting him, and, being sheltered by the god of the forests on dry land, has ever since waged war on his brother Tāne, who, in return, has waged war against him.

Hence, Tāne supplies the offspring of his brother Tūmatauenga with canoes, with spears and with fishhooks made from his trees, and with nets woven from his fibrous plants, that they may destroy the offspring of Tangaroa; whilst Tangaroa, in return, swallows up the offspring of Tāne, overwhelming canoes with the surges of his sea, swallowing up the lands, trees, and houses that are swept off by floods, and ever wastes away, with his lapping waves, the shores that confine him, that the giants of the forests may be washed down and swept out into his boundless ocean, that he may then swallow up the insects, the young birds and the various animals which inhabit them—all which things are recorded in the prayers which were offered to these gods.

Tāwhirimātea next rushed on to attack his brothers Rongomātāne and Haumia-tikitiki, the gods and progenitors of cultivated and uncultivated food; but Papa, to save these for her other children, caught them up, and hid them in a place of safety; and so well were these children of hers concealed by their mother Earth, that Tāwhirimātea sought for them in vain.

Tāwhirimātea having thus vanquished all his other brothers, next rushed against Tūmatauenga, to try his strength against his; he exerted all his force against him, but he could neither shake him or prevail against him. What did Tūmatauenga care for his brother’s wrath? he was the only one of the whole party of brothers who had planned the destruction of their parents, and had shown himself brave and fierce in war; his brothers had yielded at once before the tremendous assaults of Tāwhirimātea and his progeny—Tānemahuta and his offspring had been broken and torn in pieces—Tangaroa and his children had fled to the depths of the ocean or the recesses of the shore— Rongomātāne and Haumia-tikitiki had been hidden from him in the earth—but Tūmatauenga, or man, still stood erect and unshaken upon the breast of his mother Earth; and now at length the hearts of Heaven and of the god of storms became tranquil, and their passions were assuaged.

Tūmatauenga, or fierce man, having thus successfully resisted his brother, the god of hurricanes and storms, next took thought how he could turn upon his brothers and slay them, because they had not assisted him or fought bravely when Tāwhirimātea had attacked them to avenge the separation of their parents, and because they had left him alone to show his prowess in the fight. As yet death had no power over man. It was not until the birth of the children of Taranga and of Makeatutara, of Māuitaha, of Māuirota, of Māuipae, of Māuiwaho, and of Māui-tikitiki-o-Taranga, the demigod who tried to deceive Hine-nui-te-pō, that death had power over men. If that goddess had not been deceived by Māui-tikitiki, men would not have died, but would in that case have lived forever; it was from his deceiving Hine-nui-te-pō that death obtained power over mankind, and penetrated to every part of the earth.

Tūmatauenga continued to reflect upon the cowardly manner in which his brothers had acted, in leaving him to show his courage alone, and he first sought some means of injuring Tānemahuta, because he had not come to aid him in his combat with Tāwhirimātea, and partly because he was aware that Tāne had had a numerous progeny, who were rapidly increasing, and might at last prove hostile to him, and injure him, so he began to collect leaves of the whanake tree, and twisted them into nooses, and when his work was ended, he went to the forest to put up his snares, and hung them up—ha! ha! the children of Tāne fell before him, none of them could any longer fly or move in safety.

Then he next determined to take revenge on his brother Tangaroa, who had also deserted him in the combat; so he sought for his offspring, and found them leaping or swimming in the water; then he cut many leaves from the flax plant, and netted nets with the flax, and dragged these, and hauled the children of Tangaroa ashore.

After that, he determined also to be revenged upon his brothers Rongomātāne and Haumia-tikitiki; he soon found them by their peculiar leaves, and he scraped into shape a wooden hoe, and plaited a basket, and dug in the earth and pulled up all kinds of plants with edible roots, and the plants which had been dug up withered in the sun.

Thus Tūmatauenga devoured all his brothers, and consumed the whole of them, in revenge for their having deserted him and left him to fight alone against Tāwhirimātea and Rangi.

When his brothers had all thus been overcome by Tu’, he assumed several names, namely, Tūkāriri, Tūkanguha, Tūkataua, Tū-whakaheke-tangata, Tū-mata-whāiti, and Tūmatauenga; he assumed one name for each of his attributes displayed in the victories over his brothers. Four of his brothers were entirely deposed by him, and became his food; but one of them, Tāwhirimātea, he could not vanquish or make common, by eating him for food, so he, the last born child of Heaven and Earth, was left as an enemy for man, and still, with a rage equal to that of man, this elder brother ever attacks him in storms and hurricanes, endeavouring to destroy him alike by sea and land.

Now the meanings of these names of the children of the Heaven and Earth are as follows:—

Tangaroa signifies fish of every kind; Rongomātāne signifies the sweet potato, and all vegetables cultivated as food; Haumia-tikitiki signifies fern root, and all kinds of food which grow wild; Tānemahuta signifies forests, the birds and insects which inhabit them, and all things fashioned from wood; Tāwhirimātea signifies winds and storms; and Tūmatauenga signifies man.

Four of his brothers having, as before stated, been made common, or articles of food, by Tūmatauenga, he assigned for each of them fitting incantations, that they might be abundant, and that he might easily obtain them.

Some incantations were proper to Tānemahuta, they were called Tāne.

Some incantations were for Tangaroa, they were called Tangaroa.

Some were for Rongomātāne, they were called Rongomātāne.

Some were for Haumia-tikitiki, they were called Haumia.

The reason that he sought these incantations was, that his brothers might be made common by him, and serve for his food. There were also incantations for Tāwhirimātea to cause favourable winds, and prayers to the vast Heaven for fair weather, as also for mother Earth that she might produce all things abundantly. But it was the great God that taught these prayers to man.

There were also many prayers and incantations composed for man, suited to the different times and circumstances of his life—prayers at the baptism of an infant; prayers for abundance of food, for wealth; prayers in illness; prayers to spirits, and for many other things.

The bursting forth of the wrathful fury of Tāwhirimātea against his brothers, was the cause of the disappearance of a great part of the dry land; during that contest a great part of mother Earth was submerged. The names of those beings of ancient days who submerged so large a portion of the earth were—Terrible-rain, Long-continued-rain, Fierce-hail-storms, and their progeny were, Mist, Heavy dew, and Light dew, and these together submerged the greater part of the earth, so that only a small portion of dry land projected above the sea.

From that time clear light increased upon the earth, and all the beings which were hidden between Rangi and Papa before they were separated, now multiplied upon the earth. The first beings begotten by Rangi and Papa were not like human beings; but Tūmatauenga bore the likeness of a man, as did all his brothers, as also did a Po, a Ao, a Kore, te Kimihanga and Runuku, and thus it continued until the times of Ngāinui and his generation, and of Whiro-te-tupua and his generation, and of Tiki-tawhito-ariki and his generation, and it has so continued to this day.

The children of Tūmatauenga were begotten on this earth, and they increased, and continued to multiply, until we reach at last the generation of Māuitaha, and of his brothers Māuiroto, Māuiwaho, Māuipae, and Māui-tikitiki-o-Taranga.

Up to this time the vast Heaven has still ever remained separated from his spouse the Earth. Yet their mutual love still continues—the soft warm sighs of her loving bosom still ever rise up to him, ascending from the woody mountains and valleys, and men call these mists; and the vast Heaven, as he mourns through the long nights his separation from his beloved, drops frequent tears upon her bosom, and men seeing these, term them dewdrops.

The Legend of Rata

His Adventures with the Enchanted Tree and Revenge of his Father’s Murder

Before Tāwhaki ascended up into the heavens a son named Wahieroa had been born to him by his first wife. As soon as Wahieroa grew to man’s estate he took Kura for a wife, and she bore him a son whom they called Rata. Wahieroa was slain treacherously by a chief named Matukutakotako, but his son Rata was born some time before his death. It therefore became his duty to revenge the death of his father Wahieroa, and Rata having grown up, at last devised a plan for doing this. He therefore gave the necessary orders to his dependants, at the same time saying to them, “I am about to go in search of the man who slew my father.”

He then started upon a journey for this purpose, and at length arrived at the entrance to the place of Matukutakotako. He found there a man who was left in charge of it sitting at the entrance to the courtyard, and he asked him, saying, “Where is the man who killed my father?” The man who was left in charge of the place answered him, “He lives beneath in the earth there, and I am left here by him, to call to him and warn him when the new moon appears. At that season he rises and comes forth upon the earth, and devours men as his food.”

Rata then said to him, “All that you say is true, but how can he know when the proper time comes for him to rise up from the earth?” The man replied, “I call aloud to him.”

Then said Rata, “When will there be a new moon?” And the man who was left to take care of the place answered him, “In two nights hence. Do you now return to your own village, but on the morning of the second day from this time come here again to me.”

Rata, in compliance with these directions, returned to his own dwelling, and waited there until the time that had been appointed him, and on the morning of that day he again journeyed along the road he had previously travelled, and found the man sitting in the same place, and he asked him, saying, “Do you know any spot where I can conceal myself, and lie hid from the enemy with whom I am about to fight, from Matukutakotako?” The man replied, “Come with me until I show you the two fountains of clear water.”

They then went together until they came to the two fountains. The man then said to Rata, “The spot that we stand on is the place where Matuku rises up from the earth, and yonder fountain is the one in which he combs and washes his dishevelled hair, but this fountain is the one he uses to reflect his face in whilst he dresses it. You cannot kill him whilst he is at the fountain he uses to reflect his face in, because your shadow would be also reflected in it, and he would see it; but at the fountain in which he washes his hair you may smite and slay him.”

Rata then asked the man, “Will he make his appearance from the earth this evening?” And the man answered, “Yes.”

They had not waited long there when evening arrived and the moon became visible, and the man said to Rata, “Do you now go and hide yourself near the brink of the fountain in which he washes his hair;” and Rata went and hid himself near the edge of the fountain, and the man who had been left to watch for the purpose shouted aloud, “Ho, ho! the new moon is visible—a moon two days old.” And Matukutakotako heard him, and seizing his two-handed wooden sword, he rose up from the earth, and went straight to his two fountains. Then he laid down his two-handed wooden sword on the ground, at the edge of the fountain where he dressed his hair, and, kneeling down on both knees beside it, he loosened the strings which bound up his long locks, and shook out his dishevelled hair, and plunged down his head into the cool clear waters of the fountain. So Rata, creeping out from where he lay hid, rapidly moved up and stood behind him, and as Matukutakotako raised his head from the water, Rata with one hand seized him by the hair, while with the other he smote and slew him. Thus he avenged the death of his father Wahieroa.

Rata then asked the man whom he had found in charge of the place, “Where shall I find the bones of Wahieroa my father?” And the keeper of the place answered him, “They are not here; a strange people who live at a distance came and carried them off.”

Upon hearing this, Rata returned to his own village, and there reflected over many designs by which he might recover the bones of his father.

At length he thought of an excellent plan for this purpose, so he went into the forest and having found a very tall tree, quite straight throughout its entire length, he felled it, and cut off its noble branching top, intending to fashion the trunk into a canoe; and all the insects which inhabit trees, and the spirits of the forests, were very angry at this, and as soon as Rata had returned to the village at evening, when his day’s work was ended, they all came and took the tree, and raised it up again, and the innumerable multitude of insects, birds, and spirits, who are called “The offspring of Hakuturi,” worked away at replacing each little chip and shaving in its proper place, and sang aloud their incantations as they worked; this was what they sang with a confused noise of various voices:—

Fly together, chips and shavings,
Stick ye fast together,
Hold ye fast together;
Stand upright again, O tree!

Early the next morning back came Rata, intending to work at hewing the trunk of his tree into a canoe. When he got to the place where he had left the trunk lying on the ground, at first he could not find it, and if that fine tall straight tree, which he saw standing whole and sound in the forest, was the same he thought he had cut down, there it was now erect again. However, he stepped up to it, and manfully hewing away at it again, he felled it to the ground once more, and off he cut its fine branching top again, and began to hollow out the hold of the canoe, and to slope off its prow and the stern into their proper gracefully curved forms; and in the evening, when it became too dark to work, he returned to his village.

As soon as he was gone, back came the innumerable multitudes of insects, birds, and spirits, who are called the offspring of Hakuturi, and they raised up the tree upon its stump once more, and with a confused noise of various voices, they sang incantations as they worked, and when they had ended these the tree again stood sound as ever in its former place in the forest.

The morning dawned, and Rata returned once more to work at his canoe. When he reached the place, was not he amazed to see the tree standing up in the forest, untouched, just as he had at first found it? But he, nothing daunted, hews away at it again, and down it topples crashing to the earth. As soon as he saw the tree upon the ground, Rata went off as if going home, and then turned back and hid himself in the underwood, in a spot whence he could peep out and see what took place. He had not been hidden long when he heard the innumerable multitude of the children of Tāne approaching the spot, singing their incantations as they came along; at last they arrived close to the place where the tree was lying upon the ground. Lo, a rush upon them is made by Rata. Ha, he has seized some of them; he shouts out to them, saying, “Ha, ha, it is you, is it, then, who have been exercising your magical arts upon my tree?” Then the children of Tāne all cried aloud in reply, “Who gave you authority to fell the forest god to the ground? You had no right to do so.”

When Rata heard them say this, he was quite overcome with shame at what he had done.

The offspring of Tāne again all called our aloud to him, “Return, O Rata, to thy village, we will make a canoe for you.”

Rata, without delay, obeyed their orders, and as soon as he had gone they all fell to work. They were so numerous, and understood each what to do so well, that they no sooner began to adze out a canoe than it was completed. When they had done this, Rata and his tribe lost no time in hauling it from the forest to the water, and the name they gave to that canoe was Riwaru.

When the canoe was afloat upon the sea, 140 warriors embarked on board it, and without delay they paddled off to seek their foes. One night, just at nightfall, they reached the fortress of their enemies, who were named Ponaturi. When they arrived there, Rata alone landed, leaving the canoe afloat and all his warriors on board. As he stole along the shore, he saw that a fire was burning on the sacred place where the Ponaturi consulted their gods and offered sacrifices to them. Rata, without stopping, crept directly towards the fire, and hid himself behind some thick bushes of the Harakeke.[14] He then saw that there were some priests upon the other side of the same bushes, serving at the sacred place, and, to assist themselves in their magical arts, they were making use of the bones of Wahieroa, knocking them together to beat time while they were repeating a powerful incantation known only to themselves, the name of which was Titikura. Rata listened attentively to this incantation until he learnt it by heart, and when he was quite sure that he knew it, he rushed suddenly upon the priests; they, surprised and ignorant of the numbers of their enemy, or whence they came, made little resistance, and were in a moment smitten and slain. The bones of his father Wahieroa were then eagerly snatched up by him; he hastened with them back to the canoe, embarked on board it, and his warriors at once paddled away, striving to reach his fortified village.

In the morning some of the Ponaturi repaired to their sacred place, and found their priests lying dead there, just as they were slain by Rata. So, without delay, they pursued him. A thousand warriors of their tribe followed after Rata. At length this army reached the fortress of Rata, and an engagement at once took place, in which the tribe of Rata was worsted, and sixty of its warriors slain. At this moment Rata bethought him of the spell he had learnt from the priests, and, immediately repeating the potent incantation Titikura, his slain warriors were by its power once more restored to life; then they rushed again to the combat, and the Ponaturi were slaughtered by Rata and his tribe, a thousand of them—the whole thousand were slain.

Te Rata’s task of avenging his father’s death being thus ended, his tribe hauled up his large canoe on the shore, and roofed it over with thatch to protect it from the sun and weather. Rata now took Tongarautawhiri as one of his wives, and she bore him a son whom he named Tūwhakararo. When this son came to man’s estate, he took Apakura as one of his wives, and from her sprang a son named Whakatau. He was not born in the manner that mortals are, but came into being in this way: One day Apakura went down upon the seacoast, and took off a little apron which she wore in front as a covering, and threw it into the ocean, and a god named Rongotakawiu took it and shaped it, and gave it form and being, and Whakatau sprang into life, and his ancestor Rongotakawiu taught him magic and the use of enchantments of every kind.

When Whakatau was a little lad, his favourite amusement was flying kites. Mortals then often observed kites flying in the air, and could see nothing else, for Whakatau was running about at the bottom of the waters, still holding the end of the string of the kite in his hands. One day he stole up out of the water by degrees, and at length came upon the shore, when the whole of his body was quite plainly seen by some people who were near, and they ran as fast as they could to catch him. When Whakatau observed them all running to seize him, he slipped back again into the water, and continued flying his kite as before; but the people who had seen him were surprised at this strange sight, and being determined to catch him the next time he came out, they sat down upon the bank to wait for him. At last Whakatau came up out of the water again, and stepped on shore once more; then the people who were watching for him all ran at full speed to catch him. When Whakatau saw them coming after him again, he cried out, “You had better go and bring Apakura here, she is the only person who can catch me and hold me fast.”

When they heard this, one of them ran to fetch Apakura, and she came with him at once, and as soon as she saw little Whakatau, she called out to him, “Here I am; I am Apakura.” Whakatau then stopped running, and Apakura caught hold of him with her hands, and she questioned him, saying, “Whom do you belong to?” And Whakatau answered her, “I am your child; you one day threw the little apron which covered you on the sands of the sea, and the god Rongotakawiu, my ancestor, formed me from it, and I grew up a human being, and he named me Whakatau.”

From that time Whakatau left the water and continued to live on shore. His principal amusement, as long as he was a lad, was still flying kites; but he understood magic well, and nothing was concealed from him, and when he grew up to be a man he became a renowned hero.

This second legend of the destruction by Whakataupōtiki of the house called Te Tihi-o-Manono, or Te Uru-o-Manono, is added, because it differs considerably from the other, and is often alluded to in ancient poems.

Tinirau determined to attempt to avenge the death of his descendant Tūwhakararo, and he thought that the best person to do this was Whakatau, whom he knew to be very skilful in war, and in enchantments, so he directed his wife Hine-i-te-iwaiwa to find Whakatau, and she went in search. When she reached a village near where she expected to find him, she asked some people whom she saw, where Whakatau was, and they answered her, “He is on the top of yonder hill flying a kite.” She at once proceeded on her way until she came to the hill, and seeing a man there, she asked him, “Can you tell me where I can find Whakatau?” and he replied, “You must have passed him as you came here.” Then she returned to the village where she had seen the people, and said to them, “Why, the man upon the hill says that Whakatau is here;” but they told her that the man who had spoken to her must have been Whakatau himself, and that she had better return to him, and told her marks by which she might know him. She therefore returned, and he, after some time, when she showed him that she knew certain marks about his person, admitted that he was Whakatau; and he then asked her what had made her come to him? and she replied, “Tinirau sent me to you to ask you to come and assist in avenging the death of our near relative; the warriors are all collecting at the village of Tinirau, but they fear to go to attack these enemies, for they are the bravest of all the enemies of Tinirau.” Whakatau then asked her, “Have you yet given a feast to the warriors?” and she said, “Not yet.” He then spoke to her, saying, “Return at once and when you reach your village, give a great feast to the warriors; give them abundance of potted birds from the forests, but let all the oil in which the birds were preserved be kept for me; as for yourself, do not go to the feast, but, decking your head with a mourning dress of feathers, remain seated close in the house of mourning.” Then Hine-i-te-iwaiwa at once returned to Tinirau, to do as she had been directed.

Shortly after his visitor had left him, Whakatau called aloud to his people, saying. “Let the sideboards be at once fresh lashed on to our canoe, to the canoe of our ancestor of Rata.” His men were so anxious to fulfil their chief’s orders, that almost as soon as he had spoken they were at work, and had finished the canoe that very day, and dragged it down to the sea; when night fell, six of his warriors embarked in it, and Whakatau made the seventh; they then paddled off, following a direct course, until they reached the village of Tinirau; where they found Hine-i-te-iwaiwa seated in her house of mourning. Whakatau then asked her, “Have the warriors all left yet?” and she replied, “They will not do it, they are afraid.” Whakatau then said to her, “Farewell, then; do you remain here until you hear further from me.”

Whakatau and his men having re-embarked in their canoe, made a straight course for the place where was situated the great house called the Tihi-o-Manono, and they let their anchor drop and floated there.

When the next morning broke, and some of the people of the village coming out of the house, and beyond their defences, saw the canoe floating at the anchorage, they gave the alarm, crying out, “A war party! a war party!” Then the warriors came rushing forth to the fray in crowds, and arranged themselves in bands. Then stood forth one of their champions whose name was Mango-huritapena and he defied Whakatau, who was standing up in his canoe, calling out, “Were you fool enough, then, to come here of your own accord?” and Whakatau answered him, by shouting out, “Which of the arts of war do you consider yourself famous for?” and Mango-huritapena shouted out in answer, “I am a most skilful diver.” “Dive here, then, if you dare,” shouted out Whakatau in reply. Then the champion of the enemy gave a plunge into the water, and dived under it. Just as he got right under the canoe, one of Whakatau’s men poured the oil which Hine-i-te-iwaiwa had given them into the sea, and its waters immediately became quite transparent, so that they saw the warrior come floating up under the canoe, and Whakatau transfixed him with a wooden spear; so that champion perished.

Then forward stepped another champion named Pitakataka, and he defied Whakatau, shouting out, “Ah! you only killed Mango-huritapena because he chanced to put himself in a wrong position.” Whakatau shouted out in reply, “Which of the arts of war are you skilled in then?” and he answered. “Oh! I leap so skilfully that I seem to fly in the air.” “Then leap here, if you dare,” answered Whakatau; and the champion of his enemies took a run and made a spring high into the air; but Whakatau laid a noose on the canoe, and as the warrior alighted in it, he drew it tight and caught him as a bird in a snare, and thus slew that warrior also.

And thus, one after the other, he slew ten of the most famous warriors of his enemies; one whom he had seized, he saved alive, but he cut out his tongue, and then said to him, “Now, off with you to the shore again, and tell them there how I have overcome you all;” having done this, Whakatau retired a little distance back from the place, so that his canoe could not be seen by his enemies.

In the afternoon Whakatau landed on the coast, and before eating anything, offered the prescribed sacrifice of the hair and a part of the skin of the head of one of his victims to the gods; and when the religious rites were finished, he ate food; and having done this, he directed the people he had with him to return, saying, “Return at once, and when you reach the residence of Hine-i-te-iwaiwa, speak to her, saying, ‘Whakatau told us to come, and tell you, that he could not return with us;’ and he further said, ‘If heavy rain falls in large drops, it is a sign that I have been killed; but if a light, misty rain falls, and the whole horizon is lighted up with flames, then you may know that I have conquered, and that I have burnt the Tihi-o-Manono;’ he also said that he wished you to sit upon the roof of your house watching until you saw the Tihi-o-Manono burnt.” Whakatau’s people at once returned to Hine-i-te-iwaiwa to deliver the message he had given them.

Just before nightfall, Whakatau drew near the great house, called the Tihi-o-Manono, and as the people of Whitinakonako, a great chief, were collecting firewood at the edge of a forest, he stealthily dropped in amongst them, pretending to be collecting firewood too; and as they were going home with their loads of firewood upon their backs, he managed to push on in front of them, and got into the house first with a long rope in his hand. One end of this he pushed between one of the side posts which supported the roof, and the plank walls of the house, and did the same with every post of the house, until the rope had gone quite round it, and then he made one end of it fast to the last post, and held the other end in his hand.

By this time the people who lived in the house all came crowding on to pass the night in it, and soon filled it up: the house was so large, and there were so many of them, that they had to light ten fires in it.

When their fires had burnt up brightly, some of them called out to Mangōpare, the man whom Whakatau had saved alive, and whose tongue he had cut out, “Well now, tell us what kind of looking fellow that was who cut your tongue out;” and Mangōpare answered, “There is no one I can compare him to, he was not like a man in the proportion of his frame.” One of them then called out, “Was he at all like me?” But Mangōpare answered, “There is nobody I can compare him to.” Then another called out, “Was he at all like me?” and another, “Was he like me?” until, at length, Mangōpare called out, “Have I not already told you, that there is not one of you whom I can compare to him?”

Whakatau himself then exclaimed, “Was he at all like me?” And Mangōpare, who had not before seen him in the crowd, looked attentively at him for a minute, and then cried out, “I say, look here all of you at this fellow, he is not unlike the man, he looks very like him, perhaps it is he himself.” But Whakatau coolly asked him again, “Was the man really something like me?” And Mangōpare replied, “Yes, he was like you: I really think it was you;” and Whakatau shouted aloud, “You are right, it was I.” As soon as they heard this, all of them in a moment sprang to their feet. But, at the same instant, Whakatau laid hold of the end of the rope which he had passed round the posts of the house, and, rushing out, pulled it with all his strength, and straightway the house fell down, crushing all within it, so that the whole tribe perished, and Whakatau, who had escaped to the outside of the house, set it on fire, and Hine-i-te-iwaiwa, who was sitting upon the roof of her own house watching for the event, saw the whole of one part of the heavens red with its flames, and she knew that her enemies were destroyed. Whakatau, having thus avenged the death of Tūwhakararo, returned to his own village.

The Legend of Poutini and Whaiapu

The Discovery of New Zealand

Now pay attention to the cause of the contention which arose between Poutini and Whaiapu, which led them to emigrate to New Zealand. For a long time they both rested in the same place, and Hine-tū-a-hōanga, to whom the stone Whaiapu[15] belonged, became excessively enraged with Ngāhue, and with his stone Poutini.[16] At last she drove Ngāhue out and forced him to leave the place, and Ngāhue departed and went to a strange land, taking his jade stone. When Hine-tū-a-hōanga saw that he was departing with his precious stone, she followed after them, and Ngāhoe arrived at Tūhua with his stone, and Hine-tū-a-hōanga arrived and landed there at the same time with him, and began to drive him away again. Then Ngāhue went to seek a place where his jade stones might remain in peace, and he found in the sea this island Aotearoa (the northern island of New Zealand), and he thought he would land there.

Then he thought again, lest he and his enemy should be too close to one another, and should quarrel again, that it would be better for him to go further off with his jade stone, a very long way off. So he carried it off with him, and they coasted along, and at length arrived at Arahura (on the west coast of the middle island), and he made that an everlasting resting place for his jade stone; then he broke off a portion of his jade stone, and took it with him and returned, and as he coasted along he at length reached Wairere (believed to be upon the east coast of the northern island), and he visited Whangaparāoa and Tauranga, and from thence he returned direct to Hawaiki, and reported that he had discovered a new country which produced the moa and jade stone in abundance. He now manufactured sharp axes from his jade stone; two axes were made from it, Tutauru and Hauhauterangi. He manufactured some portions of one piece of it into images for neck ornaments, and some portions into ear ornaments; the name of one of these ear ornaments was Kaukaumatua, which was recently in the possession of Te Heuheu, and was only lost in 1846, when he was killed with so many of his tribe by a landslip. The axe Tutauru was only lately lost by Purahokura and his brother Reretai, who were descended from Tamaihutoroa. When Ngāhue, returning, arrived again in Hawaiki, he found them all engaged in war, and when they heard his description of the beauty of this country of Aotea, some of them determined to come here.

Construction of Canoes to Emigrate to New Zealand

They then felled a tōtara tree in Rarotonga, which lies on the other side of Hawaiki, that they might build the Arawa from it. The tree was felled, and thus the canoe was hewn out from it and finished. The names of the men who built this canoe were, Rātā, Wahieroa, Ngāhue, Parata, and some other skilful men, who helped to hew out the Arawa and to finish it.

A chief of the name of Hoturoa, hearing that the Arawa was built, and wishing to accompany them, came to Tamatekapua and asked him to lend him his workmen to hew out some canoes for him too, and they went and built and finished the Tainui and some other canoes.

The workmen above mentioned are those who built the canoes in which our forefathers crossed the ocean to this island, to Aotearoa. The names of the canoes were as follows: the Arawa was first completed, then Tainui, then Mātaatua, and Tākitumu, and Kurahaupō, and Tokomaru, and Matahourua. These are the names of the canoes in which our forefathers departed from Hawaiki, and crossed to this island. When they had lashed the topsides on to the Tainui, Rātā slew the son of Manaia, and hid his body in the chips and shavings of the canoes. The names of the axes with which they hewed out these canoes were Hauhauterangi, and Tutauru. Tutauru was the axe with which they cut off the head of Uenuku.

All these axes were made from the block of green stone brought back by Ngāhue to Hawaiki, which was called “The fish of Ngāhue.” He had previously come to these islands from Hawaiki, when he was driven out from thence by Hine-tū-a-hōanga, whose fish or stone was Obsidian. From that cause Ngāhue came to these islands; the canoes which afterwards arrived here came in consequence of his discovery.

Construction of Canoes to Emigrate to New Zealand

They then felled a totara tree in Rarotonga, which lies on the other side of Hawaiki, that they might build the Arawa from it. The tree was felled, and thus the canoe was hewn out from it and finished. The names of the men who built this canoe were, Rata, Wahie-roa, Ngahue, Parata, and some other skilful men, who helped to hew out the Arawa and to finish it.

A chief of the name of Hotu-roa, hearing that the Arawa was built, and wishing to accompany them, came to Tama-te-kapua and asked him to lend him his workmen to hew out some canoes for him too, and they went and built and finished the Tainui and some other canoes.

The workmen above mentioned are those who built the canoes in which our forefathers crossed the ocean to this island, to Aotearoa. The names of the canoes were as follows: the Arawa was first completed, then Tainui, then Matatua, and Takitumu, and Kura-hau-po, and Toko-maru, and Matawhaorua. These are the names of the canoes in which our forefathers departed from Hawaiki, and crossed to this island. When they had lashed the topsides on to the Tainui, Rata slew the son of Manaia, and hid his body in the chips and shavings of the canoes. The names of the axes with which they hewed out these canoes were Hauhau-te-Rangi, and Tutauru. Tutauru was the axe with which they cut off the head of Uenuku.

All these axes were made from the block of green stone brought back by Ngahue to Hawaiki, which was called “The fish of Ngahue.” He had previously come to these islands from Hawaiki, when he was driven out from thence by Hine-tu-a-hoanga, whose fish or stone was Obsidian. From that cause Ngahue came to these islands; the canoes which afterwards arrived here came in consequence of his discovery.

Legend of the Emigration of Turi

The Progenitor of the Whanganui Tribes

The following narrative shows the cause which led Turi, the ancestor of the Whanganui tribes, to emigrate to New Zealand, and the manner in which he reached these islands.

Hoimatua, a near relation of Turi, had a little boy named Pōtikiroroa. This young fellow was sent one day with a message to Uenuku, who was an ariki, or chief high priest, to let him know that a burnt offering had been made to the gods, of which Uenuku, as ariki, was to eat part, and the little fellow accidentally tripped and fell down in the very doorway of Wharekura, the house of Uenuku, and this being a most unlucky omen, Uenuku was dreadfully irritated, and he laid hold of the little fellow and ate him up, without even having the body cooked, and so the poor boy perished.

Turi was determined to have revenge for this barbarous act, and to slay some person as a payment for little Pōtikiroroa, and after casting about in his thoughts for some time as to the most effectual mode of doing this, he saw that his best way of revenging himself would be to seize Hawepōtiki, the little son of Uenuku, and kill him.

One day Turi, in order to entice the boy to his house, ordered the children of all the people who dwelt there with him to begin playing together, in a place where Hawepōtiki could see them; so they began whipping their tops, and whirling their whizgigs, but it was of no use; the little fellow could not be tempted to come and play with them, and that plan failed.

At last summer came with its heats, scorching men’s skins; and Turi, one very hot day, ordered all the little children to run and bathe in the river Waimātuhirangi; so they all ran to the river and began sporting and playing in the water. When little Hawepōtiki saw all the other lads swimming and playing in the river, he was thrown off his guard and ran there too, and Turi waylaid him and killed him in a moment, and thus revenged the death of Pōtikiroroa.

After killing the poor boy, Turi cut the heart out of his body, himself and his friends eat the body; but when, shortly afterwards, a chieftainess named Hotukura, sent up a present of baskets of food to their sacred prince to Uenuku, carried in the usual way by a long procession of people, some of Turi’s friends pushed into the basket of baked sweet potatoes prepared for Uenuku the heart of Te Hawepōtiki, cut up and baked too, and so it was carried up to Uenuku in the basket, and laid before him that he might eat it.

Uenuku, who had missed his little boy, being still unable to ascertain what had become of him, could not help sighing when he saw such an excellent feast, and said, “Poor little Hawepōtiki, how he would have liked this, but he now no longer comes running to sit by my side at mealtime;” and then he himself ate the food that was laid before him. He had hardly, however, ended his meal when one of his friends who had found what had been done, came and told him, saying, “They have made you eat a part of Hawepōtiki.” And he answered, “Very well, let it be; he lies in the belly of Toitehuatahi;” meaning by this proverb that he would have a fearful revenge; but he showed no other signs of feeling, that he might not gratify his enemies by manifesting his sorrow, or alarm them by loud threats of revenge.

At this time Turi was living in a house, the name of which was Rangiātea, and there were born two of his children, Tūrangaimua and Tāneroroa. One evening, shortly after the death of Te Hawepōtiki, Rongorongo, Turi’s wife, went out of the house to suckle her little girl, Tāneroroa, and she heard Uenuku in his house, named Wharekura, chanting a poem, of which this was the burden:—

“Oh! let the tribes be summoned from the south,
Oh! let the tribes be summoned from the north;
Let Ngāti Ruanui come in force;
Let Ngāti Rongotea’s warriors too be there,
That we may all our foes destroy,
And sweep them utterly away.
Oh, they ate one far nobler than themselves.”

When Rongorongo heard what Uenuku was chanting, she went back to her house and said to her husband, “Turi, I have just heard them chanting this poem in Wharekura.” And Turi answered, “What poem do you say it was?” Then she hummed it gently over to her husband, and Turi at once divined the meaning of it,[23] and said to his wife, “That poem is meant for me;” and he knew this well, because, as he had killed the child of Uenuku, he guessed that they meant to slay him as a payment for the boy, and that the lament his wife had heard evinced that they were secretly laying their plans of revenge.

He, therefore, at once started off to his father-in-law, Toto, to get a canoe from him, in which he might escape from his enemies; and Toto gave him one, the name of which was Aotea; the tree from which it had been made grew upon the banks of the Lake Waiharakeke. Toto had first hewn down the tree, and then split it, breaking it lengthways into two parts; out of one part of the tree he made a canoe, which he named Matahorua, and out of the other part he made a canoe which he named Aotea. He gave the canoe which he had named Aotea he made a present of to Rongorongo; thus giving a canoe to each of his two daughters. Matahorua was the canoe in which a large part of the world was explored, and Reti was the name of the man who navigated it.

One day Kupe and Hoturapa went out upon the sea to fish together; and when they had anchored the canoe at a convenient place, Kupe let down his line into the sea; and he said to his cousin, Hoturapa, “Hotu’, my line is foul of something; do you, like a good young fellow, dive down and release it for me.” But Hoturapa said, “Just give me your line, and let me see if I cannot pull it up for you.” But Kupe answered, “It’s of no use, you cannot do it; you had better give a plunge in at once, and pull it up.” This was a mere stratagem upon the part of Kupe, that he might obtain possession of Kuramārōtini, who was Hoturapa’s wife. However, Hoturapa, not suspecting this, good-naturedly dived down at once to bring up Kupe’s line; and as soon as he had made his plunge, Kupe at once cut the rope which was attached to the anchor, and paddled off for the shore as fast as he could go, to carry off Hoturapa’s wife, Kuramārōtini. When Hoturapa came up to the surface of the water, the canoe was already a long distance from him, and he cried out to Kupe, “Oh, Kupe, bring the canoe back here to take me in.” But Kupe would not listen to him; he brought not back the canoe, and so Hoturapa perished. Kupe then made haste and carried off Kuramārōtini, and to escape from the vengeance of the relations of Hoturapa he fled away with her on the ocean, in her canoe Matahorua, and discovered the islands of New Zealand, and coasted entirely round them without finding any inhabitants.

As Kupe was proceeding down the east coast of New Zealand, and had reached Castle Point, a great cuttlefish, alarmed at the sight of a canoe with me in it, fled away from a large cavern which exists in the south headland of the cove there; it fled before Kupe, in the direction of Raukawa, or Cook’s Straits. When Kupe arrived at these straits, he crossed them in his canoe, to examine the middle islands. Seeing the entrance of Awaiti (now called Tory Channel) running deep up into the land, he turned his canoe in there to explore it. He found a very strong current coming out from between the lands, and named the entrance Kurateau. Strong as the current was, Kupe stemmed it in his canoe, and ascended it until he was just surmounting the crown of the rapid. The great cuttlefish, or dragon, that had fled from Castle Point, which Kupe named Te Wheke-a-Muturangi, or the cuttlefish of Muturangi, had fled to Tory Channel, and was lying hid in this part of the current. The monster heard the canoe of Kupe approaching as they were pulling up the current, and raised its arms above the waters to catch and devour the canoe, men and all. As it thus floated upon the water, Kupe saw it, and pondered how he might destroy the terrible monster. At last he thought of a plan for doing this. He had already found that, although he kept on chopping off portions of its gigantic arms, furnished with suckers, as it tried to fold them about the canoe, in order to pull it down, the monster was too fierce to care for this; so Kupe seized an immense hollow calabash he had on board to carry his water in, and threw it overboard. Hardly had it touched the water ere the monster flew at it, thinking that it was the canoe of Kupe, and that he would destroy it; so it reared its whole body out of the water, to press down the huge calabash under it; and Kupe, as he stood in his canoe, being in a most excellent position to cut it with his axe, seized the opportunity, and striking it a tremendous blow, he severed it in two, and killed it.[24]

The labours of Kupe consisted in this, that he discovered these islands, and examined the different openings which he found running up into the country. He only found two inhabitants in the country—a bird which he named the Kōkako, and another bird which he named the Tīwaiwaka. He, however, did not ultimately remain in these islands, but returned to his own house, leaving the openings he had examined in the country as signs that he had been here.

Thus he left his marks here, but he himself returned to his own country, where he found Turi and all his people still dwelling, although it was now the fourth year from that one in which he had slain little Hawepōtiki; but Turi was then on the point of flying to escape from the vengeance of Uenuku, and as he heard of the discoveries Kupe had made, he determined to come to these islands. So he had his canoe, the Aotea, dragged down to the shore in the night; and Kupe, who happened to be near the place, and heard the bottom of the canoe grating upon the beach as they hauled it along, went to see what was going on; and when he found what Turi was about to do, he said to him, “Now, mind, Turi, keep ever steering to the eastward, where the sun rises; keep the bow of your canoe ever steadily directed towards that point of the sky.” Turi answered him, “You had better accompany me, Kupe. Come, let us go together.” And when Kupe heard this, he said to Turi, “Do you think that Kupe will ever return there again?” and he then continued, “When you arrive at the islands, you had better go at once and examine the river that I discovered (said to be the Pātea); its mouth opens direct to the westward. You will find but two inhabitants there (meaning the Kōkako and Tīwaiwaka); one of them carries its tail erect and sticking out. Now do not mistake the voice of one of them for that of a man, for it calls out just like one; and if you stand on one side of the river, and call out to them, you will hear their cries answering you from the other. That will be the very spot that I mentioned to you.”[25]

Turi’s brother-in-law, Tuau, now called out to him, “Why, Turi, the paddles you are taking with you are good for nothing, for they are made from the huhoe tree.” Turi replied, “Wherever can I get other paddles now?” and Tuau answered, “Just wait a little, until I run for the paddles of Taipāraeroa;” and he brought back, and put on board the canoe, two paddles, the names of which were Rangihorona and Kautukiterangi, and two bailers, the names of which were Tipuahoronuku and Rangikawheriko. Then Turi said, “Tuau, come out a little way to sea with me, and then return again, when you have seen me fairly started upon my long voyage.” To this Tuau cheerfully consented, and got into the canoe, which was already afloat. Then were carried on board all the articles which the voyagers were to take; and their friends out on board for them, seed, sweet potatoes, of the species called Te Kakau, and dried stones of the berries of the karaka tree; and some live edible rats in boxes, and some tame green parrots; and added some pet Pūkeko, or large waterhens; and many other valuable things were put on board the canoe, whence the proverb, “The Aotea’s valuable freight.”

At last away floated the canoe, whilst it was yet night, and Tuau sat at the stern, gently paddling as they dropped out from the harbour; but when they got to its mouth, Turi called out to his brother-in-law, “Tuau, you come and sit for a little at the house amidships, on the floor of the double canoe, and let me take the paddle and pull till I warm myself.” So Tuau came amidships, and sat down with the people there, whilst Turi went astern and took his paddle. Then Turi and his people pulled as hard as they could, and were soon far outside the harbour in the wide sea. Tuau, who had intended to land at the heads, at last turned to see what distance they had got. Alas! alas! they were far out at sea. Then he called out to Turi, “Oh, Turi, Turi, pray turn back the canoe and land me.” But not the least attention did Turi pay to him; he persisted in carrying off his brother-in-law with him, although there was Tuau weeping and grieving when he thought of his children and wife, and lamenting as he exclaimed, “How shall I ever get back to my dear wife and children from the place where you are going to!” But what does Turi care for that; he still thinks fit to carry him off with him, and Tuau cannot now help himself. They were now so far out at sea that he could not gain the shore, for he could scarcely have seen where the land was whilst swimming in the water, as it was during the night time that they started.

Lo! the dawn breaks; but hardly had the daylight of the first morning of their voyage appeared than one of the party, named Tapo, became insolent and disobedient to Turi. His chief was therefore very wroth with him, and hove him overboard into the sea; and when Tapo found himself in the water, and saw the canoe shooting ahead, he called out to Turi quite cheerfully and jocosely, “I say, old fellow, come now, let me live in the world a little longer.” And when they heard him call out in this manner, they knew he must be under the protection of the god Maru, and said, “Here is Maru, here is Maru.” So they hauled him into the canoe again and saved his life.

At last the seams of Turi’s canoe opened in holes in many places, and the water streamed into it, and they rapidly dipped the bailers into the water and dashed it out over the sides; Turi, in the meanwhile, reciting aloud an incantation, which was efficacious in preventing a canoe from being swamped. They succeeded at length, by these means, in reaching a small island which lies in mid-ocean, which they named Rangitahua. There they landed, and ripped all the old lashings out of the seams of the canoe, and re-lashed the top sides on to it, and thoroughly refitted it.

Amongst the chiefs who landed there with them was one named Porua, whose canoe was called Te Rīrino. They were carrying some dogs with them, as these would be very valuable in the islands they were going to, for supplying by their increase a good article of food and skins for warm cloaks. On this island they, however, killed two of them, the names of which were Whakapapa-tuakua and Tangakākāriki. The first of these they cooked and shared amongst them, but the second they cut up raw as an offering to the gods, and laid it cut open in every part before them, and built a sacred place, and set up pillars for the spirits, that they might entirely consume the sacrifice; and they took the enchanted apron of the spirits, and spread it open before them, and wearied the spirits by calling on them for some omen, saying, “Come, manifest yourselves to us, O gods; make haste and declare the future to us. It may be now that we shall not succeed in passing to the other side of the ocean; but if you manifest yourselves to us, and are present with us, we shall pass there in safety.” Then they rose up from prayer, and roasted with fire the dog which they were offering as a sacrifice, and holding the sacrifice aloft, called over the names of the spirits to whom the offering was made; and having thus appeased the wrath of the offended spirits, they again stuck up posts for them, saying as they did so—

“Tis the post which stands above there;
’Tis the post which stands in the heavens,
Near Atutahimarehua.”

Thus they removed all ill luck from the canoes, by repeating over them prayers called Keuenga, Takanga, Whakainuinumanga, etc., etc.

When all these ceremonies were ended, a very angry discussion arose between Potoru and Turi, as to the direction they should now sail in; Turi persisted in wishing to pursue an easterly course, saying, “Nay, nay, let us still sail towards the quarter where the sun first flares up;” but Potoru answered him, “But I say nay, nay, let us proceed towards that quarter of the heavens in which the sun sets.” Turi replied, “Why, did not Kupe, who had visited these islands, particularly tell us, ‘Now mind, let nothing induce you to turn the prow of the canoe away from that quarter of the heavens in which the sun rises?’ ” However, Potoru still persisted in his opinion, and at last Turi gave up the point, and let him have his own way; so they embarked and left the island of Rangitahua, and sailed on a westerly course.

After they had pursued this course for some time, the canoe Rīrino getting into the surf, near some rocks, was lost on a reef which they named Taputapuatea, being swept away by a strong current, a rapid current, by a swift running current, swiftly running on to the realms of death; and the Rīrino was dashed to pieces: hence to the present day is preserved this proverb, “You are as obstinate as Potoru, who persisted in rushing on to his own destruction.”

When the Rīrino had thus been lost, Turi, in the Aotea, pursued his course towards the quarter of the rising sun, and whilst they were yet in mid-ocean, a child, whom he named Tutawa, was born to Turi; they had then but nine sweet potatoes left, and Turi took one of these, leaving now but eight, and he offered the one he took as a sacrifice to the spirits, and touched with it the palate of little Tutawa, born in mid-ocean, at the same time repeating the fitting prayers. When they drew near the shore of these islands, one of the crew named Tuanui-a-te-ra was very disobedient and insolent to Turi, who, getting exceedingly provoked with him, threw him overboard into the sea. When they had got near enough to the shore to see distinctly they foolishly threw the red ornaments they wore on their heads (named Pōhutukawa) into the sea, these being old, dirty, and faded from length of wear, for they thought, although wrongly, the red things they saw in such abundance on the shore were similar ornaments.

At length the Aotea is run up on the beach of these islands, and the wearied voyagers spring out of her on to the sands, and the first thing they remark are the footprints of a man. They run to examine them, and find them to be those of Tuanui-a-te-ra, whom Turi had shortly before thrown overboard. There can be no doubt of this, because some of the footprints are crooked, exactly suiting a deformed foot which he had.

Turi having rested after his voyage, determined to start and seek for the river Pātea, which Kupe had described to him, and he left his canoe Aotea in the harbour, which he named after it. He travelled along the coast line from Aotea to Pātea, having sent one party before him, under Pungarehu, ordering them to plant the stones of the berries of the karaka tree, which they had brought with them, all along their route, in order that so valuable an article of food might be introduced into these islands. Turi, who followed with another party after Pungarehu, gave names to all the places as they came along. When he reached the harbour of Kāwhia he gave it that name, or the awhinga of Turi; then he came to Marokopa, or the place that Turi wound round to another spot; the river Waitara he named from the tāranga, or wide steps which he took in fording at its mouth; Mōkau, or Moekau, he named from his sleeping there; at Mangati they opened and spread out an enchanted garment named Hunokiko, and as all the people gazed at it, Turi named the place Mātakitaki; at another place (near the lake at the Grey institution at Taranaki), Turi took up a handful of earth to smell it, that he might guess whether the soil was good enough, and he named that place Hongihongi; another place, six miles to the south of Taranaki, he named Tapuwae, or the footsteps of Turi; another place he named Ōakura, from the bright redness of the enchanted cloak Hunokiko; another place Katikara, twelve miles south of Taranaki; another river he named Rāoa, from a piece of food he was eating nearly choking him there; another spot he named Kaupokonui (a river thirty-four miles northwest of Pātea), or the head of Turi; when they arrived there the enchanted cloak Hunokiko was twice opened and spread out, so he called the spot Marae kura; a place that they encamped at he named Kapuni (a river at Waimate), or the encampment of Turi; another place he called Waingongoro, or the place at which Turi snored; another spot he named Tanganoe, after his paddle; Ohingahape he named after the crooked foot of Tuanui-a-te-ra; a headland where there was a natural bridge running over a cave he named Whitikau, from the long time he was fording in the water to turn the headland, because he did not like to cross the bridge (this is five miles north of Pātea).

At length he reached the river which Kupe had described to him; there he built a pa, or fortress, which he named Rangitaawhi, and there he erected a post, which he named Whakatopea, and he built a house, which he named Matangireia, and he laid down a doorsill, or threshold, which he named Paepaehakehake; and he built a small elevated storehouse to hold his food, and he named it Paeāhua; the river itself he named Pātea; and he dug a well, which he named Parara-ki-te-uru. The farm he cultivated there he named Hekeheke-i-papa; the wooden spade he made he called Tipuiahuma. Then he had his farm dug up, and the chant they sang to encourage themselves, and to keep time as they dug, was—

“Break up our goddess mother,
Break up the ancient goddess earth.
We speak of you, O earth, but do not you disturb
The plants we have brought hither from Hawaiki the noble.
It was Māui who scraped the earth in heaps round the sides
In Kuratau.”

There they planted the farm. They had but eight seed potatoes, but they divided these into small pieces, which they put separately into the ground; and when the shoots sprang up, Turi made the place sacred with prayers and incantations, lest anyone should venture there and hurt the plants; the name of the incantation he used was Ahuaroa. When harvesttime came, they gathered in the crop of sweet potatoes, and found that they had eight hundred baskets of them.

The deeds above related were those which our ancestor Turi performed. Rongorongo was the name of his principal wife, and they had several children, from whom sprang the tribes of Whanganui and the Ngāti Manui tribe.

Legend of the Emigration of Turi

The Progenitor of the Whanganui Tribes

The following narrative shows the cause which led Turi, the ancestor of the Whanganui tribes, to emigrate to New Zealand, and the manner in which he reached these islands.

Hoimatua, a near relation of Turi, had a little boy named Potikiroroa. This young fellow was sent one day with a message to Uenuku, who was an ariki, or chief high-priest, to let him know that a burnt-offering had been made to the gods, of which Uenuku, as ariki, was to eat part, and the little fellow accidentally tripped and fell down in the very doorway of Wharekura, the house of Uenuku, and this being a most unlucky omen, Uenuku was dreadfully irritated, and he laid hold of the little fellow and ate him up, without even having the body cooked, and so the poor boy perished.

Turi was determined to have revenge for this barbarous act, and to slay some person as a payment for little Potikiroroa, and after casting about in his thoughts for some time as to the most effectual mode of doing this, he saw that his best way of revenging himself would be to seize Hawepotiki, the little son of Uenuku, and kill him.

One day Turi, in order to entice the boy to his house, ordered the children of all the people who dwelt there with him to begin playing together, in a place where Hawepotiki could see them; so they began whipping their tops, and whirling their whizgigs, but it was of no use; the little fellow could not be tempted to come and play with them, and that plan failed.

page 127

At last summer came with its heats, scorching men's skins; and Turi, one very hot day, ordered all the little children to run and bathe in the river Waimatuhirangi; so they all ran to the river and began sporting and playing in the water. When little Hawepotiki saw all the other lads swimming and playing in the river, he was thrown off his guard and ran there too, and Turi waylaid him and killed him in a moment, and thus revenged the death of Potikiroroa.

After killing the poor boy, Turi cut the heart out of his body, himself and his friends eat the body; but when, shortly afterwards, a chieftainess named Hotukura, sent up a present of baskets of food to their sacred prince to Uenuku, carried in the usual way by a long procession of people, some of Turi's friends pushed into the basket of baked sweet potatoes prepared for Uenuku the heart of Te Hawepotiki, cut up and baked too, and so it was carried up to Uenuku in the basket, and laid before him that he might eat it.

Uenuku, who had missed his little boy, being still unable to ascertain what had become of him, could not help sighing when he saw such an excellent feast, and said, “Poor little Hawepotiki, how he would have liked this, but he now no longer comes running to sit by my side at mealtime;” and then he himself ate the food that was laid before him. He had hardly, however, ended his meal when one of his friends who had found what had been done, came and told him, saying, “They have made you eat a part of Hawepotiki.” And he answered, “Very well, let it be; he lies in the belly of Toi-te-huatahi;” meaning by this proverb that he would have a fearful revenge; but he showed no other signs of feeling, that he might not gratify his enemies by manifesting his sorrow, or alarm them by loud threats of revenge.

At this time Turi was living in a house, the name of which was Rangiatea, and there were born two of his children, Turangaimua and Taneroroa. One evening, shortly after the death of Te Hawepotiki, Rongo-rongo, Turi's wife, went out of the house to suckle her little girl, Taneroroa, and she heard Uenuku in his page 128 house, named Wharekura, chanting a poem, of which this was the burden:—

“Oh! let the tribes be summoned from the south,
Oh! let the tribes be summoned from the north;
Let Ngati-Ruanui come in force;
Let Ngati-Rongotea's warriors too be there,
That we may all our foes destroy,
And sweep them utterly away.
Oh, they ate one far nobler than themselves.”

When Rongo-rongo heard what Uenuku was chanting, she went back to her house and said to her husband, “Turi, I have just heard them chanting this poem in Wharekura.” And Turi answered, “What poem do you say it was?” Then she hummed it gently over to her husband, and Turi at once divined the meaning of it,* and said to his wife, “That poem is meant for me;” and he knew this well, because, as he had killed the child of Uenuku, he guessed that they meant to slay him as a payment for the boy, and that the lament his wife had heard evinced that they were secretly laying their plans of revenge.

He, therefore, at once started off to his father-in-law, Toto, to get a canoe from him, in which he might escape from his enemies; and Toto gave him one, the name of which was Aotea; the tree from which it had been made grew upon the banks of the Lake Waiharakeke. Toto had first hewn down the tree, and then split it, breaking it lengthways into two parts; out of one part of the tree he made a canoe, which he named Matahorua, and out of the other part he made a canoe which he named Aotea. He gave

* The discovery of a plot by guessing the meaning of a song which persons were overheard singing was a common circumstance with all the races and throughout all the islands of the Pacific; for instance, in Pitcairn's Island, when first occupied by part of the crew of the “Bounty” and some Tahitian men and women we find:—“Brown and Christian were very intimate, and their two wives overheard one night Williams's second wife sing a song, ‘Why should the Tahitian men sharpen their axes to cut off the Englishmen's heads? The wives of Brown and Christian told their husbands what Williams's second wife had been singing; when Christian heard of it, he went by himself with his gun to the house where all the Tahitian men were assembled; he pointed his gun at them, but it missed fire. Two of the natives ran away into the bush.”—Pitcairn's Island and the Islanders.

page 129 the canoe which he had named Aotea he made a present of to Rongo-rongo; thus giving a canoe to each of his two daughters. Matahorua was the canoe in which a large part of the world was explored, and Reti was the name of the man who navigated it.

One day Kupe and Hoturapa went out upon the sea to fish together; and when they had anchored the canoe at a convenient place, Kupe let down his line into the sea; and he said to his cousin, Hoturapa, “Hotu', my line is foul of something; do you, like a good young fellow, dive down and release it for me.” But Hoturapa said, “Just give me your line, and let me see if I cannot pull it up for you.” But Kupe answered, “It's of no use, you cannot do it; you had better give a plunge in at once, and pull it up.” This was a mere stratagem upon the part of Kupe, that he might obtain possession of Kuramarotini, who was Hoturapa's wife. However, Hoturapa, not suspecting this, good-naturedly dived down at once to bring up Kupe's line; and as soon as he had made his plunge, Kupe at once cut the rope which was attached to the anchor, and paddled off for the shore as fast as he could go, to carry off Hoturapa's wife, Kuramarotini. When Hoturapa came up to the surface of the water, the canoe was already a long distance from him, and he cried out to Kupe, “Oh, Kupe, bring the canoe back here to take me in.” But Kupe would not listen to him; he brought not back the canoe, and so Hoturapa perished. Kupe then made haste and carried off Kuramarotini, and to escape from the vengeance of the relations of Hoturapa he fled away with her on the ocean, in her canoe Matahorua, and discovered the islands of New Zealand, and coasted entirely round them without finding any inhabitants.

As Kupe was proceeding down the east coast of New Zealand, and had reached Castle Point, a great cuttle-fish, alarmed at the sight of a canoe with me in it, fled away from a large cavern which exists in the south headland of the cove there; it fled before Kupe, in the direction of Raukawa, or Cook's Straits. When Kupe arrived at these straits, he crossed them in his canoe, to examine the middle islands. Seeing the entrance of Awa-iti (now called Tory Channel) running deep up into the land, he page 130 turned his canoe in there to explore it. He found a very strong current coming out from between the lands, and named the entrance Kura-te-au. Strong as the current was, Kupe stemmed it in his canoe, and ascended it until he was just surmounting the crown of the rapid. The great cuttle-fish, or dragon, that had fled from Castle Point, which Kupe named Te Wheke-a-Muturangi, or the cuttle-fish of Muturangi, had fled to Tory Channel, and was lying hid in this part of the current. The monster heard the canoe of Kupe approaching as they were pulling up the current, and raised its arms above the waters to catch and devour the canoe, men and all. As it thus floated upon the water, Kupe saw it, and pondered how he might destroy the terrible monster. At last he thought of a plan for doing this. He had already found that, although he kept on chopping off portions of its gigantic arms, furnished with suckers, as it tried to fold them about the canoe, in order to pull it down, the monster was too fierce to care for this; so Kupe seized an immense hollow calabash he had on board to carry his water in, and threw it overboard. Hardly had it touched the water ere the monster flew at it, thinking that it was the canoe of Kupe, and that he would destroy it; so it reared its whole body out of the water, to press down the huge calabash under it; and Kupe, as he stood in his canoe, being in a most excellent position to cut it with his axe, seized the opportunity, and striking it a tremendous blow, he severed it in two, and killed it.*

The labours of Kupe consisted in this, that he discovered these islands, and examined the different openings which he found running up into the country. He only found two inhabitants in the country—a bird which he named the Kokako, and another bird which he named the Tiwaiwaka. He, however, did not ultimately remain in these islands, but returned to his own house, leaving the openings he had examined in the country as signs that he had been here.

* They show several spots upon the east coast where Kupe touched with his canoes; but I have not yet had time to arrange and transcribe the various traditions connected with his landing at those places.—G. G.

page 131

Thus he left his marks here, but he himself returned to his own country, where he found Turi and all his people still dwelling, although it was now the fourth year from that one in which he had slain little Hawepotiki; but Turi was then on the point of flying to escape from the vengeance of Uenuku, and as he heard of the discoveries Kupe had made, he determined to come to these islands. So he had his canoe, the Aotea, dragged down to the shore in the night; and Kupe, who happened to be near the place, and heard the bottom of the canoe grating upon the beach as they hauled it along, went to see what was going on; and when he found what Turi was about to do, he said to him, “Now, mind, Turi, keep ever steering to the eastward, where the sun rises; keep the bow of your canoe ever steadily directed towards that point of the sky.” Turi answered him, “You had better accompany me, Kupe. Come, let us go together.” And when Kupe heard this, he said to Turi, “Do you think that Kupe will ever return there again?” and he then continued, “When you arrive at the islands, you had better go at once and examine the river that I discovered [said to be the Patea]; its mouth opens direct to the westward. You will find but two inhabitants there [meaning the kokako and tiwaiwaka]; one of them carries its tail erect and sticking out. Now do not mistake the voice of one of them for that of a man, for it calls out just like one; and if you stand on one side of the river, and call out to them, you will hear their cries answering you from the other. That will be the very spot that I mentioned to you.”*

Turi's brother-in-law, Tuau, now called out to him, “Why, Turi, the paddles you are taking with you are good for nothing, for they are made from the huhoe-tree.” Turi replied, “Wherever can I get other paddles now?” and Tuau answered, “Just wait a little, until I run for the paddles of Taiparae-roa;” and he brought back, and put on board the canoe, two paddles, the names of which were Rangihorona and Kautu-ki-te-rangi, and two bailers, the names of which were Tipuahoronuku and Rangi-ka-wheriko.

* It will be seen that they did not follow Kupe's directions, thinking that he was deceiving them, he being probably friendly to Uenuku.

page 132 Then Turi said, “Tuau, come out a little way to sea with me, and then return again, when you have seen me fairly started upon my long voyage.” To this Tuau cheerfully consented, and got into the canoe, which was already afloat. Then were carried on board all the articles which the voyagers were to take; and their friends out on board for them, seed, sweet potatoes, of the species called Te Kakau, and dried stones of the berries of the Karaka-tree; and some live edible rats in boxes, and some tame green parrots; and added some pet Pukekos, or large water-hens; and many other valuable things were put on board the canoe, whence the proverb, “The Aotea's valuable freight.”

At last away floated the canoe, whilst it was yet night, and Tuau sat at the stern, gently paddling as they dropped out from the harbour; but when they got to its mouth, Turi called out to his brother-in-law, “Tuau, you come and sit for a little at the house amidships, on the floor of the double canoe, and let me take the paddle and pull till I warm myself.” So Tuau came amidships, and sat down with the people there, whilst Turi went astern and took his paddle. Then Turi and his people pulled as hard as they could, and were soon far outside the harbour in the wide sea. Tuau, who had intended to land at the heads, at last turned to see what distance they had got. Alas! alas! they were far out at sea. Then he called out to Turi, “Oh, Turi, Turi, pray turn back the canoe and land me.” But not the least attention did Turi pay to him; he persisted in carrying off his brother-in-law with him, although there was Tuau weeping and grieving when he thought of his children and wife, and lamenting as he exclaimed, “How shall I ever get back to my dear wife and children from the place where you are going to!” But what does Turi care for that; he still thinks fit to carry him off with him, and Tuau cannot now help himself. They were now so far out at sea that he could not gain the shore, for he could scarcely have seen where the land was whilst swimming in the water, as it was during the night time that they started.

Lo! the dawn breaks; but hardly had the daylight of the first morning of their voyage appeared than one of the party, named page 133 Tapo, became insolent and disobedient to Turi. His chief was therefore very wroth with him, and hove him overboard into the sea; and when Tapo found himself in the water, and saw the canoe shooting ahead, he called out to Turi quite cheerfully and jocosely, “I say, old fellow, come now, let me live in the world a little longer.” And when they heard him call out in this manner, they knew he must be under the protection of the god Maru, and said, “Here is Maru, here is Maru.” So they hauled him into the canoe again and saved his life.

At last the seams of Turi's canoe opened in holes in many places, and the water streamed into it, and they rapidly dipped the bailers into the water and dashed it out over the sides; Turi, in the meanwhile, reciting aloud an incantation, which was efficacious in preventing a canoe from being swamped. They succeeded at length, by these means, in reaching a small island which lies in mid-ocean, which they named Rangitahua. There they landed, and ripped all the old lashings out of the seams of the canoe, and re-lashed the top sides on to it, and thoroughly refitted it.

Amongst the chiefs who landed there with them was one named Porua, whose canoe was called Te Ririno. They were carrying some dogs with them, as these would be very valuable in the islands they were going to, for supplying by their increase a good article of food and skins for warm cloaks. On this island they, however, killed two of them, the names of which were Whaka-papa-tuakua and Tanga-kakariki. The first of these they cooked and shared amongst them, but the second they cut up raw as an offering to the gods, and laid it cut open in every part before them, and built a sacred place, and set up pillars for the spirits, that they might entirely consume the sacrifice; and they took the enchanted apron of the spirits, and spread it open before them, and wearied the spirits by calling on them for some omen, saying, “Come, manifest yourselves to us, O gods; make haste and declare the future to us. It may be now that we shall not succeed in passing to the other side of the ocean; but if you manifest yourselves to us, and are present with us, we shall pass there in safety.” Then they rose up from prayer, and roasted page 134 with fire the dog which they were offering as a sacrifice, and holding the sacrifice aloft, called over the names of the spirits to whom the offering was made; and having thus appeased the wrath of the offended spirits, they again stuck up posts for them, saying as they did so—

“Tis the post which stands above there;
'Tis the post which stands in the heavens,
Near Atutahimarehua.”

Thus they removed all ill-luck from the canoes, by repeating over them prayers called Keuenga, Takanga, Whakainuinumanga, &c., &c.

When all these ceremonies were ended, a very angry discussion arose between Potoru and Turi, as to the direction they should now sail in; Turi persisted in wishing to pursue an easterly course, saying, “Nay, nay, let us still sail towards the quarter where the sun first flares up;” but Potoru answered him, “But I say nay, nay, let us proceed towards that quarter of the heavens in which the sun sets.” Turi replied, “Why, did not Kupe, who had visited these islands, particularly tell us, ‘Now mind, let nothing induce you to turn the prow of the canoe away from that quarter of the heavens in which the sun rises?’” However, Potoru still persisted in his opinion, and at last Turi gave up the point, and let him have his own way; so they embarked and left the island of Rangitahua, and sailed on a westerly course.

After they had pursued this course for some time, the canoe Ririno getting into the surf, near some rocks, was lost on a reef which they named Taputapuatea, being swept away by a strong current, a rapid current, by a swift running current, swiftly running on to the realms of death; and the Ririno was dashed to pieces: hence to the present day is preserved this proverb, “You are as obstinate as Potoru, who persisted in rushing on to his own destruction.”

When the Ririno had thus been lost, Turi, in the Aotea, pursued his course towards the quarter of the rising sun, and whilst they were yet in mid-ocean, a child, whom he named Tutawa, was born to Turi; they had then but nine sweet potatoes page 135 left, and Turi took one of these, leaving now but eight, and he offered the one he took as a sacrifice to the spirits, and touched with it the palate of little Tutawa, born in mid-ocean, at the same time repeating the fitting prayers. When they drew near the shore of these islands, one of the crew named Tuanui-a-te-ra was very disobedient and insolent to Turi, who, getting exceedingly provoked with him, threw him overboard into the sea. When they had got near enough to the shore to see distinctly they foolishly threw the red ornaments they wore on their heads (named Pohutukawa) into the sea, these being old, dirty, and faded from length of wear, for they thought, although wrongly, the red things they saw in such abundance on the shore were similar ornaments.

At length the Aotea is run up on the beach of these islands, and the wearied voyagers spring out of her on to the sands, and the first thing they remark are the footprints of a man. They run to examine them, and find them to be those of Tuanui-a-te-ra, whom Turi had shortly before thrown overboard. There can be no doubt of this, because some of the footprints are crooked, exactly suiting a deformed foot which he had.

Turi having rested after his voyage, determined to start and seek for the river Patea, which Kupe had described to him, and he left his canoe Aotea in the harbour, which he named after it. He travelled along the coast line from Aotea to Patea, having sent one party before him, under Pungarehu, ordering them to plant the stones of the berries of the Karaka-tree, which they had brought with them, all along their route, in order that so valuable an article of food might be introduced into these islands. Turi, who followed with another party after Pungarehu, gave names to all the places as they came along. When he reached the harbour of Kawhia he gave it that name, or the awhinga of Turi; then he came to Maro-kopa, or the place that Turi wound round to another spot; the river Waitara he named from the taranga, or wide steps which he took in fording at its mouth; Mokau, or Moekau, he named from his sleeping there; at Manga-ti they opened and spread out an enchanted garment named Hunokiko, and as all the people gazed page 136 at it, Turi named the place Matakitaki; at another place (near the lake at the Grey institution at Taranaki), Turi took up a handful of earth to smell it, that he might guess whether the soil was good enough, and he named that place Hongihongi; another place, six miles to the south of Taranaki, he named Tapuwae, or the footsteps of Turi; another place he named Oakura, from the bright redness of the enchanted cloak Hunokiko; another place Katikara, twelve miles south of Taranaki; another river he named Raoa, from a piece of food he was eating nearly choking him there; another spot he named Kaupoko-nui (a river thirty-four miles north-west of Patea), or the head of Turi; when they arrived there the enchanted cloak Hunokiko was twice opened and spread out, so he called the spot Marae kura; a place that they encamped at he named Kapuni (a river at Waimate), or the encampment of Turi; another place he called Waingongoro, or the place at which Turi snored; another spot he named Tanganoe, after his paddle; Ohingahape he named after the crooked foot of Tua-nui-a-te-ra; a headland where there was a natural bridge running over a cave he named Whiti-kau, from the long time he was fording in the water to turn the headland, because he did not like to cross the bridge (this is five miles north of Patea).

At length he reached the river which Kupe had described to him; there he built a pa, or fortress, which he named Rangitaawhi, and there he erected a post, which he named Whakatopea, and he built a house, which he named Matangirie, and he laid down a door-sill, or threshold, which he named Paepaehakehake; and he built a small elevated storehouse to hold his food, and he named it Paeahua; the river itself he named Patea; and he dug a well, which he named Parara-ki-te-uru. The farm he cultivated there he named Hekeheke-i-pape; the wooden spade he made he called Tipu-i-ahuma. Then he had his farm dug up, and the chant they sang to encourage themselves, and to keep time as they dug, was—

“Break up our goddess mother,
Break up the ancient goddess earth.
We speak of you, O earth, but do not you disturb
page 137The plants we have brought hither from Hawaiki the noble.
It was Maui who scraped the earth in heaps round the sides
In Kuratau.”

There they planted the farm. They had but eight seed potatoes, but they divided these into small pieces, which they put separately into the ground; and when the shoots sprang up, Turi made the place sacred with prayers and incantations, lest any one should venture there and hurt the plants; the name of the incantation he used was Ahuaroa. When harvest-time came, they gathered in the crop of sweet potatoes, and found that they had eight hundred baskets of them.

The deeds above related were those which our ancestor Turi performed. Rongo-rongo was the name of his principal wife, and they had several children, from whom sprang the tribes of Whanga nui and the Ngati-manui tribe.

The Story of Hinemoa

The Maiden of Rotorua

And the man said to him, “Now O governor, just look round you, and listen to me, for there is something worth seeing here; that very spot you are sitting upon, is the place on which sat our great ancestress Hinemoa, when she swam over here from the main. But I’ll tell you the whole story.

“Look you now, Rangiuru was the name of the mother of a chief called Tūtānekai; she was properly the wife of Whakauekaipapa (the great ancestor of the Ngāti Whakaue tribe); but she at one time ran away with a chief named Tūwharetoa (the great ancestor of the Te Heukeu and the Ngāti Tūwharetoa tribe); before this she had three sons by Whakaue, their names were Tawakeheimoa, Ngāraranui, and Tuteaiti. It was after the birth of this third son, that Rangiuru eloped with Tūwharetoa, who had come to Rotorua as a stranger on a visit. From this affair sprang Tūtānekai, who was an illegitimate child; but finally, Whakaue and Rangiuru were united again, and she had another son whose name was Kōpako; and then she had a daughter whom they named Tupa; she was the last child of Whakaue.

“They all resided here on the island of Mokoia. Whakaue was very kind indeed to Tūtānekai, treating him as if he was his own son; so they grew up there, Tūtānekai and his elder brothers, until they attained to manhood.

“Now there reached them here a great report of Hinemoa, that she was a maiden of rare beauty, as well as of high rank, for Umukaria (the great ancestor of the Ngāti Unui-kara-hapu, or sub-tribe), was her father; her mother’s name was Hinemaru. When such fame attended her beauty and rank, Tūtānekai and each of his elder brothers desired to have her as a wife.

“About this time Tūtānekai built an elevated balcony, on the slope of that hill just above you there, which he called Kaiweka. He had contracted a great friendship for a young man named Tiki. They were both fond of music: Tūtānekai played on the horn, and Tiki on the pipe; and they used to go up into the balcony and play on their instruments in the night; and on calm evenings the sound of their music was wafted by the gentle land breeze across the lake to the village at Ōwhata, where dwelt the beautiful Hinemoa, the younger sister of Wāhiao.

“Hinemoa could then hear the sweet-sounding music of the instruments of Tūtānekai and of his dear friend Tiki, which gladdened her heart within her. Every night the two friends played on their instruments in this manner, and Hinemoa then ever said to herself, ‘Ah! that is the music of Tūtānekai which I hear.’

“For although Hinemoa was so prized by her family, that they would not betroth her to any chief, nevertheless she and Tūtānekai had met each other on those occasions when all the people of Rotorua come together.

“In those great assemblies of the people Hinemoa had seen Tūtānekai, and as they often glanced each at the other, to the heart of each of them the other appeared pleasing, and worthy of love, so that in the breast of each there grew up a secret passion for the other. Nevertheless, Tūtānekai could not tell whether he might venture to approach Hinemoa to take her hand, to see would she press his in return, because said he, ‘Perhaps I may be by no means agreeable to her;’ on the other hand, Hinemoa’s heart said to her, ‘If you send one of your female friends to tell him of your love, perchance he will not be pleased with you.’

“However, after they had thus met for many, many days, and had long fondly glanced each at the other, Tūtānekai sent a messenger to Hinemoa, to tell of his love; and when Hinemoa had seen the messenger, she said, ‘Eh-hu! have we then each loved alike?’

“Some time after this, and when they had often met, Tūtānekai and his family returned to their own village; and being together one evening, in a large warm house of general assembly, the elder brothers of Tūtānekai said, ‘Which of us has by signs, or by pressure of the hand, received proofs of the love of Hinemoa?’ And one said, ‘It is I who have;’ and another said, ‘No, but it is I.’ Then they also questioned Tūtānekai, and he said, ‘I have pressed the hand of Hinemoa, and she pressed mine in return;’ but his elder brothers said, ‘No such thing; do you think she would take any notice of such a lowborn fellow as you are?’ He then told his reputed father, Whakaue, to remember what he would then say to him, because he really had received proofs of Hinemoa’s love; they had even actually arranged a good while before, the time at which Hinemoa should run away to him; and when the maiden asked, ‘What shall be the sign by which I shall know that I should then run to you?’ he said to her, ‘A trumpet will be heard sounding every night; it will be I who sound it, beloved—paddle then your canoe to that place.’ So Whakaue kept in his mind this confession which Tūtānekai had made to him.

“Now always about the middle of the night Tūtānekai, and his friend Tiki, went up into their balcony and played, the one upon his trumpet, the other upon his flute, and Hinemoa heard them, and desired vastly to paddle in her canoe to Tūtānekai; but her friends suspecting something, had been careful with the canoes, to leave none afloat, but had hauled them all up upon the shore of the lake; and thus her friends had always done for many days and for many nights.

“At last she reflected in her heart, saying ‘How can I then contrive to cross the lake to the island of Mokoia? it can plainly be seen that my friends suspect what I am going to do.’ So she sat down upon the ground to rest; and then soft measures reached her from the trumpet of Tūtānekai, and the young and beautiful chieftainess felt as if an earthquake shook her to make her go to the beloved of her heart; but then arose the recollection, that there was no canoe. At last she thought, perhaps I might be able to swim across. So she took six large dry empty gourds, as floats, lest she should sink in the water, three of them for each side, and she went out upon a rock, which is named Iri-iri-kapua, and from thence to the edge of the water, to the spot called Wairerewai, and there she threw off her clothes and cast herself into the water, and she reached the stump of a sunken tree which used to stand in the lake, and was called Hinewhata, and she clung to it with her hands, and rested to take breath, and when she had a little eased the weariness of her shoulders, she swam on again, and whenever she was exhausted she floated with the current of the lake, supported by the gourds, and after recovering strength she swam on again; but she could not distinguish in which direction she should proceed, from the darkness of the night; her only guide was the soft measure from the instrument of Tūtānekai; that was the mark by which she swam straight to Waikimihia, for just above that hot spring was the village of Tūtānekai, and swimming, at last she reached the island of Mokoia.

“At the place where she landed on the island, there is a hot spring separated from the lake only by a narrow ledge of rocks; this is it—it is called, as I just said, Waikimihia. Hinemoa got into this to warm herself, for she was trembling all over, partly from the cold, after swimming in the night across the wide lake of Rotorua, and partly also, perhaps, from modesty, at the thoughts of meeting Tūtānekai.

“Whilst the maiden was thus warming herself in the hot spring, Tūtānekai happened to feel thirsty, and said to his servant, ‘Bring me a little water;’ so his servant went to fetch water for him, and drew it from the lake in a calabash, close to the spot where Hinemoa was sitting. The maiden, who was frightened, called out to him in a gruff voice, like that of a man, ‘Whom is that water for?’ He replied, ‘It’s for Tūtānekai.’ ‘Give it here, then,’ said Hinemoa. And he gave her the water, and she drank, and having finished drinking, she purposely threw down the calabash, and broke it. Then the servant asked her, ‘What business had you to break the calabash of Tūtānekai?’ but Hinemoa did not say a word in answer. The servant then went back, and Tūtānekai said to him, ‘Where is the water I told you to bring me?’ So he answered, ‘Your calabash was broken.’ And his master asked him, ‘Who broke it?’ and he answered, ‘The man who is in the bath.’ And Tūtānekai said to him, ‘Go back again then, and fetch me some water.’

“He therefore took a second calabash, and went back, and drew water in the calabash from the lake; and Hinemoa again said to him, ‘Whom is that water for?’ So the slave answered as before, ‘For Tūtānekai.’ And the maiden again said, ‘Give it to me, for I am thirsty.’ And the slave gave it to her, and she drank, and purposely threw down the calabash, and broke it. And these occurrences took place repeatedly between those two persons.

“At last the slave went again to Tūtānekai, who said to him, ‘Where is the water for me?’ and his servant answered, ‘It is all gone. Your calabashes have been broken.’ ‘By whom?’ said his master. ‘Didn’t I tell you that there is a man in the bath?’ answered the servant. ‘Who is the fellow?’ said Tūtānekai. ‘How can I tell?’ replied the slave; ‘why, he’s a stranger.’ ‘Didn’t he know the water was for me?’ said Tūtānekai. ‘How did the rascal dare to break my calabashes? Why, I shall die from rage.’

“Then Tūtānekai threw on some clothes, and caught hold of his club, and away he went, and came to the bath, and called out, ‘Where’s that fellow who broke my calabashes?’ And Hinemoa knew the voice, that the sound of it was that of the beloved of her heart; and she hid herself under the overhanging rocks of the hot spring; but her hiding was hardly a real hiding, but rather a bashful concealing of herself from Tūtānekai, that he might not find her at once, but only after trouble and careful searching for her. So he went feeling about along the banks of the hot spring, searching everywhere, whilst she lay coyly hid under the ledges of the rock, peeping out, wondering when she should be found. At last he caught hold of a hand, and cried out, ‘Halloa, who’s this?’ and Hinemoa answered, ‘It’s I, Tūtānekai.’ And he said, ‘But who are you? who’s I?’ Then she spoke louder, and said, ‘It’s I; ’tis Hinemoa.’ And he said, ‘Ho! ho! ho! can such in very truth be the case? Let us two then go to my house.’ And she answered, ‘Yes;’ and she rose up in the water as beautiful as the wild white hawk, and stepped upon the edge of the bath as graceful as the shy white crane; and he threw garments over her, and took her, and they proceeded to his house, and reposed there; and thenceforth, according to the ancient laws of the Māori, they were man and wife.

“When the morning dawned, all the people of the village went forth from their houses to cook their breakfasts, and they all ate; but Tūtānekai tarried in his house. So Whakaue said, ‘This is the first morning that Tūtānekai has slept in this way; perhaps the lad is ill: bring him here—rouse him up.’ Then the man who was to fetch him went and drew back the sliding wooden window of the house, and peeping in, saw four feet. Oh! he was greatly amazed, and said to himself, ‘Who can this companion of his be?’ However, he had seen quite enough, and turning about, hurried back as fast as he could to Whakaue, and said to him, ‘Why, there are four feet, I saw them myself, in the house.’ Whakaue answered, ‘Who’s his companion, then? hasten back and see.’ So back he went to the house, and peeped in at them again, and then for the first time he saw it was Hinemoa. Then he shouted out in his amazement, ‘Oh! here’s Hinemoa, here’s Hinemoa, in the house of Tūtānekai!’ and all the village heard him, and there arose cries on every side, ‘Oh! here’s Hinemoa, here’s Hinemoa with Tūtānekai!’ And his elder brothers heard the shouting, and they said, ‘It is not true;’ for they were very jealous indeed. Tūtānekai then appeared coming from his house, and Hinemoa following him, and his elder brothers saw that it was indeed Hinemoa; and they said, ‘It is true, it is a fact.’

“After these things Tiki thought within himself, ‘Tūtānekai has married Hinemoa, she whom he loved; but as for me, alas! I have no wife;’ and he became sorrowful, and returned to his own village. And Tūtānekai was grieved for Tiki, and he said to Whakaue, ‘I am quite ill from grief for my friend Tiki.’ And Whakaue said, ‘What do you mean?’ And Tūtānekai replied, ‘I refer to my young sister Tupa: let her be given as a wife to my beloved friend, to Tiki.’ And his reputed father, Whakaue, consented to this. So his young sister Tupa was given to Tiki, and she became his wife.

“The descendants of Hinemoa and of Tūtānekai are at this very day dwelling on the lake of Rotorua, and never yet have the lips of the offspring of Hinemoa forgotten to repeat tales of the great beauty of their renowned ancestress, Hinemoa, and of her swimming over here; and this, too, is the burden of a song still current.”

The Story of Hine-Moa

The Maiden of Rotorua

And the man said to him, “Now O governor, just look round you, and listen to me, for there is something worth seeing here; that very spot you are sitting upon, is the place on which sat our great ancestress Hine-Moa, when she swam over here from the main. But I'll tell you the whole story.

“Look you now, Rangi-Uru was the name of the mother of a chief called Tutanekai; she was properly the wife of Whakaue-Kaipapa (the great ancestor of the Ngatiwhakaue tribe); but she at one time ran away with a chief named Tuwharetoa (the great ancestor of the Te Heukeu and the Ngatituwharetoa tribe); before this she had three sons by Whakaue, their names were Tawakeheimoa, Ngararanui, and Tuteaiti. It was after the birth of this third son, that Rangi-Uru eloped with Tuwharetoa, who had come to Rotorua as a stranger on a visit. From this affair sprang Tutanekai, who was an illegitimate child; but finally, Whakaue and Rangi-Uru were united again, and she had another son whose name was Kopako; and then she had a daughter whom they named Tupa; she was the last child of Whakaue.

“They all resided here on the island of Mokoia. Whakaue was very kind indeed to Tutanekai, treating him as if he was his own son; so they grew up there, Tutanekai and his elder brothers, until they attained to manhood.

“Now there reached them here a great report of Hine-Moa, that she was a maiden of rare beauty, as well as of high rank, for Umukaria (the great ancestor of the Ngati Unui-kara-hapu, or page 147 sub-tribe), was her father; her mother's name was Hine-Maru. When such fame attended her beauty and rank, Tutanekai and each of his elder brothers desired to have her as a wife.

“About this time Tutanekai built an elevated balcony, on the slope of that hill just above you there, which he called Kaiweka. He had contracted a great friendship for a young man named Tiki. They were both fond of music: Tutanekai played on the horn, and Tiki on the pipe; and they used to go up into the balcony and play on their instruments in the night; and on calm evenings the sound of their music was wafted by the gentle land-breeze across the lake to the village at Owhata, where dwelt the beautiful Hine-Moa, the younger sister of Wahiao.

“Hine-Moa could then hear the sweet-sounding music of the instruments of Tutanekai and of his dear friend Tiki, which gladdened her heart within her. Every night the two friends played on their instruments in this manner, and Hine-Moa then ever said to herself, ‘Ah! that is the music of Tutanekai which I hear.’

“For although Hine-Moa was so prized by her family, that they would not betroth her to any chief, nevertheless she and Tutanekai had met each other on those occasions when all the people of Rotorua come together.

“In those great assemblies of the people Hine-Moa had seen Tutanekai, and as they often glanced each at the other, to the heart of each of them the other appeared pleasing, and worthy of love, so that in the breast of each there grew up a secret passion for the other. Nevertheless, Tutanekai could not tell whether he might venture to approach Hine-Moa to take her hand, to see would she press his in return, because said he, ‘Perhaps I may be by no means agreeable to her;’ on the other hand, Hine-Moa's heart said to her, ‘If you send one of your female friends to tell him of your love, perchance he will not be pleased with you.’

“However, after they had thus met for many, many days, and had long fondly glanced each at the other, Tutanekai sent a messenger to Hine-Moa, to tell of his love; and when Hine-Moa had seen the messenger, she said, ‘Eh-hu! have we then each loved alike?’

page 148

“Some time after this, and when they had often met, Tutanekai and his family returned to their own village; and being together one evening, in a large warm house of general assembly, the elder brothers of Tutanekai said, ‘Which of us has by signs, or by pressure of the hand, received proofs of the love of Hine-Moa?’ And one said, ‘It is I who have;’ and another said, ‘No, but it is I.’ Then they also questioned Tutanekai, and he said, ‘I have pressed the hand of Hine-Moa, and she pressed mine in return;’ but his elder brothers said, ‘No such thing; do you think she would take any notice of such a low-born fellow as you are?’ He then told his reputed father, Whakaue, to remember what he would then say to him, because he really had received proofs of Hine-Moa's love; they had even actually arranged a good while before, the time at which Hine-Moa should run away to him; and when the maiden asked, ‘What shall be the sign by which I shall know that I should then run to you?’ he said to her, ‘A trumpet will be heard sounding every night; it will be I who sound it, beloved—paddle then your canoe to that place.’ So Whakaue kept in his mind this confession which Tutanekai had made to him.

“Now always about the middle of the night Tutanekai, and his friend Tiki, went up into their balcony and played, the one upon his trumpet, the other upon his flute, and Hine-Moa heard them, and desired vastly to paddle in her canoe to Tutanekai; but her friends suspecting something, had been careful with the canoes, to leave none afloat, but had hauled them all up upon the shore of the lake; and thus her friends had always done for many days and for many nights.

“At last she reflected in her heart, saying ‘How can I then contrive to cross the lake to the island of Mokoia? it can plainly be seen that my friends suspect what I am going to do.’ So she sat down upon the ground to rest; and then soft measures reached her from the trumpet of Tutanekai, and the young and beautiful chieftainess felt as if an earthquake shook her to make her go to the beloved of her heart; but then arose the recollection, that there was no canoe. At last she thought, perhaps I might be able page 149 to swim across. So she took six large dry empty gourds, as floats, lest she should sink in the water, three of them for each side, and she went out upon a rock, which is named Iri-iri-kapua, and from thence to the edge of the water, to the spot called Wai-rere-wai, and there she threw off her clothes and cast herself into the water, and she reached the stump of a sunken tree which used to stand in the lake, and was called Hinewhata, and she clung to it with her hands, and rested to take breath, and when she had a little eased the weariness of her shoulders, she swam on again, and whenever she was exhausted she floated with the current of the lake, supported by the gourds, and after recovering strength she swam on again; but she could not distinguish in which direction she should proceed, from the darkness of the night; her only guide was the soft measure from the instrument of Tutanekai; that was the mark by which she swam straight to Waikimihia, for just above that hot spring was the village of Tutanekai, and swimming, at last she reached the island of Mokoia.

“At the place where she landed on the island, there is a hot spring separated from the lake only by a narrow ledge of rocks; this is it—it is called, as I just said, Waikimihia. Hine-Moa got into this to warm herself, for she was trembling all over, partly from the cold, after swimming in the night across the wide lake of Rotorua, and partly also, perhaps, from modesty, at the thoughts of meeting Tutanekai.

“Whilst the maiden was thus warming herself in the hot-spring, Tutanekai happened to feel thirsty, and said to his servant, ‘Bring me a little water;’ so his servant went to fetch water for him, and drew it from the lake in a calabash, close to the spot where Hine-Moa was sitting. The maiden, who was frightened, called out to him in a gruff voice, like that of a man, ‘Whom is that water for?’ He replied, ‘It's for Tutanekai.’ ‘Give it here, then,’ said Hine-Moa. And he gave her the water, and she drank, and having finished drinking, she purposely threw down the calabash, and broke it. Then the servant asked her, ‘What business had you to break the calabash of Tutanekai?’ but Hine-Moa did page 150 not say a word in answer. The servant then went back, and Tutanekai said to him, ‘Where is the water I told you to bring me?’ So he answered, ‘Your calabash was broken.’ And his master asked him, ‘Who broke it?” and he answered, ‘The man who is in the bath.’ And Tutanekai said to him, ‘Go back again then, and fetch me some water.’

“He therefore took a second calabash, and went back, and drew water in the calabash from the lake; and Hine-Moa again said to him, ‘Whom is that water for?’ So the slave answered as before, ‘For Tutanekai.’ And the maiden again said, ‘Give it to me, for I am thirsty.’ And the slave gave it to her, and she drank, and purposely threw down the calabash, and broke it. And these occurrences took place repeatedly between those two persons.

“At last the slave went again to Tutanekai, who said to him, ‘Where is the water for me?’ and his servant answered, ‘It is all gone. Your calabashes have been broken.’ ‘By whom?’ said his master. ‘Didn't I tell you that there is a man in the bath?’ answered the servant. ‘Who is the fellow?’ said Tutanekai. ‘How can I tell?’ replied the slave; ‘why, he's a stranger.’ ‘Didn't he know the water was for me?’ said Tutanekai. ‘How did the rascal dare to break my calabashes? Why, I shall die from rage.’

“Then Tutanekai threw on some clothes, and caught hold of his club, and away he went, and came to the bath, and called out, ‘Where's that fellow who broke my calabashes?’ And Hine-Moa knew the voice, that the sound of it was that of the beloved of her heart; and she hid herself under the overhanging rocks of the hot spring; but her hiding was hardly a real hiding, but rather a bashful concealing of herself from Tutanekai, that he might not find her at once, but only after trouble and careful searching for her. So he went feeling about along the banks of the hot spring, searching everywhere, whilst she lay coyly hid under the ledges of the rock, peeping out, wondering when she should be found. At last he caught hold of a hand, and cried out, ‘Hollo, who's this?’ and Hine-Moa answered, ‘It's I, Tutanekai.’ And he said, ‘But who are you? who's I?’ Then she spoke louder, and said, page 151 ‘It's I; 'tis Hine-Moa.’ And he said, ‘Ho! ho! ho! can such in very truth be the case? Let us two then go to my house.’ And she answered, ‘Yes;’ and she rose up in the water as beautiful as the wild white hawk, and stepped upon the edge of the bath as graceful as the shy white crane; and he threw garments over her, and took her, and they proceeded to his house, and reposed there; and thenceforth, according to the ancient laws of the Maori, they were man and wife.

“When the morning dawned, all the people of the village went forth from their houses to cook their breakfasts, and they all ate; but Tutanekai tarried in his house. So Whakaue said, ‘This is the first morning that Tutanekai has slept in this way; perhaps the lad is ill: bring him here—rouse him up.’ Then the man who was to fetch him went and drew back the sliding wooden window of the house, and peeping in, saw four feet. Oh! he was greatly amazed, and said to himself, ‘Who can this companion of his be?’ However, he had seen quite enough, and turning about, hurried back as fast as he could to Whakaue, and said to him, ‘Why, there are four feet, I saw them myself, in the house.’ Whakaue answered, ‘Who's his companion, then? hasten back and see.’ So back he went to the house, and peeped in at them again, and then for the first time he saw it was Hine-Moa. Then he shouted out in his amazement, ‘Oh! here's Hine-Moa, here's Hine-Moa, in the house of Tutanekai!’ and all the village heard him, and there arose cries on every side, ‘Oh! here's Hine-Moa, here's Hine-Moa with Tutanekai!’ And his elder brothers heard the shouting, and they said, ‘It is not true;’ for they were very jealous indeed. Tutanekai then appeared coming from his house, and Hine-Moa following him, and his elder brothers saw that it was indeed Hine-Moa; and they said, ‘It is true, it is a fact.’

“After these things Tiki thought within himself, ‘Tutanekai has married Hine-Moa, she whom he loved; but as for me, alas! I have no wife;’ and he became sorrowful, and returned to his own village. And Tutanekai was grieved for Tiki, and he said to Whakaue, ‘I am quite ill from grief for my friend Tiki.’ And page 152 Whakaue said, ‘What do you mean?’ And Tutanekai replied, ‘I refer to my young sister Tupa: let her be given as a wife to my beloved friend, to Tiki.’ And his reputed father, Whakaue, consented to this. So his young sister Tupa was given to Tiki, and she became his wife.

“The descendants of Hine-Moa and of Tutanekai are at this very day dwelling on the lake of Rotorua, and never yet have the lips of the offspring of Hine-Moa forgotten to repeat tales of the great beauty of their renowned ancestress, Hine-Moa, and of her swimming over here; and this, too, is the burden of a song still current.”

The Art of Netting Learned by Kahukura from the Fairies

Ko Te Korero Mo Nga Patupaiarehe

Once upon a time, a man of the name of Kahukura wished to pay a visit to Rangiaowhia, a place lying far to the northward, near the country of the tribe called Te Rarawa. Whilst he lived at his own village, he was continally haunted by a desire to visit that place. At length he started on his journey, and reached Rangiaowhia, and as he was on his road, he passed a place where some people had been cleaning mackerel, and he saw the inside of the fish lying all about the sand on the sea-shore: surprised at this, he looked about at the marks, and said to himself, “Oh, this must have been done by some of the people of the district.” But when he came to look a little more narrowly at the footmarks, he saw that the people who had been fishing had made them in the night-time, not that morning, nor in the day; and he said to himself. “These are no mortals who have been fishing here—spirits must have done this; had they been men, some of the reeds and grass which they sat on in their canoe would have been lying about.” He felt quite sure from several circumstances, that spirits or fairies had been there; and after observing everything well, he returned to the house where he was stopping. He, however, held fast in his heart what he had seen, as something very striking to tell all his friends in every direction, and as likely to be the means of gaining knowledge which might enable him to find out something new.

So that night he returned to the place where he had observed all these things, and just as he reached the spot, back had come the fairies too, to haul their net for mackerel; and some of them were shouting out, “The net here! the net here!” Then a canoe paddled off to fetch the other one in which the net was laid, and as they dropped the net into the water, they began to cry out, “Drop the net in the sea at Rangiaowhia, and haul it at Mamaku.” These words were sung out by the fairies, as an encouragement in their work, and from the joy of their hearts at their sport in fishing.

As the fairies were dragging the net to the shore Kahukura managed to mix amongst them, and hauled away at the rope; he happened to be a very fair man, so that his skin was almost as white as that of these fairies, and from that cause he was not observed by them. As the net came close into the shore, the fairies began to cheer and shout, “Go out into the sea some of you, in front of the rocks, lest the nets should be entangled in Tawata-wauia-a-Teweteweuia,” for that was the name of a rugged rock standing out from the sandy shore; the main body of the fairies kept hauling at the net, and Kahukura pulled away in the midst of them.

When the first fish reached the shore, thrown up in the ripples driven before the net as they hauled it in, the fairies had not yet remarked Kahukura, for he was almost as fair as they were. It was just at the very first peep of dawn that the fish were all landed, and the fairies ran hastily to pick them up from the sand, and to haul the net up on the beach. They did not act with their fish as men do, dividing them into separate loads for each, but every one took up what fish he liked, and ran a twig through their gills, and as they strung the fish, they continued calling out, “Make haste, run here, all of you, and finish the work before the sun rises.”

Kahukura kept on stringing his fish with the rest of them. He had only a very short string, and, making a slip-knot at the end of it, when he had covered the string with fish, he lifted them up, but had hardly raised them from the ground when the slip-knot gave way from the weight of the fish, and off they fell; then some of the fairies ran good-naturedly to help him to string his fish again, and one of them tied the knot at the end of the string for him, but the fairy had hardly gone after knotting it, before Kahukura had unfastened it, and again tied a slip-knot at the end; then he began stringing his fish again, and when he had got a great many on, up he lifted them, and off they slipped as before. This trick he repeated several times, and delayed the fairies in their work by getting them to knot his string for him, and put his fish on it. At last full daylight broke, so that there was light enough to distinguish a man's face, and the fairies saw that Kahukura was a man; then they dispersed in confusion, leaving their fish and their net, and abandoning their canoes, which were nothing but stems of flax. In a moment the fairies started for their own abodes; in their hurry, as has just been said, they abandoned their net which was made of rushes; and off the good people fled as fast as they could go. Now was first discovered the stitch for netting a net, for they left theirs with Kahukura, and it became a pattern for him. He thus taught his children to make nets, and by them the Maori race were made acquainted with that art, which they have now known from very remote times.

Te Kanawa's Adventure with a Troop of Fairies

Te Kanawa, a chief of Waikato, was the man who fell in with a troop of fairies upon the top of Puke-more, a high hill in the Waikato district.

This chief happened one day to go out to catch kiwis with his dogs, and when night came on he found himself right at the top of Puke-more. So his party made a fire to give them light, for it was very dark. They had chosen a tree to sleep under—a very large tree, the only one fit for their purpose that they could find; in fact, it was a very convenient sleeping-place, for the tree had immense roots, sticking up high above the ground: they slept between these roots, and made the fire beyond them.

As soon as it was dark they heard loud voices, like the voices of people coming that way; there were the voices of men, of women, and of children, as if a very large party of people were coming along. They looked for a long time, but could see nothing; till at last Te Kanawa knew the noise must proceed from fairies. His people were all dreadfully frightened, and would have run away if they could; but where could they run to? for they were in the midst of a forest, on the top of a lonely mountain, and it was dark night.

For a long time the voices grew louder and more distinct as the fairies drew nearer and nearer, until they came quite close to the fire; Te Kanawa and his party were half dead with fright. At last the fairies approached to look at Te Kanawa, who was a very handsome fellow. To do this, they kept peeping slily over the large roots of the tree under which the hunters were lying, and page 182 kept constantly looking at Te Kanawa, whilst his companions were quite insensible from fear. Whenever the fire blazed up brightly, off went the fairies and hid themselves, peeping out from behind stumps and trees; and when it burnt low, back they came close to it, merrily singing as they moved—

“Here you come climbing over Mount Tirangi
To visit the handsome chief of Ngapuhi,
Whom we have done with.”*

A sudden thought struck Te Kanawa, that he might induce them to go away if he gave them all the jewels he had about him; so he took off a beautiful little figure, carved in green jade,† which he wore as a neck ornament, and a precious carved jade ear-drop from his ear. Ah, Te Kanawa was only trying to amuse and please them to save his life, but all the time he was nearly frightened to death. However, the fairies did not rush on the men to attack them, but only came quite close to look at them. As soon as Te Kanawa had taken off his neck ornament, and pulled out his jade ear-ring, and his other ear-ring, made of a tooth of the tiger-shark, he spread them out before the fairies, and offered them to the multitude who were sitting all round about the place; and thinking it better the fairies should not touch him, he took a stick, and fixing it into the ground, hung his neck ornament and ear-rings upon it.

As soon as the fairies had ended their song, they took patterns of the ear-rings, and handed them about from one to the other, until they had passed through the whole party, which then suddenly disappeared, and nothing more was seen of them.

The fairies carried off with them similitudes of all the jewels of Te Kanawa, but they left behind them his jasper neck ornament and his ear-rings, so that he took them back again, the hearts of the fairies being quite contented at getting the patterns alone; they saw, also, that Te Kanawa was an honest, well-dispositioned page 183 fellow. However, the next morning, as soon as it was light, he got down the mountain as fast as he could without stopping to hunt longer for kiwis.

The fairies are a very numerous people; merry, cheerful, and always singing, like the cricket. Their appearance is that of human beings, nearly resembling a European's; their hair being very fair, and so is their skin. They are very different from the Maories, they do not resemble them.

Te Kanawa had died before any Europeans arrived in New Zealand.

*Te Wherowhero, afterwards the first Maori King. He related this story to me, but said he did not remember the whole song, and that this was the concluding verse; it was probably in allusion to their coming to peep at Te Kanawa.

†Jade or Nephrite, commonly called greenstone.

The Loves of Takarangi and Rau-Mahora

There was, several generations since, a chief of the Taranaki tribe, named Rangirarunga. His pa was called Whakarewa; it was a large pa, renowned for the strength of its fortifications. This chief had a very beautiful daughter, whose name was Rau-Mahora; she was so celebrated for her beauty that the fame of it had reached all parts of these islands, and had, therefore, come to the ears of Te Rangi-apitirua, a chief of the Ngati-Awa tribes, to whom belonged the pa of Puke-ariki, on the hill where the Governor’s house stood in New Plymouth. This chief had a son named Takarangi; he was the hero of his tribe. He, too, naturally heard of the beauty of Rau-mahora; and it may be that his heart sometimes dwelt long on the thoughts of such great loveliness.

Now in those days long past, there arose a war between the tribes of Te Rangi-apitirua and of the father of Rau-mahora; and the army of the Ngati-Awa tribes marched to Taranaki, to attack the pa of Rangirarunga, and the army invested that fortress, and sat before it night and day, yet they could not take it; they continued nevertheless constantly to make assaults upon it, and to attack the garrison of the fortress, so that its inhabitants became worn out from want of provisions and water, and many of them were near dying.

At last the old chief of the pa, Rangirarunga, overcome by thirst, stood on the top of the defences of the pa, and cried out to the men of the enemy’s army, “I pray you to give me one drop of water.” Some of his enemies, pitying the aged man, said, “Yes;” and one ran with a calabash to bring him water. But the majority being more hard-hearted were angry at this, and broke the calabash in his hands, so that not a drop of water reached the poor old man; and this was done several times, whilst his enemies continued disputing amongst themselves.

The old chief still stood on the top of the earthen wall of the fortress, and he saw the leader of the hostile force, with the symbols of his rank fastened on his head: he wore a long white comb, made from the bone of a whale, and a plume of the long downy feathers of the white heron, the emblems of his chieftainship. Then was heard by all, the voice of the aged man as he shouted to him from the top of the wall: "Who art thou?" And the other cried out to him: "Lo, he who stands here before you is Takarangi." And the aged chief of the pa called down to him: "Young warrior, art thou able to still the wrathful surge which foams on the hidden rocks of the shoal of O-rongo-mai-ta-kupe?" meaning: "Hast thou, although a chief, power to calm the wrath of these fierce men?" Then proudly replied to him the young chief: "The wrathful surge shall be stilled; this arm of mine is one which no dog dares to bite," meaning that no plebeian hand dared touch his arm, made sacred by his deed and rank, or to dispute his will. But what Takarangi was really thinking in his heart was, "That dying old man is the father of Rau-mahora, of that so lovely maid. Ah, how I should grieve if one so young and innocent should die tormented with the want of water." Then he arose, and slowly went to bring water for that aged man, and for his youthful daughter; and he filled a calabash, dipping it up from the cool spring which gushes up from the earth, and is named Fount Oringi.[28] No word was spoken, or movement made, by the crowd of fierce and angry men, but all, resting upon their arms, looked on in wonder and in silence. Calm lay the sea, that was before so troubled, all timid and respectful in the lowly hero's presence; and the water was taken by Takarangi, and by him was held up to the aged chief; then was heard by all, the voice of Takarangi, as he cried aloud to him, "There:-said I not to you, ‘No dog would dare to bite this hand of mine?’ Behold the water for you—for you and for that young girl.” Then they drank, both of them, and Takaranga gazed eagerly at the young girl, and she too looked eagerly at Takarangi; long time gazed they, each one at the other; and as the warriors of the army of Takarangi looked on, lo, he had climbed up and was sitting at the young maiden’s side; and they said amongst themselves, “O comrades, our lord Takarangi loves war, but one would think he likes Rau-mahora almost as well.”

At last a sudden thought struck the heart of the aged chief, of the father of Rau-mahora: so he said to his daughter, “O my child, would it be pleasing to you to have this young chief for a husband?” and the young girl said, “I like him.” Then the old man consented that his daughter should be given as a bride to Takarangi, and he took her as his wife. Thence was that war brought to an end, and the army of Takarangi dispersed, and they returned each man to his own village, and they came back no more to make war against the tribes of Taranaki—for ever were ended their wars against them.

And the descendants of Rau-mahora dwell here in Wellington. They are Te Puni, and all his children, and his relatives. For Takarangi and Rau-mahora had a daughter named Rongougaroa, who was married to Te Whiti; and they had a son named Ani-waniwa, who married Tawhirikura; and they had a son named Rerewha-i-te-rangi, and he married Puku, who was the mother of Te Puni.

The History of Pāoa, the Ancestor of the Ngāti Pāoa Tribe

When Pāoa came to this country, bordering on the river Thames, Waihou and Piako, he came from the southward, from the Ngāti Kahunghu tribe; the Whaiapāoa (East Cape) was the country of his ancestors; his father was named Rongo-tiu-moe-whara.

Whilst Pāoa was living with his father, he had a quarrel with his wife; and she, being overcome with shame, went away to other places, to stop there, and mourn and weep for the manner in which she had been treated by her husband. For a long time after she had gone Pāoa remained, expecting that his wife would come back again; and after he had expected her return for very many days, at last he surmised she must have gone to some very distant place; so he thought, “Perhaps she has gone to a great distance, I will go and find her.”

Then he set off on his journey, with his slave as a travelling companion, and went through many villages searching for his wife, and she could not be found; for when she heard the voice of Pāoa she hid herself. However he continued to travel in search of her, but as he could nowhere find his wife, at last he returned to his father and his relations, that he might once more see them. And when he arrived at their village he wept towards them, saying, “If we cannot find her, I and my slave will return to search this town and that town, and this village and that village. If we cannot find her, I and my slave will still continue to search for her.”

Then his father spoke, saying, “Yes, go, my son, but take some of your brethren with you to bear you company upon the road.”

And Pāoa answered, “ ’Tis well, I will take them; if we find her, then we will all return to you; if we cannot find her, I will send my brothers back to you; but, as for myself, I will not in that case return to you, but I and my slave will persevere in our efforts, and will continue until we have searched every town and village.”

His father replied, “Be it so, my son.”

Then Pāoa and his brothers started and traversed the forests until they came out into the Taupō country, and at last reached the Lake of Taupō; but Pāoa’s wife could not be found there; so he then said to his brethren, “Now, then, my young brothers, you must return to our father, to cheer up his heart once more.” But his brothers earnestly entreated him to let them still bear him company, and spoke most affectionately to their eldest brother; but Pāoa spoke angrily to them, and positively ordered them to return. So they went on their way home again, and returned from Taupō to the Whaiapāoa.

So Pāoa pursued his journey in peace and reached Tongariro, and thence came out upon the Taranaki country; but his wife could nowhere be found. Then he pursued his journey up the west coast, until he came out upon the river Waikato, some distance above its mouth, in the interior of the country, and stopped at a village there. And when the people of the village saw Pāoa, they questioned his slave, saying, “Who is this?” and they were answered by the slave,

“It is Pāoa.”

And they asked the slave again, “Whence does he come?”

And the slave told them thus, “We come together from the eastward, from the rising sun.”

Then they questioned further, saying, “What made you undertake this journey?”

And the slave answered them, “We came to try to find his wife, and we have searched everywhere, and, lo! she has not yet been found.”

Then the people of the village said to the slave, “Why should such a woman be sought after in this manner by you? here is a maiden as a wife for him; why should you search further? If there are maidens in your country, have we not as good here? Why should such a woman be sought after in such a manner by you? Lo, here is a maiden as a wife for your master.” Then Pāoa was married to a maiden of that place.

Then he removed a little way from that village to Kaitotehe, and dwelt there, and made it his permanent residence; and two male children were there born to him; the eldest was named Toawhena, the second Toapoto. And after he had lived there for some time, Pāoa cast his glances on a very beautiful young woman, but who was a slave of very mean origin; and Pāoa made love to that woman, caught by her beauty—that was the cause that led Pāoa to make her his slave wife—and he deserted his wife of high rank and his children. When Pāoa’s slave saw that his master had deserted his wife of rank, he said to himself, “As for me, I will return to my lady.” So he returned to his mistress, and continued to live with her as her slave; and, in order to support her children, his mistress was obliged to work with her slave. And they cultivated together a garden of sweet potatoes, and were fortunate, for in the first year they had one hundred baskets of sweet potatoes, and in the second year they had two hundred baskets of sweet potatoes; and the slave and his lady went on working most industriously, and extending their cultivations.

Pāoa and the woman he had taken as a slave wife also laboured together, and they extended their cultivations as much as they could; but strangers kept on dropping in, consuming from time to time a few basketfuls of their produce; for visitors who came never went to any other house; they naturally all resorted to Pāoa, that it might be seen that they regarded him as the principal person; and thus it went on each year.

At last, after the third season of harvest, some distant connections of Pāoa’s principal wife came in their canoe into the river Horotiu, and landed at Pepepe, where was their young female relation, the wife of Pāoa. So the travellers asked her, saying, “Where shall we find Pāoa?”

And she told them, “Oh, Pāoa’s place is a little lower down the river, at Kaitotehe.”

Then the travellers went straight on board their canoe again, and pulled down the river to Kaitotehe, and landed there; and there was Pāoa. And some of his people raised the cry of “Strangers! strangers! Here are strangers come to visit Pāoa!”

Now it happened that the slave wife of Pāoa had just come back from the forests, from gathering the curved sprouts of the mamaku trees, and sprouts of the mauku, and such coarse kinds of wild food as are eaten in times of scarcity; and as soon as she had come back she bound up the sprouts she had collected in the leaves of the wharangi and of the karamū, that they might be so cooked as to be juicy and tender, and then put them under the hot ashes of the fire. She was just caught doing this by the strangers who had arrived; and off she ran on one side, leaving her vegetables cooking, not having had time to take them out of the fire. In came the strangers, straight up to the village from the river; and whilst some of them went up to the houses, others came straight to the fire where the food was cooking; and seeing the hot ashes heaped up, they said amongst themselves, “Someone is cooking eels here;” and those amongst them who were very glad at the thought of getting such good food said, “Ah! there are no doubt some nice eels cooking in this fire.” And the travellers lingered about the fire, waiting until the person the food belonged to should come back again, and, taking off the fire, should take out the dainties they longed for. But not a bit did the woman come back to her fire again; she was nearly dead with alarm lest the strangers should see the food cooking in her oven, and should say, “See what beggarly stuff this wretched creature eats.” As for Pāoa, too, he could not open his mouth to say a word, he felt so disgraced at not having any food to set before his guests.

At last Pāoa told his slave wife to run to his principal wife and bring a few sweet potatoes for the visitors; but the woman said to him, “What is the use of my going? she will not let us have any.”

But Pāoa answered, “Never mind, you had better go; even if you get none, you can but try.”

So the woman hurried off to carry Pāoa’s message; and whilst she was still coming, and a long way off, she was seen by the children of Pāoa’s principal wife; and off ran the children to their mother, and told her, saying, “Here comes that slave wife of Pāoa’s.”

When their mother heard what they said, off she ran too, and got into her house to hide herself. However, the other woman came straight on to the house, for she had seen Pāoa’s wife go into it; and when she reached the doorway she bent down, and, peeping into the house, there she saw Pāoa’s wife working away, weaving a garment of flax. So she saluted the wife of Pāoa, and his principal wife saluted her too; and when the ceremonies of the salutation were completed, the slave wife delivered her message, and said, “I have been sent here by Pāoa to fetch a little food for the strangers who have just arrived.”

Now Pāoa’s principal wife had guessed very readily that the woman had been sent by Pāoa to fetch provisions; so she in her turn spoke and said, “I send provisions for the strangers indeed! Whence should I have provisions? Am I a man, that I should be strong to labour and till the ground? Has a poor woman strength to labour? I will not part with any of my hard-earned little store of food. I shall keep it to nourish my deserted children, lest they perish from want.”

All this time Pāoa was waiting anxiously until his messenger returned; and as soon as ever she came back he questioned her, saying, “Well, what does she say?” and the woman answered,

“She will not give any provisions; she says she has nothing to give her children, and they are famishing.”

When Pāoa heard this, he had not a word to say; he felt so completely abashed, that he could give no answer; but he turned to the strangers and said, “We have no food here, and shall be very hungry, so that we can have no pleasant conversation. It is only when the appetite is satisfied that conversation runs agreeably.”

The strangers still sat until evening began to close in, till almost starving with hunger; then his guests returned to their own village. On the very same day that they had arrived they got into their canoe again, and pulled away. As for poor Pāoa, he was left overwhelmed with shame, and he said that he would abandon that country, and be off and seek some new abode; and that very night he departed a fugitive from his own place.

Thus Pāoa started in the night, and he went straight from the Waikato for Hauraki, up the valley of the Mangawara Creek, which runs out into the Waikato, at the base of Mount Taupiri, on its eastern side. When the day dawned, Pāoa was still pushing hurriedly on; and at last he reached the hills of Tikitikimaurea, where the Mangawara has its source; and ascending these, he rested there, and saw the Waikato lying far behind him, and Hauraki lying before him: and then he wept sore for grief at leaving his children, and his people, and his place. He wept long as he thought of these things; and when tears had somewhat assuaged his grief, he bid them all farewell, and ceased sorrowing.

Then he resumed his journey again, and pushed straight on for the river Piako, and at last came out upon the banks of that river, and stopped at a fortified village named Mirimirirau, and he stopped there and dwelt there amongst the people of that place, and they became a people for him, and they dealt kindly with him, and he was as a chief to them, and he dwelt there; and a year passed away, and by degrees the fame of Pāoa spread into the district of Hauraki, and at length it reached the village of Ruawhea.

And it chanced that a visiting party started from the fortified village where Pāoa dwelt, and went to Ruawhea, where a large part of the people of Hauraki were assembled; and when they saw the party of visitors approaching, a cry was raised, “These strangers come from a great distance; they come from the river Piako.” Then, indeed, loud were the cries of “Welcome! welcome!” which were raised; and the visitors took up their abode in some of the buildings which belonged to Tukutuku (she was the daughter of the chief of Ruawhea); and they seated themselves there, and had not sat long—indeed, but a very short time—when their hospitable young hostess had fires lighted to roast fern root in, to stay their appetites whilst other food was prepared; and they rose up and went to the fires, and partook of the fern root whilst better food was preparing; and when the food was cooked, it was spread out before them, and consisted chiefly of delicate eels. When they had finished their meal, they lay down to rest; and when day broke they went to the residences of other people, each one going to the place of those friends he had come to visit.

After many days the several persons of this visiting party all assembled again at the residence of Tukutuku previous to returning home, and they rested there, intending to sleep there. As soon as it grew dark, a bright fire was lighted in the house, and the dancers were all ranged in order; for the residence of a chief was known by the people dancing there.

Whilst the dance was going on, Tukutuku took an opportunity of questioning some of the strangers, saying, “Where is he of whom we have heard so much here?”

Then the strangers answered, “Whom do you mean?” The maiden replied, “I mean Pāoa;” and they answered her,

“Oh, he is living on the Piako.”

And she said, “Do you think we shall ever see Pāoa here?” and they replied,

“We cannot tell; perhaps he will come here.”

The young maiden was still unmarried. Many chiefs flocked about her to try to win her favour, but she never would consent to take them. Now when her parents heard their daughter asking in this manner after Pāoa, they said to one another, “Why, surely the girl must have taken a fancy to Pāoa: do you hear how she is asking after him?”

When the morning broke, the party of visitors departed for the Piako, filled with wonder at the greatness and rank of the maiden, and the number of her dependents. Her real greatness was shown by her courteousness and generosity to all her dependents; and when they saw this, their hearts were moved, and they brought to her as presents large quantities of food, such as dried shellfish and other delicacies, so that she could show great hospitality to strangers.

When the party from Pāoa’s fortified village, who had been visiting at Hauraki, arrived near their own place, the people of the fortress saw them returning, and they waved their garments and cried out, “Hasten here, hasten here!” as a welcome to them upon their return; so those who were returning landed, and entered the fortress, and seated themselves in the courtyard, and began to relate all that they had seen and heard. And they talked until evening, and Pāoa was seated with them; and as they talked they mentioned the great rank of Tukutuku, the maiden whom they had seen, and they said to Pāoa, “Oh! father, the maiden questioned us about you.”

And he replied, “About whom, say you, did the maiden question you?”

And they said, “She questioned us about you, saying, ‘Where is the man whose renown has been so much heard of here?’ and we answered her, ‘Who is it you are asking after?’ and she told us, ‘It is Pāoa I am speaking of;’ and then the maiden said to us, ‘I should much like to see him; for his fame is noised over the whole country, far and wide.’ Then we told her, ‘he is to be found at his own fortress;’ and she questioned us again, saying, ‘Where is his fortress?’ And we answered, ‘At Mirimirirau.’ Then she said to us, ‘Do you think he will visit my residence, or not?’ And we answered the maid, ‘Who knows? perhaps he will visit this place.’ ”

When Pāoa heard this, he said to them, “Wait a little, we will all go and see her in the tenth month, when our crops are harvested and stored; let us go on our journey unembarrassed with work, lest whilst we are absent on the journey our hearts should feel anxious about our homes;” and all his people fell in with this arrangement, saying,

“Yes, yes; we will start in the tenth month. Let the party be large; let not one of us fail of going.”

And he said, “Be it so; let the maiden’s request be complied with;” and when this understanding had been come to, the party broke up.

When the tenth month arrived, Pāoa started with a very large retinue, on a visit to Hauraki; they went in their canoes, and they stopped at Kerepēhi, and there they slept the first night; and the next day they continued to pull down the river, until they reached its mouth at Rawaki, and there they rested a little and partook of food; and as soon as the tide began to flow, they again embarked in their canoes, and entered the Hauraki river, and they went up the river rapidly and without pulling hard; for they went in with the flood tide. And when the people of the village at the entrance saw them, they shouted aloud to them with cries of welcome; so they landed there, and went towards the village in a body, with Pāoa in the midst of them; and as they all moved along, Pāoa towered high above them all; he looked, as he walked along, like the bird called the “stilts” moving in a flock of little birds. And as they moved towards the village, loud cries of “Welcome, welcome!” continued to resound; so they went gladly on until they reached the village. Pāoa had put on his old coarse cloak, made of the leaves of the tī tree: next his body he had a rough cloak, such as chiefs wear, outside of that a cloak made of flax, and over all his coarse cloak made of tī leaves. They all seated themselves in a courtyard; and then the people of the village all looked hard at them, trying to make out which was Pāoa, saying, “Who is that in the coarse cloak? perhaps it is the chief of whom we have heard so much.” They had not rested very long, when their hosts brought bundles of firewood and fern root, and stones to pound it on; then they lighted up clear, bright fires, and began to bake the pieces of fern root, and then to pound them with wooden mallets; and the noise of the rapidly beating mallets was loud as the confused murmur of a multitude. In a little time they laid out on one side the pieces of baked fern root, which they had duly pounded, with baskets of cooked fish; and the visitors, rising from their seats, went to partake of the food prepared for them; and Pāoa seated himself in the midst of them; and the people of the village (who still had their eyes fixed upon him) picked out a basket with fine salmon (kahawai) in it, and laid it before him for his portion; they thought, “We will find out whether he is an affected fellow, or a really great man. If he is a weak, conceited fellow, he will only eat the best food, and refuse the worst.” But Pāoa, just looking at the basket of beautiful fish they had placed before him, pushed it on one side for his companions to eat, pulled a flax dish, with the refuse food in it, towards him, and ate of that, and so fast, too, that he appeared hardly to have dipped his hand twice in it when he had finished it all; and when some of the people of the village saw the manner in which he ate, they said to one another, “After all, he’s a low fellow; see what stuff he eats;” but the old men of the village said,

“That man is a chief, he is only trying to appear to be a person of no importance.”

Presently Pāoa took another flax dish of refuse, dirty food, and swallowed that also. Then one of the people of the village, no longer able to restrain his curiosity, asked a young lad of the party of their guests, “Who is that man?” And he was answered by the lad, “That is Pāoa.”

When he heard this, he went to the place where the chiefs of the village were sitting by (watching their guests eat), and told them, “That is Pāoa; how dirtily he eats!”

Some of the people who heard this said, “It is Pāoa, the greedy;” thence that proverb has ever since been applied to the Ngāti Pāoa tribe; so that men say, “as greedy as a Ngāti Pāoa!”

Pāoa being thus at last recognised and being known to them all, they all collected and crowded round to gaze at him, saying, “It is truly no wonder that such reports have spread here of this man, that he was such a fine handsome fellow.”

When Pāoa’s people had all done eating, they all retired again, and took their seats upon the ground on one side. Then the people of the place brought forth a present for Pāoa—a “pueru” cloak, and a cloak which they were weaving, and which was nearly finished. They then all lay down to sleep.

As soon as the day broke, the travellers entered their canoes, and pulled away again upon their journey. As they came up the river, they were seen by the people of Turua, which is a fortified village; and the greater part of Pāoa’s people said, “We had better not land here;” but the people of the place waved their garments, and cried out to them, “Welcome, welcome!” Then Pāoa said, “When there is a call to a feast, open your ears” (Let the drum of your ears be then not thick); and the Ngāti Pāoa have ever since kept that saying amongst them as a proverb.

So they landed there, and they were received and treated just in the same manner as at the former village. Pāoa did not throw off his warm cloak manufactured of tī leaves, but continued to wear it; and the people kindled fires and cooked fern root for them, and they ate food and slept there; and as soon as day broke, they again embarked in their canoes and continued to pull up the river.

They next halted at Te Kari; for they were invited to stop there by the inhabitants of that fortified village: so they landed there, and they were all at once recognised by the people of that village; for some of them had formerly visited the Piako, and had seen Pāoa; but those persons in the village who had not previously seen Pāoa, came to gaze upon him, and admired him extremely. The tide was now ebbing, and it was difficult to pull against the stream; but in the evening the tide began to flow again, so they then sent off a canoe up the river to Ruawhea that they might hear that Pāoa had arrived in their district; and as they pulled along in the dark, the people of the village of Rangiora heard the noise of their paddles, and they called out, “Where do you we hear paddling in that canoe come from?”

And they answered them, “Oh, we belong to this district.”

Then they again asked them, “Which of our villages are you coming from?”

And they told them, “We come from Te Kari!”

Then they asked them, “What is the news there?”

And they replied, “Oh, not much; the great piece of news is, that Pāoa is there; and we are going up the river that Taharua may hear the news.”

Then they asked, “Will Pāoa and his party come up the river tomorrow?”

And they answered, “Yes, in the morning, as soon as the tide makes and some food has been cooked for them to eat before they start; but we must pull on.”

And the others answered, “Depart, then; pull well on your journey.”

And when the people at the village of Te Matai heard their paddles as they pulled up the river, they asked them just the same questions as they were asked at Rangiora; they then pulled on to the village of Te Mangarahi, and told the people there the very same news; and, in the same manner, as they passed the village of Tutu they told the news there. At last they landed at Opukeko, which was the fortified village of the chief Taharua. There also they asked them the news, saying, “What news have you brought, that you thus come pulling up the river by night?”

And they answered, “We come to let you know that here is Pāoa arrived at the village of Te Kari.”

And they asked, “Is it really Pāoa, or some of his people?” They replied, “It is really Pāoa.”

“When will he arrive?”

They answered, “By and by; he will probably not be able to travel quickly. The people of the villages will try to detain him; for he is a stranger in these parts, and they will wish to entertain him.”

Then the others asked them, “But which place is it that they are coming to visit, to stop there for some time as guests?”

They answered them, “It is here they are coming—to this village; therefore it was that we came here, that you might be aware of their intention.”

And the others replied, “It was very good of you.”

Then they all slept.

The next morning Tukutuku arose very early, and employed herself in melting fragrant gums to perfume her house with. As for the visitors who were coming to stay with them, they continued their journey, and pulled up the river as far as the village at Rangiora; and there, as the people called to them with cries of “Welcome, welcome!” they landed, and remained for that day and night.

The next morning they again resumed their journey; and when they reached the village of Mangarahi a large number of people ran out to welcome them, and to beg them to stay there; and being thus invited by the inhabitants of that village, they landed and remained there. As for Pāoa, he still would wear his old coarse cloak. And his companions said to him, “O, father! will you not throw off that old coarse thing? before much longer its stiff, rough collar will rub all the hair off the back of your head.”

And he answered, “Never mind; it will do well enough.” In all respects he behaved in the same way in this village as he had done in the others they had rested at.

They slept there that night, and the next morning they again continued to pull up the river. And when they reached the village of Tutu, its inhabitants all shouted out to them with cries of welcome and invited them to come on shore. And the people all went down to the river to escort Pāoa up to their village; and he stopped there, and passed the night at that village.

In the evening a messenger, who had been sent from Taharua’s fortified village, reached Tutu. He had been sent there to see if Pāoa had arrived so far upon his journey; and as none of them at Taharua’s village knew him, as he was a stranger, the messenger had been directed to observe his appearance, so as to be able to point him out from his companions when they arrived, that they might all know which was Pāoa. This messenger, having ascertained that Pāoa and his party intended the next morning to pull up to the village of Taharua, returned there the same evening; and when he reached the village, he told them that the guests who were coming to visit them would arrive there on the morrow.

When Tukutuku heard this, she spoke to her servants, saying, “Now, my people, rise early in the morning, and gather leaves to strew the courtyard and the house for the strangers.” She had already prepared scents and fragrant gums to perfume the house with; and having now given these orders to her people, they all retired to rest.

But the next day, very early in the morning, Tukutuku arose, and went and gave the necessary directions for preparing abundance of food for the strangers, and then returning she smeared the inside of her house with perfumes and sweet-smelling gums; for it was her house which was to be allotted to the strangers on their arrival; and when she had thus perfumed it, she drew close the sliding door and the window, that the perfume might not escape; so that the house might smell delightfully, and be agreeable to her guests when they arrived. She next caused the floor of the verandah in front of her house to be covered with clean fine mats for the strangers to sit upon.

The same morning the party who were coming to visit them continued their journey, and the people of the village of Tutu came with them, to escort them upon their way. As they pulled up the river, they were seen coming by the people of Taharua’s village, who were collected upon the top of the parapets of the fortification to salute them with songs of welcome; then was heard the cheering joyful sound of the ancient Māori song of welcome for strangers.

On they came, pulling straight for the landing place; and as they landed they were saluted with cries of “Welcome, welcome!” and they came on towards the village; and when Pāoa rose up in the canoe to land, he put on the same coarse old mat made of the leaves of the tī tree. All the rest of his party were dressed in handsome cloaks; he alone wore an old, exceedingly shabby coarse cloak. His friends were all quite vexed with him, and asked him to throw off that shabby old thing; but he only replied, “That’ll do; I’ll keep this cloak on.”

Although the rest were so well dressed, and Pāoa so badly, yet those who had not seen him before had not long to look before they distinguished which was him, and said, “There! That’s Pāoa!” because his appearance was so much superior to that of the others; and yet they could not see his good garments, because they were covered by his coarse old cloak; and as for his hair, it was all rough and disordered, twisted up behind by the high collar of his old cloak, so that his hair all stuck up and his head looked quite shaggy. His friends felt quite discontented; for they said they wished him to look to advantage there, where he was a stranger. Thus they went along on the path to the village through the crowd which had collected to look at the strangers. At length they entered the village, and the courtyard which had been strewed with leaves for their reception; and those who were in front seated themselves in the verandah of the house which had been prepared for them.

In the meantime Pāoa followed on, the main part of the people thronging round him to look at him. When he came up to the house, he called out to his party, “Let us all go inside the house, and leave the outside vacant for these people to sit there.”

Then those of his party who were in front went on, and some of them laying hold of the door of the house drew it back; and no sooner was the door opened than out issued a very delicious smell, the sweet scent of the perfume; and they all cried out, “Oh! oh! how very sweet the house smells!” But what did Pāoa care for the sweet perfume? And although the house was so beautified, and although the floor of it was covered with such beautiful variegated mats that he ought for very shame to have thrown aside his coarse old cloak, nevertheless he would not take it off, but, as soon as he had got into the house, lay down in it, to sleep in it, just as he was.

No long time elapsed ere food was spread before the strangers; it consisted of eels and sweet potatoes. As for Pāoa, he did not show himself outside the house, but ate his food inside it, and then lay down to sleep there again until evening, when the people of the village assembled to dance before the strangers; for amongst the natives of New Zealand the dances of the evening distinguish the village of a chief. When the ranks of the dancers were formed, Pāoa came out into the verandah of the house, and seated himself there to look on, but he did not mingle with the dancers. When the people of the village had finished their dancing and singing, their visitors stood up to dance and sing in their turn; and at length they also ceased.

Then, when their guests retired into their house, after the dances were over, the principal inhabitants of the village all crowded into it also, to hear what took place; and there also came young Tukutuku, the daughter of Taharua, the chief of the place, and she went and seated herself in the dark corner at the farthest end of the house, whence she could watch Pāoa without being seen. She often tried to draw near to Pāoa, but from shyness she could not do so; and although she stayed in the house with the others, talking until the morning broke, she never once approached him.

In the early morning, food was prepared for the visitors; and as soon as it was spread before them, they ate their food. Two days they remained there; and for two days and nights Tukutuku tried to approach Pāoa, but she could not overcome her shyness, and she came not near him. Upon the third day Pāoa told his people that they must return to their own place, that he felt dull and tired from stopping so long. The inhabitants of the village heard of this his intention, and so did Tukutuku. So the young chieftainess came to try to detain the strangers; and having come, she said, “I hear you are about to return.”

And her visitors answered her, “ ’Tis true.”

And she said to them, “Do we not give you food enough, that you leave us so soon? Nay, stop a little longer; then presently you shall return to your own village.”

And they replied, “Be it so.”

It was not yet evening when the servants of the young chieftainess appeared, bringing a feast for the strangers, and laid thousands of nicely dressed eels before them, so that her guests now, for the first time, were fully aware of her wealth and substance; and when night closed in, the dancers arranged themselves in ranks, and all the people of the village assembled, because the strangers were to start the next day; and they all continued for a long time to dance and sing, and at length ceased, and then they all assembled in the house of their guests. Then came the young chieftainess, Tukutuku, and seated herself at the door of the house. Pāoa, too, was lying at the side of the house, next to the door; that was the place he had occupied ever since his arrival; for that seat in a house is always set apart for a chief, and no inferior person may occupy it. And it was not long before the young girl, according to the custom of her country, stretched out her hand, and taking Pāoa’s hand, pressed it. Of course the young girl had told her father and her mother of her love for Pāoa, and they had given their consent to it; therefore it was that she stretched forth her hand to take Pāoa’s. But Pāoa did not like this at all; for he feared, if he accepted her love, that he and his party might be slain by her tribe. He thought that her parents had not consented to her wishes. In the meantime the young girl again tried to take his hand; but Pāoa rudely thrust her hand away.

Then also Pāoa felt so vexed about her, that he ordered his people to stop the song and dance. So the people of the place all broke up, and went out from the house of the strangers, and returned to their own homes, and the young girl was forced to go with them. When she reached her father, she told him how she had put forth her hand to take Pāoa’s; and the old man said to her, “Did not he appear pleased at this sign of your love?” and she answered,

“Alas! no.”

Then her mother said to her, “Go back again, and try again, and take some of your female friends as witnesses with you, lest the man say that your anxiety to gain his love arises from your own wishes alone. He is doubtless afraid lest he and his people should be slain. He thinks undoubtedly that your father and I have not given out consent. Go, and do not be afraid.”

Then the young girl went, with four of her female friends, she making the fifth; and she seated herself for a time outside in the open air (for she felt herself abashed at Pāoa having so rudely thrust her hand away), and she then told one of her companions to go and fetch him. When this female came to Pāoa, she said to him, “Come along alone with me.”

But Pāoa answered, “Where to?” and she said,

“Oh, just here. It is a young lady who sent me to you.”

Pāoa’s young men, observing this, said, “Oh, we had better all go together.”

But the female who had been sent to fetch Pāoa said, “No, no; do you all stop here; do not come.”

Then Pāoa’s people murmured amongst themselves, saying, “Who may this woman be?” and others of them answered,

“Oh, it is one of the female friends of Tukutuku, whom we see always going about with her in the daytime.”

And they answered them, “So it is; perhaps, then, Tukutuku sent her to fetch Pāoa.”

In the meantime Pāoa had gone off with the messenger. They went along together until they came to a house, in the verandah of which they found Tukutuku sitting with her female friends. The floor of the house was nicely covered with floor mats, and the house was made to smell sweetly from sweet-scented Tāwhiri leaves being scattered about it.

As soon as Tukutuku saw Pāoa coming, she welcomed him by crying out, “Welcome, welcome!” As for him, he sat down at the door of the house, for he felt quite ashamed when he saw that there were only females there. But Tukutuku’s friends called out to Pāoa, “You are welcome; pray walk inside the house.”

So Pāoa entered the house, and seated himself; as for Tukutuku, she and her friends were seated in the verandah. One side of the house was left for Pāoa. The house was lighted with a lamp, made of twisted flax dipped in shark’s oil; and one of Tukutuku’s companions kept on trimming the lamp which she held.

When Tukutuku and her friends had entered the house, her companions said, “We will go now.”

But Tukutuku stopped them, begging them to stay, saying, “Let us all pass the night here, until tomorrow’s dawn has well broken.” They still, however, persisted in leaving her; but she still detained them; so they remained, and they let the lamp go out, and they all prepared to sleep.

Then Pāoa said to Tukutuku, “Are you of noble birth?”

And she answered him, “I am nobly born. There is no other great prince in these districts except my father.”

Then he replied, “That is very good; as you say it, it is true, and pleases me.” Again he spoke to her, saying, “Is your nation a powerful nation?”

And the young girl answered, “They are so. If you would see the greatness of my race, look as far as the mountains of Moehau (at Cape Colville); they reach to there. Did you see them as you passed Rawaki?”

Pāoa answered her, “Yes, I did see them.”

And the young girl said again, “From thence my father’s territories extend right round the Cape and along the coast to the eastward as far as Katikati; there they end, that is the limit.”

Pāoa then spoke to her, saying, “As for me, I have no people over whom I rule, I am but a sojourner in the land; my own country is Whiapu (or the East Cape);” and then he related to her the manner and cause of his coming to that country, down to the time of his arriving at her village.

When the next day had well broken, Pāoa arose and returned to his friends, and to the people who formed his retinue, and the young girl and her companions returned to her mother’s house; and her companions spoke to her mother, saying, “Pāoa came to our house.”

And the old lady asked them, saying, “Who brought him there?”

And they answered, “We did; our young mistress told us to bring him there!”

And her mother answered, “It is well.”

Before long the news became spread abroad, that Pāoa and Tukutuku were man and wife. Then a war party, led by the young chiefs who would fain have had Tukutuku for their wife, came to molest Taharua, the father of the young girl, and to demand a payment from him, and they said they would also attack and rob Pāoa and his people out of revenge; but Taharua stopped them, saying, “Let the war party rob me alone; but do not go to our guests. What right have you to trouble men who have done no wrong?” In truth, the young girl was betrothed to no man; she avoided all her lovers, she did not like any of them; therefore the war party molested Taharua without any just cause or reason. Yet that day many war parties came to molest and rob Taharua; and then they ceased, there was an end of them.

Finally those who accompanied Pāoa paddled away to their homes again; but he remained with his young wife, with Tukutuku. When a month had expired, he said to her that he was anxious to return to his own village on the Piako. And the young wife answered, “So? Well, then, let us go together, and make our journey in such a manner that you may see all my subjects and all my relations, and that they may see me, lest they get vexed at my long tarrying away from them; for it is some time since I sent to them, saying, ‘I am about to come down the river to see you!’ ”

Pāoa replied to her, “Yes, yes; do let us go together.”

So they rested that night, and next morning, as soon as the sun rose, they got into their canoes and paddled down the river, and they landed at each one of the same villages which Pāoa had stopped at when he came up the river, village for village, until they came out of the mouth of the river into the gulf; and by this time her subjects had given to their young chieftainess two large canoes full of baskets of shellfish, which had been taken from their shells and then strung upon strings and dried in the sun. Thus Pāoa saw how great was the esteem in which they held his young wife, so that he said, “Nothing could be better than his young wife for a great chieftainess for the country.”

Having quitted the river, they paddled on and landed at Tararu, and stopped there, and his young wife left there the presents of dried shellfish which she had received, intending to take them on board the canoes again upon her return; and they slept that night at Tararu.

The next morning, when the sun arose, they again paddled on upon their journey, until they reached Te Puru, where they landed, and there a present of dried fish was made to them; and they returned the same day to Waiau.

There Pāoa first tasted the mussels of Waiau, which place belonged to his wife; and he liked that place very much on account of the goodness of its mussels; then they continued their homeward journey from that place, and, as they returned, six canoes full of baskets of dried shellfish were given to them; and when they again reached Tararu, they began to return up the river towards the Piako. When they arrived at Pareparenga, Tukutuku desired the people to give her a supply of fish, and they obeyed her orders; and Pāoa was therefore much pleased with the people of Pareparenga, and said that his wife should indeed be a ruler over them. Thus she continued to act towards all the people that they met with upon their journey, until they reached Pāoa’s own village; they there presented him with a canoe full of dried fish; presents of dried eels had been made to them from place to place, as they pulled along the shore. And the people of Pāoa’s village were all charmed with Tukutuku; they all quite devoted themselves to her. She treated them most kindly, and they in return dealt very affectionately with her. And when all the provisions she had brought with her were consumed, from the liberal manner in which she shared them with Pāoa’s people, she, in no way daunted, began to work most industriously to collect new supplies, by digging up the roots of the whanake, and of the pōhue, and of the kārito, and by collecting aruhe and freshwater mussels (unios). And when Pāoa’s people saw this, they exclaimed, “It is no wonder that the fame of this girl spread so far and wide; is not she truly industrious?” And when they saw their chieftainess labour so industriously, they for very shame began to labour also: hitherto they had not known the value of the above sorts of food; and partly from that cause, partly from their indolence, partly because those sorts of food were so common, they had not taken the trouble to collect them. But now they repeated the proverbs—“The deeds of a real chief surpass those of other men;” and, “The hard inside heart of a Tawa tree differs much, in the uses it can be applied to, from the soft outside sap of the tree;” and, “Well done! you are a chief of men indeed!”

The chieftainess dwelt there, and greatly increased the number of the new tribe she was collecting round her; many resorted to her; at first she had but very few dependants; but from her generosity and graciousness they now became many, so that her fortified village was thickly inhabited. And she had many children; for ten had been born to her. One of them was her renowned son, Horowhenua; he was the youngest, the lastborn of her children.

Pāoa dwelt there with her too: he had grown old, so that he was forced to support his steps with a staff. At last his affection for his first children broke forth; and he said to his sons who were with him, “My children, let me be taken to see your elder brothers.”

They all assented to his wish but Horowhenua; and he said, “Sirs, they will set our sire a task to do; those children of his are a thoughtless set.”

His brothers asked him, “What task will they give him to do?”

And he answered them, “He is aged, and a sacred person, and they will detain him there, to bless their plantations of sweet potatoes for them, that they may bring forth abundantly; but take him there, as you seem to wish it.”

But they said, “Nay, but rather let him go with twenty chosen men of our people to take care of him.”

Horowhenua answered them, “ ’Tis well; then if our brethren detain him there, let those who go with him return here to us, that we may be certified by them that he is so detained; then will we go and bring him back here again.”

His brothers answered him, “So be it.”

Then he said to his father Pāoa, “Sir, do not delay long there. If you had been younger, it would have been well that you should have been longer absent; but now that your days must be so few, we cannot afford to lose any of them: and as for this, also, remember that none would think it fitting that an aged man, as good as dead, should have a task appointed him to do.”

And Pāoa answered, “Oh, you don’t think they will give me some task to do?”

And Horowhenua replied, “They will give you a task. Who can believe they will treat you with the consideration that we do? But at least delay not long away from us; remain with them for ten days (that will be long enough) and then return to us. Certainly you should see your children.”

Pāoa answered, “ ’Tis well; I will sleep here this night, and as the morrow dawns I will depart upon my journey.”

So Pāoa started to see his first family; and as they separated from their friends to go upon their road, Horowhenua said to those who were sent with the old man to take care of him, “If they detain him there who we commit to your charge, return here speedily, that we may all go and fetch him back with us;” and they answered him,

“It shall be so.”

Then they continued their journey, and reached the top of the range at Tikitikimaurea; and Pāoa beheld from thence his own former abode, and the abode of his children, and he wept; and as he gazed on the Waikato district, and saw the fires at the village of Waitawheta sending up columns of smoke, he told those who accompanied him that there was the dwelling place of his children, and he wept again; and then they proceeded on their journey. And they halted for the night and slept upon the road, for they travelled slowly from having Pāoa under their care; for he was old, and stayed his steps with a staff.

When the day broke, again they went on their way, and just as the evening closed in they reached the outskirts of the village; and as soon as the inhabitants of it saw them, they began to call out, to warn the others, “Strangers! strangers! here are strangers coming here.”

And one ran to meet them to find out who they were, and he, finding out that it was Pāoa, ran back again, and, being questioned as to who the strangers were by the crowd who had assembled at the outcry, he told them, “It is Pāoa, and he has grown very aged, and supports his steps with a staff.”

As for Pāoa, he stopped with his party at the first house which was inhabited that he came to on the outskirts of the village; but his sons remained in the fortress of Waitawheta, because this was the first time that the old chief had returned to see his children since he had separated himself from them and from their mother.

The next morning the old man took his belt to gird himself with, and said to those who accompanied them, “Now let us go to the fortified village, that I may see my children;” and they answered,

“Be it so.” Then came those who had been appointed to conduct him to the village, and those who had been sent to bring him a present of food, that he and his people might be refreshed before the ceremonies of weeping and lamenting took place at his meeting his sons.

Pāoa bid those who had accompanied him to eat heartily of this food, and they did so; and when their meal was ended the messenger who had been sent to conduct them said, “Now let us proceed to their village;” and Pāoa answered,

“Certainly; so now, my friends, get on your backs again the loads which you have carried so far, and let us start.”

Then when those in the fortified village who had climbed up upon the fences, or crowded outside the gates, saw Pāoa and his party coming along, they raised the usual cries of welcome, and waved their garments; and the old man wept aloud as he came slowly towards them. And so, he weeping and they loudly shouting “Welcome, welcome!” he came slowly on; and when he reached the open space in the centre of the fortified village, all the people wept aloud, and their voices sounded loud as howl a great company of dogs; and they continued thus to lament aloud throughout the day, until evening closed in; then they all collected in a semicircle, and seated themselves on the ground, and then arose the sons of Pāoa and made speeches welcoming their father in the presence of the whole assembly, and the old man rose up and addressed his sons and all their people in their turn. Then were many flax baskets of food brought forth, and piled up to a very goodly height, and they all feasted until after nightfall. The principal people then assembled in the house which had been set apart for Pāoa, that they might mutually hear and tell the news; and the hearts of the sons of Pāoa were filled with gladness towards their aged sire; for they thought within themselves, “Surely he is come to bless our plantations of sweet potatoes for us, that they may produce abundantly.”

After a time his sons said to him, “Great is our good fortune, that you have thus come to us.”

And he answered them, “Why so, my children?”

And they answered him, “That you may bless for us our plantations of sweet potatoes.”

And when the old man heard them say this he laughed; and his sons said to him, “Why laughest thou, O our father?”

And he answered them, “Nay, I did but laugh.”

But they answered him again, “Nay, but tell us wherefore thou didst laugh, O father.”

And he replied, “It was but something your servant Horowhenua said.”

And they answered him, “Whose saying do you speak of?”

And he replied, “It was a direction given by your servant Horowhenua.”

And they answered, “As for us, we regard not what he says.”

But the old man said to them, “Look, now, my children; you had better be careful what you do, for he is strong and fierce.”

But they answered him with the proverb, “Who fears for a fierceness not more terrible than that of a rat?”

Again he said to them, “My children, his elder brothers said not a word against my coming here; he alone opposed my wishes, objecting to my coming here; he alone opposed my wishes, objecting to my coming here; he would hardly let me come.”

And they said, “Very well, then, we will not now let you return to him.”

But he answered, “Nay, do not detain me; for then your servant will come and take me forcibly away.”

And they said, “Let him not venture to come here to take you away; for if he does, we will slay him.”

Those who had been sent to bear Pāoa company sat by and heard these things said, and straightway they returned; and when they reached the Piako, even the village from which they had started, Horowhenua questioned them, saying, “Is there any news?”

And they said, “Yes, there is news: Pāoa is detained and will not be permitted to return here.”

Horowhenua then asked, “Who detains him?”

And they replied, “His sons.”

And he said, “Aye, I knew it would be so.”

Then they added, “But Pāoa spoke to them and said, ‘Now, take care; for if you detain me here, your servant will presently come and take me away by force, he will not remain where he is, he will come for me;’ and your brothers said to him, ‘Who will come and do this?’ and he answered, ‘Horowhenua will come and do it;’ and they replied, ‘If he ventures to come here we will slay him;’ then Pāoa answered him, ‘That you are not strong enough to do; your servant is like a mighty fish, which cannot be held in the fisher’s net, but rends it;’ and they again replied, ‘Nay, rather we say, is a net so strong that it is a fit enemy for great whales?’ ”

When Horowhenua heard this he said, “Well, they shall have what they wish. I shall see them lying dead before me ere long.”

Then he rose, and said aloud to those around him, “Gird yourselves for the battle, start for your journey to bring back our chief and father. Before he went, I cautioned you, saying, ‘Let him not go;’ it is you who have brought this upon us.”

And his elder brothers dared not to open their mouths, or to say a word in reply, because they felt that their advice had turned out badly. So Horowhenua commanded them all, saying, “Gird yourselves for war.” And his brothers consenting, their warriors all did so, and proceeded on their expedition; one hundred and forty warriors started to bring home Pāoa by force.

So they travelled upon their way, and by the evening they had reached the summit of the range at Tikitikimaurea, and looked over the district of Waikato; and there they could see the fires of the village of Waitawheta burning brightly with long columns of smoke ascending from them. There in the village was Pāoa dwelling with his sons and six hundred of their warriors. When they had for some time gazed over the extensive district which lay beneath them Horowhenua said, “Let us descend from the mountain range, and sleep at its base, at the head of the river Mangawara.” Then they journeyed on, till they reached the place he had named. He said, “Halt! we will make our camp here; at the morning’s light we will go to the fortified village of my brothers, and urge them to let our father return with us; and if his sons then refuse to let him go, it is enough, what more can we do? Then we will return; we can do no more; we shall at least have come to fetch him back with us.” His brothers assented to what he said, and they discussed the matter; and when they had ended their conversation, food was shared out for all; and when they had eaten, all slept.

They had not slept long when the seer Tīpā cried out, and roused them, saying, “You who sleep there, awake, arise; I have been troubled by visions which bode ill; the omens have filled me with alarms: there will be a battle tomorrow in which many will be slain. The omens warned me, making me start on my right or fortunate side; and then on my left or enemies’ side I felt it too. Then four times my left side shuddered, and then four times my right side; thence the victory is to be to us. So I will address myself to sleep again; then, if the spirit who is propitious to our foes repays the omens of the spirit friendly to us by making my left side again involuntarily to shudder, the omens will be unpropitious, and this very night we will return, in which case the battle upon the morrow, in which the gods foretell so many will fall, will not take place.”

Then another of the party spoke, and said that he, too, had shuddered in his sleep, and, starting, had thrown his arms out from his side as if striking down a foe, which was a good omen; on the other part, a third said that he had dreamt they were all eating the provisions they had brought with them—a dream which portended much evil. Before they had slept they had intended at the dawn of day to have gone to the fortified village as friendly visitors, and then to have tried to bring Pāoa back with them. Now from these evil-boding dreams, they all feared the thoughts of approaching the village.

When it drew near to the morning, the seer Tīpā rose again, and said, “Their gods have given me no bad omens in return for the good one I had received; I have kept expecting it in vain, but the dreadful shuddering has not returned to me. Lo, I see the signs of dawn; awake, arise, and let us arrange our plans.” Then the warriors all arose, and Tīpā addressing them said, “Without doubt the old and sacred man has, according to the custom of our priests, gone out in the early morning light to bless the plantations of sweet potatoes belonging to his sons, which lie immediately outside the fence of their fortified village;” and the warriors all agreed that such was probably the case. Then said Tīpā, “Which, then, of you will go and see?”

And Horowhenua answered, “That be my care. I will go and see; and if I find him I will bring him here.” And Tīpā answered, “ ’Tis well; and having got there, delay not.”

So Horowhenua rose up; and taking with him his two-handed wooden sword, he departed. At the very same time the old man had just arrived in the midst of the plantation of sweet potatoes, and was blessing them; and having blessed the division of the plantation which belonged to one of his sons, he had gone on to bless the other; and as soon as he had stuck into the ground his consecrated staff, he repeated this incantation, proper for the occasion:—

“There stands the consecrated staff;
It is the staff sacred to the God Turora, to Rereahi,
And to Tūrongo.
There is the holy staff;
There, there it stands.
There stands the staff,
With the toctoc[29] sacred to the God Haka
And to Hāua.
There stands the holy staff;
There, there it stands.”

The instant the aged chief had finished his blessing, there stood Horowhenua before him. Day had not yet fully broken; but the dawn was just breaking. The old man, seeing someone, said, “Who is this?”

And Horowhenua answered, “It is I.” And his father knew his voice, and he murmured lowly in reply, for he feared lest he should be slain by his other sons; for there were very many warriors in the fortified village—there were six hundred of them.

Then his father asked him, “Who have borne you company?” And his son ran over all their names for him; and when he had finished them all, the old man was filled with pity for them, and with wonder at their boldness.

Then Horowhenua said to him, “Let us begone, the day begins to break.” And his father consenting, they hurried away together.

In the meantime the people in the fortified village kept listening for the voice of the old man, when he might call them out, having finished his mystic ceremonies. And having waited a long time without hearing it, some of them said, “Surely he has become tired and has fallen asleep.”

His sons answered, “Some of you go and see.”

So some of their people went to search for him; and they called as they went, “Where are you, Sir, where are you, Sir?” At length, not finding him, some of them said, “Perhaps he has fallen asleep on the sand at the river’s edge.” So they searched along the banks, and there they found on the sand footprints going right inland. By this time day had so fully broken that men could see each other’s features; therefore the footprints could be seen quite plainly, and they saw that they were those of Horowhenua and Pāoa; so they knew that the old man had been carried off by Horowhenua. So they raised the cry of “He has been carried off, taken away by Horowhenua.” And Pāoa’s sons heard the outcry, and they sprang to their feet, and they and their six hundred men rushed out of the fortress: so the fugitives were pursued. And when Horowhenua reached his brothers and his warriors, he gave no time to welcome their father and chief with tears and weeping according to the usual custom, but they went straight upon their way homewards, for they heard the uproar from the pursuers in the distance. And ere long the pursuers came in sight of them, and saw them winding up a steep ascent of the mountain range: those who were leading the old chief and helping him on his way were in front; and Horowhenua brought up the rear with the rear guard. On came the six hundred warriors in pursuit, dashing at them as a Kahawai (salmon) darts at a fly, and soon drew near them. Already had those who were in front, conducting Pāoa, won the very summit of the ridge at Tikitikimaurea: then the old man said, “Children, leave me here, and save yourselves. I am an old man; why should you run this risk for me? My life is not worth that of one of my children.”

In the meantime their pursuers pressed close upon them. And Horowhenua rushed back in front of the rear guard, and then took a firm stand, brandishing his weapon. When Horowhenua thus stood firm, the whole hundred and forty warriors of his party took their stand with him; and then when Horowhenua made a charge to the rear, they all charged with him. Here some of his warriors were slain; five of them fell. At last Horowhenua was left fighting alone, right in the front of the battle; and his half-brother Toawhena seeing him there, strikes a blow at him with his weapon; Horowhenua parries it with his, and away it glances. Then Toawhena in his turn is fiercely smitten by Horowhenua; and down, down he goes. In the meantime up comes Toapoto to his brother’s aid; he lets fly a blow at Horowhenua, which he parries on his right side, and returns a left-handed blow, which fells Toapoto to the earth. And when the warriors saw their two chiefs thus slain, they broke and fled in confusion, but they were pursued and slaughtered; four hundred of them were slain, two hundred of them escaped; and then Pāoa was carried off in triumph by his children.

The History of Paoa, the Ancestor of the Ngatipaoa Tribe

When Paoa came to this country, bordering on the river Thames, Waihou and Piako, he came from the southward, from the Ngati-kahunghu tribe; the Whai-a-Pawa (East Cape) was the country of his ancestors; his father was named Rongo-tiu-moe-whara.

Whilst Paoa was living with his father, he had a quarrel with his wife; and she, being overcome with shame, went away to other places, to stop there, and mourn and weep for the manner in which she had been treated by her husband. For a long time after she had gone Paoa remained, expecting that his wife would come back again; and after he had expected her return for very many days, at last he surmised she must have gone to some very distant place; so he thought, “Perhaps she has gone to a great distance, I will go and find her.”

Then he set off on his journey, with his slave as a travelling companion, and went through many villages searching for his wife, and she could not be found; for when she heard the voice of Paoa she hid herself. However he continued to travel in search of her, but as he could nowhere find his wife, at last he returned to his father and his relations, that he might once more see them. And when he arrived at their village he wept towards them, saying, “If we cannot find her, I and my slave will return to search this town and that town, and this village and that village. If we cannot find her, I and my slave will still continue to search for her.”

page 195

Then his father spoke, saying, “Yes, go, my son, but take some of your brethren with you to bear you company upon the road.” And Paoa answered, “'Tis well, I will take them; if we find her, then we will all return to you; if we cannot find her, I will send my brothers back to you; but, as for myself, I will not in that case return to you, but I and my slave will persevere in our efforts, and will continue until we have searched every town and village.” His father replied, “Be it so, my son.”

Then Paoa and his brothers started and traversed the forests until they came out into the Taupo country, and at last reached the Lake of Taupo; but Paoa's wife could not be found there; so he then said to his brethren, “Now, then, my young brothers, you must return to our father, to cheer up his heart once more.” But his brothers earnestly entreated him to let them still bear him company, and spoke most affectionately to their eldest brother; but Paoa spoke angrily to them, and positively ordered them to return. So they went on their way home again, and returned from Taupo to the Whai-a-Pawa.

So Paoa pursued his journey in peace and reached Tongariro, and thence came out upon the Taranaki country; but his wife could nowhere be found. Then he pursued his journey up the west coast, until he came out upon the river Waikato, some distance above its mouth, in the interior of the country, and stopped at a village there. And when the people of the village saw Paoa, they questioned his slave, saying, “Who is this?” and they were answered by the slave, “It is Paoa.” And they asked the slave again, “Whence does he come?” And the slave told them thus, “We come together from the eastward, from the rising sun.” Then they questioned further, saying, “What made you undertake this journey?” And the slave answered them, “We came to try to find his wife, and we have searched everywhere, and, lo! she has not yet been found.” Then the people of the village said to the slave, “Why should such a woman be sought after in this manner by you? here is a maiden as a wife for him; why should you search further? If there are maidens in your country, have we not as good here? Why should such a page 196 woman be sought after in such a manner by you? Lo, here is a maiden as a wife for your master.” Then Paoa was married to a maiden of that place.

Then he removed a little way from that village to Kaitotehe, and dwelt there, and made it his permanent residence; and two male children were there born to him; the eldest was named Toa-whena, the second Toa-poto. And after he had lived there for some time, Paoa cast his glances on a very beautiful young woman, but who was a slave of very mean origin; and Paoa made love to that woman, caught by her beauty—that was the cause that led Paoa to make her his slave wife—and he deserted his wife of high rank and his children. When Paoa's slave saw that his master had deserted his wife of rank, he said to himself, “As for me, I will return to my lady.” So he returned to his mistress, and continued to live with her as her slave; and, in order to support her children, his mistress was obliged to work with her slave. And they cultivated together a garden of sweet potatoes, and were fortunate, for in the first year they had one hundred baskets of sweet potatoes, and in the second year they had two hundred baskets of sweet potatoes; and the slave and his lady went on working most industriously, and extending their cultivations.

Paoa and the woman he had taken as a slave-wife also laboured together, and they extended their cultivations as much as they could; but strangers kept on dropping in, consuming from time to time a few basketfuls of their produce; for visitors who came never went to any other house; they naturally all resorted to Paoa, that it might be seen that they regarded him as the principal person; and thus it went on each year.

At last, after the third season of harvest, some distant connections of Paoa's principal wife came in their canoe into the river Horotiu, and landed at Pepepe, where was their young female relation, the wife of Paoa. So the travellers asked her, saying, “Where shall we find Paoa?” And she told them, “Oh, Paoa's place is a little lower down the river, at Kaitotehe.” Then the travellers went straight on board their canoe again, and pulled down the river to Kaitotehe, and landed there; and there was page 197 Paoa. And some of his people raised the cry of “Strangers! strangers! Here are strangers come to visit Paoa!”

Now it happened that the slave-wife of Paoa had just come back from the forests, from gathering the curved sprouts of the mamaku trees, and sprouts of the mauku, and such coarse kinds of wild food as are eaten in times of scarcity; and as soon as she had come back she bound up the sprouts she had collected in the leaves of the wharangi and of the karamu, that they might be so cooked as to be juicy and tender, and then put them under the hot ashes of the fire. She was just caught doing this by the strangers who had arrived; and off she ran on one side, leaving her vegetables cooking, not having had time to take them out of the fire. In came the strangers, straight up to the village from the river; and whilst some of them went up to the houses, others came straight to the fire where the food was cooking; and seeing the hot ashes heaped up, they said amongst themselves, “Some one is cooking eels here;” and those amongst them who were very glad at the thought of getting such good food said, “Ah! there are no doubt some nice eels cooking in this fire.” And the travellers lingered about the fire, waiting until the person the food belonged to should come back again, and, taking off the fire, should take out the dainties they longed for. But not a bit did the woman come back to her fire again; she was nearly dead with alarm lest the strangers should see the food cooking in her oven, and should say, “See what beggarly stuff this wretched creature eats.” As for Paoa, too, he could not open his mouth to say a word, he felt so disgraced at not having any food to set before his guests.

At last Paoa told his slave-wife to run to his principal wife and bring a few sweet potatoes for the visitors; but the woman said to him, “What is the use of my going? she will not let us have any.” But Paoa answered, “Never mind, you had better go; even if you get none, you can but try.”

So the woman hurried off to carry Paoa's message; and whilst she was still coming, and a long way off, she was seen by the children of Paoa's principal wife; and off ran the children to their page 198 mother, and told her, saying, “Here comes that slave-wife of Paoa's.” When their mother heard what they said, off she ran too, and got into her house to hide herself. However, the other woman came straight on to the house, for she had seen Paoa's wife go into it; and when she reached the doorway she bent down, and, peeping into the house, there she saw Paoa's wife working away, weaving a garment of flax. So she saluted the wife of Paoa, and his principal wife saluted her too; and when the ceremonies of the salutation were completed, the slave-wife delivered her message, and said, “I have been sent here by Paoa to fetch a little food for the strangers who have just arrived.” Now Paoa's principal wife had guessed very readily that the woman had been sent by Paoa to fetch provisions; so she in her turn spoke and said, “I send provisions for the strangers indeed! Whence should I have provisions? Am I a man, that I should be strong to labour and till the ground? Has a poor woman strength to labour? I will not part with any of my hard-earned little store of food. I shall keep it to nourish my deserted children, lest they perish from want.”

All this time Paoa was waiting anxiously until his messenger returned; and as soon as ever she came back he questioned her, saying, “Well, what does she say?” and the woman answered, “She will not give any provisions; she says she has nothing to give her children, and they are famishing.” When Paoa heard this, he had not a word to say; he felt so completely abashed, that he could give no answer; but he turned to the strangers and said, “We have no food here, and shall be very hungry, so that we can have no pleasant conversation. It is only when the appetite is satisfied that conversation runs agreeably.”

The strangers still sat until evening began to close in, till almost starving with hunger; then his guests returned to their own village. On the very same day that they had arrived they got into their canoe again, and pulled away. As for poor Paoa, he was left overwhelmed with shame, and he said that he would abandon that country, and be off and seek some new abode; and that very night he departed a fugitive from his own place.

page 199

Thus Paoa started in the night, and he went straight from the Waikato for Hauraki, up the valley of the Manga-wara Creek, which runs out into the Waikato, at the base of Mount Taupiri, on its eastern side. When the day dawned, Paoa was still pushing hurriedly on; and at last he reached the hills of Tikitikimaurea, where the Mangawara has its source; and ascending these, he rested there, and saw the Waikato lying far behind him, and Hauraki lying before him: and then he wept sore for grief at leaving his children, and his people, and his place. He wept long as he thought of these things; and when tears had somewhat assuaged his grief, he bid them all farewell, and ceased sorrowing.

Then he resumed his journey again, and pushed straight on for the river Piako, and at last came out upon the banks of that river, and stopped at a fortified village named Mirimirirau, and he stopped there and dwelt there amongst the people of that place, and they became a people for him, and they dealt kindly with him, and he was as a chief to them, and he dwelt there; and a year passed away, and by degrees the fame of Paoa spread into the district of Hauraki, and at length it reached the village of Ruawhea.

And it chanced that a visiting party started from the fortified village where Paoa dwelt, and went to Ruawhea, where a large part of the people of Hauraki were assembled; and when they saw the party of visitors approaching, a cry was raised, “These strangers come from a great distance; they come from the river Piako.” Then, indeed, loud were the cries of “Welcome! welcome!” which were raised; and the visitors took up their abode in some of the buildings which belonged to Tukutuku (she was the daughter of the chief of Ruawhea); and they seated themselves there, and had not sat long—indeed, but a very short time—when their hospitable young hostess had fires lighted to roast fern-root in, to stay their appetites whilst other food was prepared; and they rose up and went to the fires, and partook of the fern-root whilst better food was preparing; and when the food was cooked, it was spread out before them, and consisted chiefly of delicate eels. When they had finished their meal, they lay down to rest; page 200 and when day broke they went to the residences of other people, each one going to the place of those friends he had come to visit.

After many days the several persons of this visiting party all assembled again at the residence of Tukutuku previous to returning home, and they rested there, intending to sleep there. As soon as it grew dark, a bright fire was lighted in the house, and the dancers were all ranged in order; for the residence of a chief was known by the people dancing there.

Whilst the dance was going on, Tukutuku took an opportunity of questioning some of the strangers, saying, “Where is he of whom we have heard so much here?” Then the strangers answered, “Whom do you mean?” The maiden replied, “I mean Paoa;” and they answered her, “Oh, he is living on the Piako.” And she said, “Do you think we shall ever see Paoa here?” and they replied, “We cannot tell; perhaps he will come here.”

The young maiden was still unmarried. Many chiefs flocked about her to try to win her favour, but she never would consent to take them. Now when her parents heard their daughter asking in this manner after Paoa, they said to one another, “Why, surely the girl must have taken a fancy to Paoa: do you hear how she is asking after him?”

When the morning broke, the party of visitors departed for the Piako, filled with wonder at the greatness and rank of the maiden, and the number of her dependents. Her real greatness was shown by her courteousness and generosity to all her dependents; and when they saw this, their hearts were moved, and they brought to her as presents large quantities of food, such as dried shell-fish and other delicacies, so that she could show great hospitality to strangers.

When the party from Paoa's fortified village, who had been visiting at Hauraki, arrived near their own place, the people of the fortress saw them returning, and they waved their garments and cried out, “Hasten here, hasten here!” as a welcome to them upon their return; so those who were returning landed, and entered the fortress, and seated themselves in the court-yard, and page 201 began to relate all that they had seen and heard. And they talked until evening, and Paoa was seated with them; and as they talked they mentioned the great rank of Tukutuku, the maiden whom they had seen, and they said to Paoa, “Oh! father, the maiden questioned us about you.” And he replied, “About whom, say you, did the maiden question you?” And they said, “She questioned us about you, saying, ‘Where is the man whose renown has been so much heard of here?’ and we answered her, ‘Who is it you are asking after?’ and she told us, ‘It is Paoa I am speaking of;’ and then the maiden said to us, ‘I should much like to see him; for his fame is noised over the whole country, far and wide.’ Then we told her, ‘he is to be found at his own fortress;’ and she questioned us again, saying, ‘Where is his fortress?’ And we answered, ‘At Mirimirirau.’ Then she said to us, ‘Do you think he will visit my residence, or not?’ And we answered the maid, ‘Who knows? perhaps he will visit this place.’” When Paoa heard this, he said to them, “Wait a little, we will all go and see her in the tenth month, when our crops are harvested and stored; let us go on our journey unembarrassed with work, lest whilst we are absent on the journey our hearts should feel anxious about our homes;” and all his people fell in with this arrangement, saying, “Yes, yes; we will start in the tenth month. Let the party be large; let not one of us fail of going.” And he said, “Be it so; let the maiden's request be complied with;” and when this understanding had been come to, the party broke up.

When the tenth month arrived, Paoa started with a very large retinue, on a visit to Hauraki; they went in their canoes, and they stopped at Kerepehi, and there they slept the first night; and the next day they continued to pull down the river, until they reached its mouth at Rawaki, and there they rested a little and partook of food; and as soon as the tide began to flow, they again embarked in their canoes, and entered the Hauraki river, and they went up the river rapidly and without pulling hard; for they went in with the flood tide. And when the people of the village at the entrance saw them, they shouted aloud to them with cries of welcome; so they landed there, and went towards the village in a body, with page 202 Paoa in the midst of them; and as they all moved along, Paoa towered high above them all; he looked, as he walked along, like the bird called the “stilts” moving in a flock of little birds. And as they moved towards the village, loud cries of “Welcome, welcome!” continued to resound; so they went gladly on until they reached the village. Paoa had put on his old coarse cloak, made of the leaves of the Ti-tree: next his body he had a rough cloak, such as chiefs wear, outside of that a cloak made of flax, and over all his coarse cloak made of Ti-leaves. They all seated themselves in a court-yard; and then the people of the village all looked hard at them, trying to make out which was Paoa, saying, “Who is that in the coarse cloak? perhaps it is the chief of whom we have heard so much.” They had not rested very long, when their hosts brought bundles of firewood and fern-root, and stones to pound it on; then they lighted up clear, bright fires, and began to bake the pieces of fern-root, and then to pound them with wooden mallets; and the noise of the rapidly beating mallets was loud as the confused murmur of a multitude. In a little time they laid out on one side the pieces of baked fern-root, which they had duly pounded, with baskets of cooked fish; and the visitors, rising from their seats, went to partake of the food prepared for them; and Paoa seated himself in the midst of them; and the people of the village (who still had their eyes fixed upon him) picked out a basket with fine salmon (kahawai) in it, and laid it before him for his portion; they thought, “We will find out whether he is an affected fellow, or a really great man. If he is a weak, conceited fellow, he will only eat the best food, and refuse the worst.” But Paoa, just looking at the basket of beautiful fish they had placed before him, pushed it on one side for his companions to eat, pulled a flax dish, with the refuse food in it, towards him, and ate of that, and so fast, too, that he appeared hardly to have dipped his hand twice in it when he had finished it all; and when some of the people of the village saw the manner in which he ate, they said to one another, “After all, he's a low fellow; see what stuff he eats;” but the old men of the village said, “That man is a chief, he is only trying to appear to be a person of no importance.”

page 203

Presently Paoa took another flax dish of refuse, dirty food, and swallowed that also. Then one of the people of the village, no longer able to restrain his curiosity, asked a young lad of the party of their guests, “Who is that man?” And he was answered by the lad, “That is Paoa.” When he heard this, he went to the place where the chiefs of the village were sitting by (watching their guests eat), and told them, “That is Paoa; how dirtily he eats!” Some of the people who heard this said, “It is Paoa, the greedy;” thence that proverb has ever since been applied to the Ngatipaoa tribe; so that men say, “as greedy as a Ngatipaoa!”

Paoa being thus at last recognised and being known to them all, they all collected and crowded round to gaze at him, saying, “It is truly no wonder that such reports have spread here of this man, that he was such a fine handsome fellow.”

When Paoa's people had all done eating, they all retired again, and took their seats upon the ground on one side. Then the people of the place brought forth a present for Paoa—a “pueru” cloak, and a cloak which they were weaving, and which was nearly finished. They then all lay down to sleep.

As soon as the day broke, the travellers entered their canoes, and pulled away again upon their journey. As they came up the river, they were seen by the people of Turua, which is a fortified village; and the greater part of Paoa's people said, “We had better not land here;” but the people of the place waved their garments, and cried out to them, “Welcome, welcome!” Then Paoa said, “When there is a call to a feast, open your ears” (Let the drum of your ears be then not thick); and the Ngatipaoa have ever since kept that saying amongst them as a proverb.

So they landed there, and they were received and treated just in the same manner as at the former village. Paoa did not throw off his warm cloak manufactured of Ti-leaves, but continued to wear it; and the people kindled fires and cooked fern-root for them, and they ate food and slept there; and as soon as day broke, they again embarked in their canoes and continued to pull up the river.

page 204

They next halted at Te Kari; for they were invited to stop there by the inhabitants of that fortified village: so they landed there, and they were all at once recognised by the people of that village; for some of them had formerly visited the Piako, and had seen Paoa; but those persons in the village who had not previously seen Paoa, came to gaze upon him, and admired him extremely. The tide was now ebbing, and it was difficult to pull against the stream; but in the evening the tide began to flow again, so they then sent off a canoe up the river to Ruawhea that they might hear that Paoa had arrived in their district; and as they pulled along in the dark, the people of the village of Rangiora heard the noise of their paddles, and they called out, “Where do you we hear paddling in that canoe come from?” And they answered them, “Oh, we belong to this district.” Then they again asked them, “Which of our villages are you coming from?” And they told them, “We come from Te Kari!” Then they asked them, “What is the news there?” And they replied, “Oh, not much; the great piece of news is, that Paoa is there; and we are going up the river that Taharua may hear the news.” Then they asked, “Will Paoa and his party come up the river to-morrow?” And they answered, “Yes, in the morning, as soon as the tide makes and some food has been cooked for them to eat before they start; but we must pull on.” And the others answered, “Depart, then; pull well on your journey.”

And when the people at the village of Te Matai heard their paddles as they pulled up the river, they asked them just the same questions as they were asked at Rangiora; they then pulled on to the village of Te Mangarahi, and told the people there the very same news; and, in the same manner, as they passed the village of Tutu they told the news there. At last they landed at Opukeko, which was the fortified village of the chief Taharua. There also they asked them the news, saying, “What news have you brought, that you thus come pulling up the river by night?” And they answered, “We come to let you know that here is Paoa arrived at the village of Te Kari.” And they asked, “Is it really Paoa, or some of his people?” They replied, “It is really page 205 Paoa.” “When will he arrive?” They answered, “By and by; he will probably not be able to travel quickly. The people of the villages will try to detain him; for he is a stranger in these parts, and they will wish to entertain him.” Then the others asked them, “But which place is it that they are coming to visit, to stop there for some time as guests?” They answered them, “It is here they are coming—to this village; therefore it was that we came here, that you might be aware of their intention.” And the others replied, “It was very good of you.” Then they all slept.

The next morning Tukutuku arose very early, and employed herself in melting fragrant gums to perfume her house with. As for the visitors who were coming to stay with them, they continued their journey, and pulled up the river as far as the village at Rangiora; and there, as the people called to them with cries of “Welcome, welcome!” they landed, and remained for that day and night.

The next morning they again resumed their journey; and when they reached the village of Mangarahi a large number of people ran out to welcome them, and to beg them to stay there; and being thus invited by the inhabitants of that village, they landed and remained there. As for Paoa, he still would wear his old coarse cloak. And his companions said to him, “O, father! will you not throw off that old coarse thing? before much longer its stiff, rough collar will rub all the hair off the back of your head.” And he answered, “Never mind; it will do well enough.” In all respects he behaved in the same way in this village as he had done in the others they had rested at.

They slept there that night, and the next morning they again continued to pull up the river. And when they reached the village of Tutu, its inhabitants all shouted out to them with cries of welcome and invited them to come on shore. And the people all went down to the river to escort Paoa up to their village; and he stopped there, and passed the night at that village.

In the evening a messenger, who had been sent from Taharua's fortified village, reached Tutu. He had been sent there to see if page 206 Paoa had arrived so far upon his journey; and as none of them at Taharua's village knew him, as he was a stranger, the messenger had been directed to observe his appearance, so as to be able to point him out from his companions when they arrived, that they might all know which was Paoa. This messenger, having ascertained that Paoa and his party intended the next morning to pull up to the village of Taharua, returned there the same evening; and when he reached the village, he told them that the guests who were coming to visit them would arrive there on the morrow.

When Tukutuku heard this, she spoke to her servants, saying, “Now, my people, rise early in the morning, and gather leaves to strew the courtyard and the house for the strangers.” She had already prepared scents and fragrant gums to perfume the house with; and having now given these orders to her people, they all retired to rest.

But the next day, very early in the morning, Tukutuku arose, and went and gave the necessary directions for preparing abundance of food for the strangers, and then returning she smeared the inside of her house with perfumes and sweet-smelling gums; for it was her house which was to be allotted to the strangers on their arrival; and when she had thus perfumed it, she drew close the sliding-door and the window, that the perfume might not escape; so that the house might smell delightfully, and be agreeable to her guests when they arrived. She next caused the floor of the verandah in front of her house to be covered with clean fine mats for the strangers to sit upon.

The same morning the party who were coming to visit them continued their journey, and the people of the village of Tutu came with them, to escort them upon their way. As they pulled up the river, they were seen coming by the people of Taharua's village, who were collected upon the top of the parapets of the fortification to salute them with songs of welcome; then was heard the cheering joyful sound of the ancient Maori song of welcome for strangers.

On they came, pulling straight for the landing-place; and as they landed they were saluted with cries of “Welcome, welcome!” page 207 and they came on towards the village; and when Paoa rose up in the canoe to land, he put on the same coarse old mat made of the leaves of the Ti-tree. All the rest of his party were dressed in handsome cloaks; he alone wore an old, exceedingly shabby coarse cloak. His friends were all quite vexed with him, and asked him to throw off that shabby old thing; but he only replied, “That'll do; I'll keep this cloak on.” Although the rest were so well dressed, and Paoa so badly, yet those who had not seen him before had not long to look before they distinguished which was him, and said, “There! That's Paoa!” because his appearance was so much superior to that of the others; and yet they could not see his good garments, because they were covered by his coarse old cloak; and as for his hair, it was all rough and disordered, twisted up behind by the high collar of his old cloak, so that his hair all stuck up and his head looked quite shaggy. His friends felt quite discontented; for they said they wished him to look to advantage there, where he was a stranger. Thus they went along on the path to the village through the crowd which had collected to look at the strangers. At length they entered the village, and the court-yard which had been strewed with leaves for their reception; and those who were in front seated themselves in the verandah of the house which had been prepared for them. In the meantime Paoa followed on, the main part of the people thronging round him to look at him. When he came up to the house, he called out to his party, “Let us all go inside the house, and leave the outside vacant for these people to sit there.” Then those of his party who were in front went on, and some of them laying hold of the door of the house drew it back; and no sooner was the door opened than out issued a very delicious smell, the sweet scent of the perfume; and they all cried out, “Oh! oh! how very sweet the house smells!” But what did Paoa care for the sweet perfume? And although the house was so beautified, and although the floor of it was covered with such beautiful variegated mats that he ought for very shame to have thrown aside his coarse old cloak, nevertheless he would not take it off, but, as soon as he had got into the house, lay down in it, to sleep in it, just as he was.

page 208

No long time elapsed ere food was spread before the strangers; it consisted of eels and sweet potatoes. As for Paoa, he did not show himself outside the house, but ate his food inside it, and then lay down to sleep there again until evening, when the people of the village assembled to dance before the strangers; for amongst the natives of New Zealand the dances of the evening distinguish the village of a chief. When the ranks of the dancers were formed, Paoa came out into the verandah of the house, and seated himself there to look on, but he did not mingle with the dancers. When the people of the village had finished their dancing and singing, their visitors stood up to dance and sing in their turn; and at length they also ceased.

Then, when their guests retired into their house, after the dances were over, the principal inhabitants of the village all crowded into it also, to hear what took place; and there also came young Tuku-tuku, the daughter of Taharua, the chief of the place, and she went and seated herself in the dark corner at the farthest end of the house, whence she could watch Paoa without being seen. She often tried to draw near to Paoa, but from shyness she could not do so; and although she stayed in the house with the others, talking until the morning broke, she never once approached him.

In the early morning, food was prepared for the visitors; and as soon as it was spread before them, they ate their food. Two days they remained there; and for two days and nights Tukutuku tried to approach Paoa, but she could not overcome her shyness, and she came not near him. Upon the third day Paoa told his people that they must return to their own place, that he felt dull and tired from stopping so long. The inhabitants of the village heard of this his intention, and so did Tukutuku. So the young chieftainess came to try to detain the strangers; and having come, she said, “I hear you are about to return.” And her visitors answered her, “'Tis true.” And she said to them, “Do we not give you food enough, that you leave us so soon? Nay, stop a little longer; then presently you shall return to your own village.” And they replied, “Be it so.”

page 209

It was not yet evening when the servants of the young chieftainess appeared, bringing a feast for the strangers, and laid thousands of nicely dressed eels before them, so that her guests now, for the first time, were fully aware of her wealth and substance; and when night closed in, the dancers arranged themselves in ranks, and all the people of the village assembled, because the strangers were to start the next day; and they all continued for a long time to dance and sing, and at length ceased, and then they all assembled in the house of their guests. Then came the young chieftainess, Tukutuku, and seated herself at the door of the house. Paoa, too, was lying at the side of the house, next to the door; that was the place he had occupied ever since his arrival; for that seat in a house is always set apart for a chief, and no inferior person may occupy it. And it was not long before the young girl, according to the custom of her country, stretched out her hand, and taking Paoa's hand, pressed it. Of course the young girl had told her father and her mother of her love for Paoa, and they had given their consent to it; therefore it was that she stretched forth her hand to take Paoa's. But Paoa did not like this at all; for he feared, if he accepted her love, that he and his party might be slain by her tribe. He thought that her parents had not consented to her wishes. In the meantime the young girl again tried to take his hand; but Paoa rudely thrust her hand away.

Then also Paoa felt so vexed about her, that he ordered his people to stop the song and dance. So the people of the place all broke up, and went out from the house of the strangers, and returned to their own homes, and the young girl was forced to go with them. When she reached her father, she told him how she had put forth her hand to take Paoa's; and the old man said to her, “Did not he appear pleased at this sign of your love?” and she answered, “Alas! no.” Then her mother said to her, “Go back again, and try again, and take some of your female friends as witnesses with you, lest the man say that your anxiety to gain his love arises from your own wishes alone. He is doubtless afraid lest he and his people should be slain. He thinks undoubtedly page 210 that your father and I have not given out consent. Go, and do not be afraid.”

Then the young girl went, with four of her female friends, she making the fifth; and she seated herself for a time outside in the open air (for she felt herself abashed at Paoa having so rudely thrust her hand away), and she then told one of her companions to go and fetch him. When this female came to Paoa, she said to him, “Come along alone with me.” But Paoa answered, “Where to?” and she said, “Oh, just here. It is a young lady who sent me to you.” Paoa's young men, observing this, said, “Oh, we had better all go together.” But the female who had been sent to fetch Paoa said, “No, no; do you all stop here; do not come.” Then Paoa's people murmured amongst themselves, saying, “Who may this woman be?” and others of them answered, “Oh, it is one of the female friends of Tukutuku, whom we see always going about with her in the daytime.” And they answered them, “So it is; perhaps, then, Tukutuku sent her to fetch Paoa.”

In the meantime Paoa had gone off with the messenger. They went along together until they came to a house, in the verandah of which they found Tukutuku sitting with her female friends. The floor of the house was nicely covered with floor-mats, and the house was made to smell sweetly from sweet-scented Tawhiri leaves being scattered about it.

As soon as Tukutuku saw Paoa coming, she welcomed him by crying out, “Welcome, welcome!” As for him, he sat down at the door of the house, for he felt quite ashamed when he saw that there were only females there. But Tukutuku's friends called out to Paoa, “You are welcome; pray walk inside the house.”

So Paoa entered the house, and seated himself; as for Tukutuku, she and her friends were seated in the verandah. One side of the house was left for Paoa. The house was lighted with a lamp, made of twisted flax dipped in shark's oil; and one of Tukutuku's companions kept on trimming the lamp which she held.

When Tukutuku and her friends had entered the house, her companions said, “We will go now.” But Tukutuku stopped page 211 them, begging them to stay, saying, “Let us all pass the night here, until to-morrow's dawn has well broken.” They still, however, persisted in leaving her; but she still detained them; so they remained, and they let the lamp go out, and they all prepared to sleep.

Then Paoa said to Tukutuku, “Are you of noble birth?” And she answered him, “I am nobly born. There is no other great prince in these districts except my father.” Then he replied, “That is very good; as you say it, it is true, and pleases me.” Again he spoke to her, saying, “Is your nation a powerful nation?” And the young girl answered, “They are so. If you would see the greatness of my race, look as far as the mountains of Moehau [at Cape Colville]; they reach to there. Did you see them as you passed Rawhaki?” Paoa answered her, “Yes, I did see them.” And the young girl said again, “From thence my father's territories extend right round the Cape and along the coast to the eastward as far as Katikati; there they end, that is the limit.”

Paoa then spoke to her, saying, “As for me, I have no people over whom I rule, I am but a sojourner in the land; my own country is Whiapu [or the East Cape];” and then he related to her the manner and cause of his coming to that country, down to the time of his arriving at her village.

When the next day had well broken, Paoa arose and returned to his friends, and to the people who formed his retinue, and the young girl and her companions returned to her mother's house; and her companions spoke to her mother, saying, “Paoa came to our house.” And the old lady asked them, saying, “Who brought him there?” And they answered, “We did; our young mistress told us to bring him there!” And her mother answered, “It is well.”

Before long the news became spread abroad, that Paoa and Tukutuku were man and wife. Then a war-party, led by the young chiefs who would fain have had Tukutuku for their wife, came to molest Taharua, the father of the young girl, and to demand a payment from him, and they said they would also attack and rob Paoa and his people out of revenge; but Taharua page 212 stopped them, saying, “Let the war-party rob me alone; but do not go to our guests. What right have you to trouble men who have done no wrong?” In truth, the young girl was betrothed to no man; she avoided all her lovers, she did not like any of them; therefore the war-party molested Taharua without any just cause or reason. Yet that day many war parties came to molest and rob Taharua; and then they ceased, there was an end of them.

Finally those who accompanied Paoa paddled away to their homes again; but he remained with his young wife, with Tuku-tuku. When a month had expired, he said to her that he was anxious to return to his own village on the Piako. And the young wife answered, “So? Well, then, let us go together, and make our journey in such a manner that you may see all my subjects and all my relations, and that they may see me, lest they get vexed at my long tarrying away from them; for it is some time since I sent to them, saying, ‘I am about to come down the river to see you!’” Paoa replied to her, “Yes, yes; do let us go together.”

So they rested that night, and next morning, as soon as the sun rose, they got into their canoes and paddled down the river, and they landed at each one of the same villages which Paoa had stopped at when he came up the river, village for village, until they came out of the mouth of the river into the gulf; and by this time her subjects had given to their young chieftainess two large canoes full of baskets of shell-fish, which had been taken from their shells and then strung upon strings and dried in the sun. Thus Paoa saw how great was the esteem in which they held his young wife, so that he said, “Nothing could be better than his young wife for a great chieftainess for the country.”

Having quitted the river, they paddled on and landed at Tararu, and stopped there, and his young wife left there the presents of dried shell-fish which she had received, intending to take them on board the canoes again upon her return; and they slept that night at Tararu.

The next morning, when the sun arose, they again paddled on upon their journey, until they reached Te Puru, where they page 213 landed, and there a present of dried fish was made to them; and they returned the same day to Waiau.

There Paoa first tasted the mussels of Waiau, which place belonged to his wife; and he liked that place very much on account of the goodness of its mussels; then they continued their homeward journey from that place, and, as they returned, six canoes full of baskets of dried shell-fish were given to them; and when they again reached Tararu, they began to return up the river towards the Piako. When they arrived at Pareparenga, Tukutuku desired the people to give her a supply of fish, and they obeyed her orders; and Paoa was therefore much pleased with the people of Pareparenga, and said that his wife should indeed be a ruler over them. Thus she continued to act towards all the people that they met with upon their journey, until they reached Paoa's own village; they there presented him with a canoe full of dried fish; presents of dried eels had been made to them from place to place, as they pulled along the shore. And the people of Paoa's village were all charmed with Tukutuku; they all quite devoted themselves to her. She treated them most kindly, and they in return dealt very affectionately with her. And when all the provisions she had brought with her were consumed, from the liberal manner in which she shared them with Paoa's people, she, in no way daunted, began to work most industriously to collect new supplies, by digging up the roots of the whanake, and of the pohue, and of the karito, and by collecting aruhe and fresh-water mussels (unios). And when Paoa's people saw this, they exclaimed, “It is no wonder that the fame of this girl spread so far and wide; is not she truly industrious?” And when they saw their chieftainess labour so industriously, they for very shame began to labour also: hitherto they had not known the value of the above sorts of food; and partly from that cause, partly from their indolence, partly because those sorts of food were so common, they had not taken the trouble to collect them. But now they repeated the proverbs—“The deeds of a real chief surpass those of other men;” and, “The hard inside heart of a Tawa tree differs much, in the uses it can be applied to, from the soft page 214 outside sap of the tree;” and, “Well done! you are a chief of men indeed!”

The chieftainess dwelt there, and greatly increased the number of the new tribe she was collecting round her; many resorted to her; at first she had but very few dependants; but from her generosity and graciousness they now became many, so that her fortified village was thickly inhabited. And she had many children; for ten had been born to her. One of them was her renowned son, Horowhenua; he was the youngest, the last-born of her children.

Paoa dwelt there with her too: he had grown old, so that he was forced to support his steps with a staff. At last his affection for his first children broke forth; and he said to his sons who were with him, “My children, let me be taken to see your elder brothers.” They all assented to his wish but Horowhenua; and he said, “Sirs, they will set our sire a task to do; those children of his are a thoughtless set.” His brothers asked him, “What task will they give him to do?” And he answered them, “He is aged, and a sacred person, and they will detain him there, to bless their plantations of sweet potatoes for them, that they may bring forth abundantly; but take him there, as you seem to wish it.” But they said, “Nay, but rather let him go with twenty chosen men of our people to take care of him.” Horowhenua answered them, “'Tis well; then if our brethren detain him there, let those who go with him return here to us, that we may be certified by them that he is so detained; then will we go and bring him back here again.” His brothers answered him, “So be it.” Then he said to his father Paoa, “Sir, do not delay long there. If you had been younger, it would have been well that you should have been longer absent; but now that your days must be so few, we cannot afford to lose any of them: and as for this, also, remember that none would think it fitting that an aged man, as good as dead, should have a task appointed him to do.” And Paoa answered, “Oh, you don't think they will give me some task to do?” And Horowhenua replied, “They will give you a task. Who can believe they will treat you with the consideration that we do? page 215 But at least delay not long away from us; remain with them for ten days (that will be long enough) and then return to us. Certainly you should see your children.” Paoa answered, “'Tis well; I will sleep here this night, and as the morrow dawns I will depart upon my journey.”

So Paoa started to see his first family; and as they separated from their friends to go upon their road, Horowhenua said to those who were sent with the old man to take care of him, “If they detain him there who we commit to your charge, return here speedily, that we may all go and fetch him back with us;” and they answered him, “It shall be so.”

Then they continued their journey, and reached the top of the range at Tikitikimaurea; and Paoa beheld from thence his own former abode, and the abode of his children, and he wept; and as he gazed on the Waikato district, and saw the fires at the village of Waitawheta sending up columns of smoke, he told those who accompanied him that there was the dwelling-place of his children, and he wept again; and then they proceeded on their journey. And they halted for the night and slept upon the road, for they travelled slowly from having Paoa under their care; for he was old, and stayed his steps with a staff.

When the day broke, again they went on their way, and just as the evening closed in they reached the outskirts of the village; and as soon as the inhabitants of it saw them, they began to call out, to warn the others, “Strangers! strangers! here are strangers coming here.” And one ran to meet them to find out who they were, and he, finding out that it was Paoa, ran back again, and, being questioned as to who the strangers were by the crowd who had assembled at the outcry, he told them, “It is Paoa, and he has grown very aged, and supports his steps with a staff.”

As for Paoa, he stopped with his party at the first house which was inhabited that he came to on the outskirts of the village; but his sons remained in the fortress of Waitawheta, because this was the first time that the old chief had returned to see his children since he had separated himself from them and from their mother.

page 216

The next morning the old man took his belt to gird himself with, and said to those who accompanied them, “Now let us go to the fortified village, that I may see my children;” and they answered, “Be it so.” Then came those who had been appointed to conduct him to the village, and those who had been sent to bring him a present of food, that he and his people might be refreshed before the ceremonies of weeping and lamenting took place at his meeting his sons.

Paca bid those who had accompanied him to eat heartily of this food, and they did so; and when their meal was ended the messenger who had been sent to conduct them said, “Now let us proceed to their village;” and Paoa answered, “Certainly; so now, my friends, get on your backs again the loads which you have carried so far, and let us start.”

Then when those in the fortified village who had climbed up upon the fences, or crowded outside the gates, saw Paoa and his party coming along, they raised the usual cries of welcome, and waved their garments; and the old man wept aloud as he came slowly towards them. And so, he weeping and they loudly shouting “Welcome, welcome!” he came slowly on; and when he reached the open space in the centre of the fortified village, all the people wept aloud, and their voices sounded loud as howl a great company of dogs; and they continued thus to lament aloud throughout the day, until evening closed in; then they all collected in a semicircle, and seated themselves on the ground, and then arose the sons of Paoa and made speeches welcoming their father in the presence of the whole assembly, and the old man rose up and addressed his sons and all their people in their turn. Then were many flax baskets of food brought forth, and piled up to a very goodly height, and they all feasted until after night-fall. The principal people then assembled in the house which had been set apart for Paoa, that they might mutually hear and tell the news; and the hearts of the sons of Paoa were filled with gladness towards their aged sire; for they thought within themselves, “Surely he is come to bless our plantations of sweet potatoes for us, that they may produce abundantly.”

page 217

After a time his sons said to him, “Great is our good fortune, that you have thus come to us.” And he answered them, “Why so, my children?” And they answered him, “That you may bless for us our plantations of sweet potatoes.” And when the old man heard them say this he laughed; and his sons said to him, “Why laughest thou, O our father?” And he answered them, “Nay, I did but laugh.” But they answered him again, “Nay, but tell us wherefore thou didst laugh, O father.” And he replied, “It was but something your servant Horowhenua said.” And they answered him, “Whose saying do you speak of?” And he replied, “It was a direction given by your servant Horowhenua.” And they answered, “As for us, we regard not what he says.” But the old man said to them, “Look, now, my children; you had better be careful what you do, for he is strong and fierce.” But they answered him with the proverb, “Who fears for a fierceness not more terrible than that of a rat?” Again he said to them, “My children, his elder brothers said not a word against my coming here; he alone opposed my wishes, objecting to my coming here; he alone opposed my wishes, objecting to my coming here; he would hardly let me come.” And they said, “Very well, then, we will not now let you return to him.” But he answered, “Nay, do not detain me; for then your servant will come and take me forcibly away.” And they said, “Let him not venture to come here to take you away; for if he does, we will slay him.”

Those who had been sent to bear Paoa company sat by and heard these things said, and straightway they returned; and when they reached the Piako, even the village from which they had started, Horowhenua questioned them, saying, “Is there any news?” And they said, “Yes, there is news: Paoa is detained and will not be permitted to return here.” Horowhenua then asked, “Who detains him?” And they replied, “His sons.” And he said, “Aye, I knew it would be so.” Then they added, “But Paoa spoke to them and said, ‘Now, take care; for if you detain me here, your servant will presently come and take me away by force, he will not remain where he is, he will come for me;’ and your brothers said to him, ‘Who will come and do page 218 this?’ and he answered, ‘Horowhenua will come and do it;’ and they replied, ‘If he ventures to come here we will slay him;’ then Paoa answered him, ‘That you are not strong enough to do; your servant is like a mighty fish, which cannot be held in the fisher's net, but rends it;’ and they again replied, ‘Nay, rather we say, is a net so strong that it is a fit enemy for great whales?’”

When Horowhenua heard this he said, “Well, they shall have what they wish. I shall see them lying dead before me ere long.” Then he rose, and said aloud to those around him, “Gird yourselves for the battle, start for your journey to bring back our chief and father. Before he went, I cautioned you, saying, ‘Let him not go;’ it is you who have brought this upon us.” And his elder brothers dared not to open their mouths, or to say a word in reply, because they felt that their advice had turned out badly. So Horowhenua commanded them all, saying, “Gird yourselves for war.” And his brothers consenting, their warriors all did so, and proceeded on their expedition; one hundred and forty warriors started to bring home Paoa by force.

So they travelled upon their way, and by the evening they had reached the summit of the range at Tikitikimaurea, and looked over the district of Waikato; and there they could see the fires of the village of Waitawheta burning brightly with long columns of smoke ascending from them. There in the village was Paoa dwelling with his sons and six hundred of their warriors. When they had for some time gazed over the extensive district which lay beneath them Horowhenua said, “Let us descend from the mountain range, and sleep at its base, at the head of the river Mangawara.” Then they journeyed on, till they reached the place he had named. He said, “Halt! we will make our camp here; at the morning's light we will go to the fortified village of my brothers, and urge them to let our father return with us; and if his sons then refuse to let him go, it is enough, what more can we do? Then we will return; we can do no more; we shall at least have come to fetch him back with us.” His brothers assented to what he said, and they discussed the matter; and when they had page 219 ended their conversation, food was shared out for all; and when they had eaten, all slept.

They had not slept long when the seer Tipa cried out, and roused them, saying, “You who sleep there, awake, arise; I have been troubled by visions which bode ill; the omens have filled me with alarms: there will be a battle to-morrow in which many will be slain. The omens warned me, making me start on my right or fortunate side; and then on my left or enemies' side I felt it too. Then four times my left side shuddered, and then four times my right side; thence the victory is to be to us. So I will address myself to sleep again; then, if the spirit who is propitious to our foes repays the omens of the spirit friendly to us by making my left side again involuntarily to shudder, the omens will be unpropitious, and this very night we will return, in which case the battle upon the morrow, in which the gods foretell so many will fall, will not take place.”

Then another of the party spoke, and said that he, too, had shuddered in his sleep, and, starting, had thrown his arms out from his side as if striking down a foe, which was a good omen; on the other part, a third said that he had dreamt they were all eating the provisions they had brought with them—a dream which portended much evil. Before they had slept they had intended at the dawn of day to have gone to the fortified village as friendly visitors, and then to have tried to bring Paoa back with them. Now from these evil-boding dreams, they all feared the thoughts of approaching the village.

When it drew near to the morning, the seer Tipa rose again, and said, “Their gods have given me no bad omens in return for the good one I had received; I have kept expecting it in vain, but the dreadful shuddering has not returned to me. Lo, I see the signs of dawn; awake, arise, and let us arrange our plans.” Then the warriors all arose, and Tipa addressing them said, “Without doubt the old and sacred man has, according to the custom of our priests, gone out in the early morning light to bless the plantations of sweet potatoes belonging to his sons, which lie immediately outside the fence of their fortified village;” and the page 220 warriors all agreed that such was probably the case. Then said Tipa, “Which, then, of you will go and see?” And Horowhenua answered, “That be my care. I will go and see; and if I find him I will bring him here.” And Tipa answered, “'Tis well; and having got there, delay not.”

So Horowhenua rose up; and taking with him his two-handed wooden sword, he departed. At the very same time the old man had just arrived in the midst of the plantation of sweet potatoes, and was blessing them; and having blessed the division of the plantation which belonged to one of his sons, he had gone on to bless the other; and as soon as he had stuck into the ground his consecrated staff, he repeated this incantation, proper for the occasion:—

“There stands the consecrated staff;
It is the staff sacred to the God Turora, to Rereahi,
And to Turongo.
There is the holy staff;
There, there it stands.
There stands the staff,
With the toctoc* sacred to the God Haka
And to Haua.
There stands the holy staff;
There, there it stands.”

The instant the aged chief had finished his blessing, there stood Horowhenua before him. Day had not yet fully broken; but the dawn was just breaking. The old man, seeing some one, said, “Who is this?” And Horowhenua answered, “It is I.” And his father knew his voice, and he murmured lowly in reply, for he feared lest he should be slain by his other sons; for there were very many warriors in the fortified village—there were six hundred of them. Then his father asked him, “Who have borne you company?” And his son ran over all their names for him; and when he had finished them all, the old man was filled with pity for them, and with wonder at their boldness. Then Horowhenua said to him, “Let us begone, the day begins to break.” And his father consenting, they hurried away together.

page 221

In the meantime the people in the fortified village kept listening for the voice of the old man, when he might call them out, having finished his mystic ceremonies. And having waited a long time without hearing it, some of them said, “Surely he has become tired and has fallen asleep.” His sons answered, “Some of you go and see.” So some of their people went to search for him; and they called as they went, “Where are you, Sir, where are you, Sir?” At length, not finding him, some of them said, “Perhaps he has fallen asleep on the sand at the river's edge.” So they searched along the banks, and there they found on the sand foot-prints going right inland. By this time day had so fully broken that men could see each other's features; therefore the footprints could be seen quite plainly, and they saw that they were those of Horowhenua and Paoa; so they knew that the old man had been carried off by Horowhenua. So they raised the cry of “He has been carried off, taken away by Horowhenua.” And Paoa's sons heard the outcry, and they sprang to their feet, and they and their six hundred men rushed out of the fortress: so the fugitives were pursued. And when Horowhenua reached his brothers and his warriors, he gave no time to welcome their father and chief with tears and weeping according to the usual custom, but they went straight upon their way homewards, for they heard the uproar from the pursuers in the distance. And ere long the pursuers came in sight of them, and saw them winding up a steep ascent of the mountain range: those who were leading the old chief and helping him on his way were in front; and Horowhenua brought up the rear with the rear guard. On came the six hundred warriors in pursuit, dashing at them as a Kahawai (salmon) darts at a fly, and soon drew near them. Already had those who were in front, conducting Paoa, won the very summit of the ridge at Tikitikimaurea: then the old man said, “Children, leave me here, and save yourselves. I am an old man; why should you run this risk for me? My life is not worth that of one of my children.”

In the meantime their pursuers pressed close upon them. And Horowhenua rushed back in front of the rear guard, and then page 222 took a firm stand, brandishing his weapon. When Horowhenua thus stood firm, the whole hundred and forty warriors of his party took their stand with him; and then when Horowhenua made a charge to the rear, they all charged with him. Here some of his warriors were slain; five of them fell. At last Horowhenua was left fighting alone, right in the front of the battle; and his half-brother Toawhena seeing him there, strikes a blow at him with his weapon; Horowhenua parries it with his, and away it glances. Then Toawhena in his turn is fiercely smitten by Horowhenua; and down, down he goes. In the meantime up comes Toapoto to his brother's aid; he lets fly a blow at Horowhenua, which he parries on his right side, and returns a left-handed blow, which fells Toapoto to the earth. And when the warriors saw their two chiefs thus slain, they broke and fled in confusion, but they were pursued and slaughtered; four hundred of them were slain, two hundred of them escaped; and then Paoa was carried off in triumph by his children.

page 223page 224

* A species of reed, the leaves of which were tied on the staff.

Appendix No. 2

On New Zealand and Polynesian Ethnology

Sir George Grey read the following paper at a meeting held on 8th May, 1869, at the Museum of Practical Geology, London, Prof. Huxley, President, in the chair:—

XXII.—On the Social Life of the Ancient Inhabitants of New Zealand, and on the National Character it was likely to form. By Sir George Grey, K.C.B.

I propose this evening to try to show what was the nature of the social life of the ancient inhabitants of New Zealand, and what kind of national character it was likely to create.

In my attempt to do this, I shall make the New Zealanders themselves describe their social life; and for this purpose I will read portions of an historical legend which I have translated, which contains a clear and, I think, in many respects a not unpleasing picture of the life which the New Zealanders passed. By this mode of dealing with the subject, it is true, it will lose attractions which an argumentative and imaginative manner of treating it might have imparted to it; but, on the other hand, it will immeasurably again in reality. We shall be travelling in the paths of truth, not of fancy; for although the historical facts of the legend might be questioned (I think wrongly) by the sceptical, all those who knew the New Zealanders when first they came into contact with Europeans, will at once recognise and admit the truth and fidelity of the picture it contains of their social life.

With regard to the New Zealand legends generally, I have laid on the table, for the inspection of the Society, some books written by natives, showing the manner in which those natives who collected them for me wrote them down, and supplied them to me.

I have also laid upon the table a printed volume of many of the native legends in the Māori language, as also a printed volume of Māori poems; and I would especially call attention to a manuscript commentary upon this volume of poems, which a native, who had formerly been one of their priests, spent several years in writing. The labour he thus undertook was entirely a work of love on his part. He had never seen a European commentary on any work. The conception of such an elucidation of their ancient poetry and customs was an entirely original one on his part. I was absent from New Zealand when he entered on the task. On my return there, I accidentally heard of the existence of this commentary, and obtained it from the writer, who had then completed his elucidation of about one-half of the volume of poems which lies on the table; and he is now engaged in elucidating and explaining the latter half of the volume. The labour thus bestowed on these poems shows in what high estimation they are held by the natives.

The legend to which I am about to call your attention is the history of the Chief Paoa, the ancestor of the Natipaoa tribe, who inhabit the country lying on the rivers Piako and Waihou, now called the Thames, not far distant from Auckland. It is a simple narrative of everyday life, of which it is replete with minute descriptions. Could we now obtain such a record of our ancient British forefathers, such a document would be regarded as the most precious of our historical possessions. Yet there are strong grounds for believing that the social life of our British ancestors closely resembled that of the ancient New Zealanders, and that scenes not much differing from one another were in remote ages occurring on the Thames in England and the Thames in New Zealand.

I also feel confident that the legend I am about to submit to you will show that the social life of the New Zealanders was likely to form a national character distinguished for hospitality, courteousness, and courage—that it was likely to develop some heroic qualities, and to render it a matter of duty on the part of the chiefs to set their people a good example in all those occupations and pursuits which were esteemed amongst them. Altogether the life the New Zealanders led was not devoid of many graces and of many charms; under it as high a degree of happiness might be enjoyed as was possible in a country where a system of worship of false gods prevailed. It is probable that many races of men have, for a vast number of centuries, led a precisely similar life; and when one hears it described in their own simple language, it is easy to understand how many of them dreaded the evils and wants of civilization, and clung with desperate tenacity to a mode of life and manners which long custom and immemorial tradition had endeared to them. Hence has sprung much of that heroic and well nigh invincible resistance which mountaineers and imperfectly civilized or barbarous races have so often opposed to the occupation of their country by foreign and more civilized nations.

But what it especially becomes those to observe who contemplate the various vicissitudes to which the human race is subject in its march from degree of civilization to degree of civilization is this, that, in such a system of society as we shall have to consider, the entire wealth of a nation is upon the whole distributed with a great degree of equality. A fair degree of comfort, and an ample amount of subsistence are the property of all. There are no startling inequalities in dwelling, in clothing, in any of the conveniences that belong to man. All amusements are in common, the property of the chief subserves for the comfort and happiness of all; and although a chief be poor, if he sprang from truly illustrious ancestors, his poverty does not impair his princely power. When, therefore, a race which has lived for centuries in such a social state becomes, to a great extent, comparatively civilized, when its civilization has reached such a condition that those evils which are inseparably mingled with the blessings of civilization become apparent, when poverty oppresses a considerable portion of the population, when the unequal distribution of lands and of the general wealth is oppressively evident and want is endured by many, when mere wealth begins to give a power which previously belonged to rank and worth, and the chiefs feel their power fading from them, it is easy to conceive that a remembrance of the former state of society, preserved in such legends as the one I am to bring before you, would constantly be present in many minds, until a general yearning for benefits lost, and a too faint recollection of the ills with which those benefits were accompanied, would take general possession of a large portion of the public mind, and a revolt would take place against the new system which had recently sprung up, and a large party would endeavour at all risks and at all hazards to restore the state of affairs which prevailed in the time of their forefathers. In truth, such a revolt against innovations has almost invariably taken place under circumstances such as I have above stated; and too often such a revolt, instead of being attributed to its natural causes, has been ascribed to an absolute incapacity for civilization in the barbarous race, and has even been held to afford a legitimate plea in justification of its extermination, instead of which only that which was to have been anticipated had occurred, and a temporary difficulty had taken place, which was certain soon to be followed and checked by a natural reaction.[50]

I have alluded to the strong probability that the social state of our British ancestors in many respects closely resembled that of the New Zealanders. In the pride of rank, station, and power, nations, like individuals, are too apt to forget the humble origin from which they sprang. In our own case, we have but few materials for adequately realising the former state of the English nation. The notices we find scattered throughout the earliest missionary letters relating to the conversion of Britain are our best guides to its former social state, as documents of exactly the same character are our best guides in the present day as to the state of New Zealand when Christianity was introduced into this country.

However humbling it may be to our pride, we shall find that, when the Pope was a powerful, honoured, and benignant prince, and the city of Rome a civilized and beneficent power in the world, our own ancestors must have been in a state in many respects not very different from that of the New Zealanders when British missionaries established themselves in this country—that is, within a period which living men can well remember.

In the year 625, Pope Boniface thus concluded a letter which he sent through the missionaries to the glorious Edwin, king of the English: “We have moreover sent you the blessing of your Protector, the blessed Peter, Prince of the Apostles; that is, a shirt, with one gold ornament, and one garment of Ancyra, which we pray your Highness to accept with the same good will as is intended by us.” And to the queen of King Edwin Pope Boniface wrote thus: “To the glorious Lady his daughter, Queen Ethelberga, Boniface, Bishop, servant of the servants of God,” etc. And then, after giving the Christian queen the most admirable and touching advice, how, by the display of Christian graces, she should strive to win the unconverted king to the true faith, the Pope goes on to say: “We have moreover sent you the blessing of your Protector, St. Peter, the Prince of the Apostles; that is, a silver looking-glass and a gilt ivory comb, which we beg your Highness to accept with the same good will as it is known to be sent by us.”

It is difficult for us now, travelling back over the space of more than twelve hundred years, and all the varying phases of civilization which have passed in that time, to realise to ourselves the king of England sitting in one part of a kind of hut, awkwardly trying on so novel a garment as a shirt in the presence of his admiring chieftains, whilst in another corner sat our scantily clad queen, coyly aud shyly peeping at her royal face in a mirror, which her laughing maids of honour and her female attendants afterwards passed from one to the other with strange ejaculations of wonder and surprise.

Let me give one illustration more to show the almost grotesque fidelity with which, in somewhat corresponding stages of society, the same images are produced in races wide as the poles asunder. Taking up Caxton’s “Golden Legend,” published in 1483, and turning to the “Life of St. Patrick,” we find the following event recorded as having occurred in Ireland:—

“After it happed on a tyme that a man of that contre stole a shepe which bylonged to his neyghbour, where upon Saynt Patryke admonished the peple, that who somever had taken his shold delyuer it ageyn whythin seven dayes. When al the peple were assembled wythin the chyrche; and the man whiche had stolen it made no semblaunce to render or delyuer agayn thys shepe, thenne Saynt Patryke commanded by the virtu of God, that the shepe shold blete and crye in the belly of hym that had eten hit; and so happed it, that in the presence of all the peple the shepe cryed and bleted in the belly of hym that had stolen hit; and the man that was culpable repented hym of his trespace, and the other fro thenne forth on kepte them fro stelyng of shepe fro ony other man.”

If now we turn to the New Zealand legends, we shall find that a dog was stolen from a chief named Whakaturia, and eaten; that the dog was in vain sought for, and that all denied having been guilty of the theft. At last Whakaturia, accompanied by his relation, Tamatekapua, who was a renowned priest, entered the village where the thief resided, and the priest then, in the presence of all the people, called on the dog, commanding it to howl in the belly of the thief who had eaten it. The dog accordingly howled in the belly of a chief named Toi. In vain Toi held his mouth closely shut, pressing his hand over it. The dog continued to howl away till Toi cursed it, saying, “Oh! hush, hush! I thought I had hid you in the big belly of Toi; and there you are, you cursed thing, still howling away.” Thus the theft was discovered, the thief was punished, and an end put to dog-stealing.

You must pardon me delaying you whilst I say a few words which at the present time may be very useful to a race in whose welfare I have for many years taken the deepest interest.

I have called your attention to the period of revolt against the further encroachments of civilisation which invariably takes place, in some form or other, in the history of every barbarous race in its progress from barbarism to civilization. Now, such revolt, in most instances with which we are acquainted, takes at the same time the form of a revolt against Christianity, and culminates in an attempt to overthrow the Christian faith.

When such an event takes place, the cry is too generally raised, that truly barbarous races are incapable of receiving the truths of Christianity—that its pure doctrines were only intended for certain races which were capable of receiving them, of appreciating them, and of profiting by them; and, forgetful of all the teachings of history, men are too ready to conclude that a race is incapable of becoming a Christian nation, which, after years of acquaintance with Christianity, and after all the leading chiefs and the great bulk of the nation have apparently embraced the Christian religion, can suddenly renounce its truths, turn upon its Christian teachers, and expel them from amongst them, and set up a religion which mingles, in grotesque confusion, Christian and pagan rites and doctrines. Another reason is thus found for alleging that it is only in the extermination of such a race that we can look for the attainment of permanent peace, Christianity, and progress in the country which it inhabits.

Now, in truth, as Christianity and civilization have gone hand in hand, as those who were becoming civilized had generally accepted the Christian doctrines, as those who had remained barbarous had for the most part clung to their pagan faith, the revolt against civilization, involved in itself, as an almost necessary consequence, a revolt against Christianity.

That the occurrence of such a circumstance in the history of a semi-barbarous race need not fill us with despair, the history of our own country fully shows. No country has more thoroughly embraced and held by the Christian faith than Britain; no country has made greater efforts to spread a knowledge of Christian doctrines amongst mankind; no country has been benefited more largely by its steadfast adherence to the Christian faith. Yet no country in its early history afforded more astounding examples of such revolts against Christianity as I have alluded to; for example, such revolts took place in 616, 633, and 635, as well as at other periods. I will confine my observations to the first of them.

Ethelbert, King of the English, had, about the 597, embraced the Christian faith. Gregory was at that time the Pope; and he not only corresponded with King Ethelbert, but sent him also a few small presents, not, apparently, of such value as the shirt and woollen garment which Pope Boniface subsequently sent to King Edwin.

Ethelbert, after gloriously governing his kingdom for fifty-six years, died in 616, the Christian bishops expressing their full belief that so good and Christian a king had entered into the eternal joys of the kingdom which is heavenly.

Yet no sooner was King Ethelbert dead than such a revolt against Christianity as I have spoken of broke out; his son and successor, Eadbald, led astray by evil influences, and the popular wish, joined in it; a form of paganism was again firmly established, apparently much resembling in its general features the Hauhau faith, which has suddenly risen in New Zealand. Bishop Mellitus was driven out of the kingdom, and, a conference of Bishops having been held, it was unanimously agreed that it was better for them all to return to their own country, where they might serve God in freedom, than to continue without any advantage among those barbarians who had revolted from the faith.

Anyone who has watched the course of recent events in New Zealand, will see the remarkable parallelism between these events and the similar ones in Britain in AD 616. It only remains for us to remember that one faithful teacher lingered in Britain in 616 when all the others withdrew; and he was ultimately able to send over into France to his brother bishops, to tell them that their former flocks were returning to Christianity, and that they might safely come back to govern their churches, which they accordingly did, finding indeed how unwise and premature had been their conclusion that their teaching had been without any advantage among these barbarians who had revolted from the faith.

It was upon such successes as these Christian teachers enjoyed, and upon such revolts against Christianity as appalled them and staggered their imperfect faith, that was built up that glorious and widespread Christian freedom in the midst of which we are all assembled here tonight.

Mr. Lecky, in his recent most brilliant work on the History of Morals, has given his reasons for concluding that fairy tales are the normal product of a certain condition of the imagination, and that the belief in fairies will invariably be found to exist in companionship with a certain form of society—that is, wherever there is an ignorant and rustic population. This is an undoubted ruth in the case of the ignorant and rustic population of New Zealand, whose fairy tales closely resemble those of Europe: but it is only a partial truth; for it holds good of a belief not only in fairies but in dragons, and of all similar delusive beliefs which the human mind is capable of conceiving. The real law which governs this subject would seem to be, that the human imagination is only capable of much more restricted flights than we are in the habit of attributing to it, and that, whatever may be the race or people, the limits to which it can reach in each stage of civilization are soon attained, and that consequently, instead of having new images presented to our minds as we explore the poetry, legends, and works of imagination of newly-discovered races, we find the same beliefs recurring with an almost monotonous and tedious uniformity, and only so slightly varied as the features of the country and the kind of animals inhabiting it, or the circumstances of the society resident there render absolutely unavoidable.

In illustration of this I will quote one or two passages from Spenser’s “Faery Queen,” together with corresponding passages from New Zealand dragon legends. These quotations from Spenser contain descriptions of dragons so apparently natural, and expressed with such minute grandeur of language, that for two centuries and a half they have justly claimed the admiration of all who love English poetry and the English tongue; yet their strict verbal and poetical conformity with the corresponding New Zealand legends are such as at first to lead to the impression, either that Spenser must have stolen his images and language from the New Zealand poets, or that they must have acted unfairly by the English bard—the truth being that Spenser has simply recorded images which had their existence given to them long before his time, and in a certain state of civilization in England, and that under similar circumstances in New Zealand the human imagination, giving reins to its fancy, had, of very necessity, fallen upon exactly similar images.

These are some of the passages to which I allude:—

“Eftsoons that dreadful dragon they espied,
Where stretched he lay upon the sunny side,
Of a great hill, himself like a great hill.”

—Spenser.

“Hardly had Hotupuku (the dragon) scented a smell like the scent of men, ere he came creeping out of his den; the war party were still hidden by the slope of the hill and the bushes from him, and he from them. Before they saw him, alas! alas! he had stolen down upon them; and ere they could break and fly when they did see him, he was so large and near that he looked like a great hill!”

—New Zealand Legend.

“With that they heard a roaring hideous sound,
That all the air with terror filled wide,
And seemed un’neath to shake the stedfast ground;
Eftsoons that dreadful dragon they espied!”

—Spenser.

“Like the crashing and rumbling of thunder was the loud roaring sound made by the dragon in rushing forth from its den!”

—N. Z. Legend.

“But all so soon as he from far descryed
Those glistring arms, that heaven with light did fill,
He roused himself full blythe, and hastened them untill.”

—Spenser.

“The huge dragon when it saw its favourite food (the warriors) all ready, as it were a meal prepared for it, joyed exceedingly, and, opening wide its vast mouth, stretched forth its tongue to lick them in, and hastened out of its den.”

—N. Z. Legend.

“As for great joyaunce of his new-come guest,
Eftsoons he ’gan advance his haughty crest,
As chaffed boar his bristles doth uprear,
And shook his scales to battle ready dress’d.”

—Spenser.

“By the power of these prayers and incantations, the large-pointed spines of the crest of the dragon sank down flat again upon its back, although just now they had been all standing erect, as he joyed to think he should devour the men he smelt.”

—N. Z. Legend.

“But stings and sharpest steel—did far exceed
The sharpness of his cruel rending claws.”

“But his most hideous head to tell
My tongue does tremble.”

“And over all with brazen scales was armed;
His large long tail, wound up in hundred folds,
Does overspread his long brass-scaly back.”

—Spenser.

“It lay there in size large as a monstrous whale, in shape like a hideous lizard; for in its huge heads, its limbs, its tail, its scales, its tough skin, its sharp spines, yes, in all these it resembled a lizard.”

—N. Z. Legend.

“His blazing eyes, like two bright shining shields,
Did burn with wrath and sparkle living fire.”

“So flamed his eyes with rage and ravenous ire.”

“But far within, as in a hollow glade,
Those glaring lamps were set that made a dreadful shade.”

—Spenser.

“They soon saw the terrible monster crouching there, with its fierce large eyes, round and flaming as the full moon, as it shoots up above the horizon. Whilst they watched those eyes they seemed to flash with various colours; and from the sun’s bright rays playing through the green leafy places into the creature’s covert, its eyes seemed to shine with a fierce green, as if a clear green jadestone had been set for a pupil in the dark black part of each of its eyes.”

—N. Z. Legend.

Without pursuing this subject into many other similar details, I will add one other quotation from the “Faery Queen.”

“I wot not whether the revenging steel
Were hardened with that holy-water dew,
Wherein he fell, or sharper edge did feel,
Or his baptized hands now greater grew,
Or other secret virtue did ensue,
Else never could the force of fleshly arm,
Nor molten metal, in his blood embrue.”

—Spenser.

The New Zealand legends regarding dragons generally equally assert that it was only by some secret virtues, obtained by prayer or supernatural means, that their heroes were enabled to destroy dragons.

Endnotes

There is a beautiful poem on Rewi’s defence of Ōrākau in Mr. Bracken’s “Lays of the Land of the Māori and Moa.” The description of this noble defence there given is quite accurate. ↩

See Journal of an Expedition Overland from Auckland to Taranaki Auckland, 1851. P. 188. ↩

If a child was born before its time, and thus perished without having known the joys and pleasures of life, it was carefully buried with peculiar incantations and ceremonies; because if cast into the water, or carelessly thrown aside, it became a malicious being or spirit, actuated by a peculiar antipathy to the human race, who it spitefully persecuted, from having been itself deprived of happiness which they enjoyed. All their malicious deities had an origin of this kind. ↩

See Tennyson’s Idylls of the King, 1st ed., Guineve, p. 240:—

“For there was no man knew from whence he came;
But after tempest, when the long wave broke
All down the thundering shore of Bude and Ross,
There came a day still as heaven, and then
They found a naked child upon the sands
Of wild Dimdagil by the Cornish sea,”
And that was Arthur; and they fostered him.

↩

The manapau was a species of tree peculiar to the country from whence the people came, where the priests say it was known by that name. ↩

This quarrel of Māui with his brother-in-law, Irawaru, is sometimes narrated in this way:—

Māui and his brother-in-law had been paying a visit to the people of a village not very distant from where they lived; when they were about to return home again, Māui asked his brother-in-law to carry a little provision for them both upon their short journey, but Irawaru answered surlily, “What should I carry any provision for? Why I have just had an excellent meal.” They then started, and Māui, who was very angry, by his enchantments drew out the earth as they proceeded, so as to lengthen exceedingly the road they had to traverse; at last, being both overcome by hunger and fatigue, they sat down to rest, and Māui, who knew what his intentions were before they started, and had brought provisions with him, eat a good meal, but gave none to his brother-in-law. He then, to throw Irawaru off his guard, asked him to clean and dress his hair for him, and laid his head on his lap for that purpose; when his own was finished, he offered to do the same for Irawaru, who suspecting no harm laid his head on Māui’s lap, who threw him into an enchanted sleep, and then by his enchantments changed him into a dog. ↩

Inhabitants of New Zealand. ↩

The New Zealanders say that the “Kanae,” or salmon, had come on shore with the Ponaturi, and escaped out of the house by its power of leaping, gaining the water again by successive springs. ↩

According to some traditions her name was Hapai. ↩

The European reader cannot at all enter into the witty nature of this adventure in the estimation of a New Zealander. The idea of a sacred chief of high rank being by mistake treated as a common slave, conveys impressions to their minds of which we can form no accurate notion. ↩

Tāwhaki is said to still dwell in the skies, and is worshipped as a god, and thunder and lightning are said to be caused by his footsteps when he moves. ↩

See here. ↩

The part of the tradition which relates to the death of Kaitangata is considerably shortened in the translation, as not being likely to interest the European reader. ↩

New Zealand flax. ↩

Or pounamu, or greenstone, or jade. ↩

Obsidian, with which the natives grind down the jade. ↩

The people of New Zealand have another name for this whirlpool; they call it “the steep descent where the world ends.” ↩

Whangaparāoa, the bay of the sperm whale, so called from the whale found there. ↩

Kei Motiti koe e noho ana—“I suppose you are at Motiti, as you can find no firewood.” ↩

The fishing bank of Taikehu. ↩

Apteryx Australis. ↩

A sharp instrument of war. ↩

The discovery of a plot by guessing the meaning of a song which persons were overheard singing was a common circumstance with all the races and throughout all the islands of the Pacific; for instance, in Pitcairn’s Island, when first occupied by part of the crew of the “Bounty” and some Tahitian men and women we find:—“Brown and Christian were very intimate, and their two wives overheard one night Williams’s second wife sing a song, ‘Why should the Tahitian men sharpen their axes to cut off the Englishmen’s heads?’ The wives of Brown and Christian told their husbands what Williams’s second wife had been singing; when Christian heard of it, he went by himself with his gun to the house where all the Tahitian men were assembled; he pointed his gun at them, but it missed fire. Two of the natives ran away into the bush.”

—Pitcairn’s Island and the Islanders.

↩

They show several spots upon the east coast where Kupe touched with his canoes; but I have not yet had time to arrange and transcribe the various traditions connected with his landing at those places.

—G. G.

↩

It will be seen that they did not follow Kupe’s directions, thinking that he was deceiving them, he being probably friendly to Uenuku. ↩

Te Wherowhero, afterwards the first Māori King, related this story to me, but said he did not remember the whole song, and that this was the concluding verse; it was probably in allusion to their coming to peep at Te Kanawa. ↩

Jade or Nephrite, commonly called greenstone. ↩

The spring of Ōrangi is still well known to the Taranaki natives, as also the site of the pā near it. ↩

A species of reed, the leaves of which were tied on the staff. ↩

Cicero. ↩

Cicero, Orat. ↩

Ptolomaeus the Magian, Mr. Vincent’s paper in “Notices et Extraits des MSS.,” tom. xvi. Paris. ↩

Smith. ↩

Burney. ↩

“De poematum Cantu.” ↩

That the enharmonic has no foundation in nature is false, for what tree tapers “per saltum?”—what river flows in heaps?—this gradation is nature’s life stream; the other scales may be compared to the proportional parts, the enharmonic to the continuous procession. ↩

Lane’s “Modern Egypt.” ↩

Lay Tradescant’s “Chinese as they are.” ↩

“Notices et Extraits des MSS.,” tom xvi. ↩

“Mémoire de la Société Royale de Lille.” ↩

Περὶ Μουσικῆς. ↩

Burney, vol. i. ↩

As the soft diatonic, the hemiolion chromatic, the soft chromatic. ↩

Lay Tradescant’s “Chinese as they are.” ↩

Author of the Papers on the Rhythm of the Ancient Greek Orators, of the Psalms, Selah, the Evil Eye, read before the Royal Society of Literature; and of Papers on Accent and Quantity, discovering their true and real difference, from authentic sources. See “English Journal of Education,” February, March, April, June, July, and August: G. Bell, 186, Fleet Street, ↩

Grey, G. (Ed.). (1853). Ko ngā mōteatea, me ngā hakirara o ngā Māori. Page 30. ↩

Grey, G. (Ed.). (1853). Ko ngā mōteatea, me ngā hakirara o ngā Māori. Page 28. ↩

Grey, G. (Ed.). (1853). Ko ngā mōteatea, me ngā hakirara o ngā Māori. Page 47. ↩

Grey, G. (Ed.). (1853). Ko ngā mōteatea, me ngā hakirara o ngā Māori. Page 211. ↩

For the Legend of Pāoa see chapter 23. ↩